<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ted Laderas, PhD on Ted Laderas, PhD</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ted Laderas, PhD on Ted Laderas, PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Boundaries and Saying No</title>
      <link>/2020/10/14/setting-boundaries-and-saying-no/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/14/setting-boundaries-and-saying-no/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I hate saying no. But as I go on in life, I realize that I can&amp;rsquo;t be all things to all people. I want to help people, but I also have to have enough energy to get through the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to go through life doing what everyone expects of you and have nothing to show for it. In fact, this is often the &lt;a href=&#34;http://visionswell.com/self-care/what-is-the-curse-of-competence/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;curse of hyper-competent people&lt;/a&gt;. People tend to see you as a gear that fits within their own vision and expect you to do things for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to outline an approach that will make it easier to say no. It starts with understanding yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-your-values-who-are-you-fighting-for&#34;&gt;What are your values? Who are you fighting for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to say no, you have to have clarity on your values and goals. What do you see your life as?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of my values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make doing data science inclusive, accessible, and fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce people to data science who hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen it before&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce useful and applicable data science skills that learners can provide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teach others about lifelong learning and participate and foster learning communities in Data Science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An equally useful question to ask yourself is &lt;em&gt;who are you fighting for&lt;/em&gt;? In my case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Underrepresented Minorities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LGBTQ folks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Myself and my husband&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will say that as I get older, I have achieved greater clarity about what matters to me, and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter to me. This clarity helps me understand what is and what isn&amp;rsquo;t important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;don-t-respond-to-requests-right-away&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t respond to requests right away&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to add to your workload, I beg you to &lt;em&gt;not give an answer right away&lt;/em&gt;. You need to check in with your feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a boilerplate response if you need something to work off of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Thanks for thinking of me with this opportunity. However, I am extremely busy at the moment. I need to evaluate my current workload in order to tell you yes or no.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This buys you time to think and understand about how you feel about the request. Also, it gives you time to compose a thoughtful reply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ask-yourself-is-this-in-line-with-my-values-goals&#34;&gt;Ask Yourself: Is this in line with my values/goals?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a deep breath, and ask yourself how you feel about the request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it help further your goals or the people you&amp;rsquo;re fighting for? Will it upset your current work/life balance? Are you willing to pay that price?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer is no to all of these, then the answer is no. No matter how noble their goals, if they don&amp;rsquo;t fit with yours and your current workload, you should probably say no. You can leave the door open for future collaborations, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few times, it may be agonizing to do this. But consulting your feelings about something will become second nature to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gently-say-no-don-t-feel-sorry&#34;&gt;Gently Say No. Don&amp;rsquo;t Feel Sorry.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the thing: &lt;em&gt;it is way easier to say no when the request doesn&amp;rsquo;t align with your values or it doesn&amp;rsquo;t benefit who you&amp;rsquo;re fighting for&lt;/em&gt;. It gives your response much more force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may need to do a little verbal/email jujitsu here, because some people don&amp;rsquo;t hear no. Use absolutes for right now, but keep the door open if you see yourself possibly working together in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More boilerplate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I really appreciate you thinking of me. However, I cannot help with your effort at the moment. I am trying to maintain work/life balance, and this would upset that. [I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll consider me for future efforts.]&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to provide more personal reasons than the above, especially if the requestor is a stranger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;boundaries-keep-you-sane&#34;&gt;Boundaries Keep You Sane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying no doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel good. But the more you do it, the more you can achieve work/life balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t be everything to everyone, and you will end up dissappointing people. But you should feel okay about that, especially if their efforts are outside your own goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that I&amp;rsquo;m still learning how to do this. I&amp;rsquo;ve written this as much for myself as for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading&#34;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parts of this article are adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://microcosmpublishing.com/catalog/books/8188&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Unfuck Your Boundaries&lt;/a&gt; by Faith Harper. Her advice is no-nonsense, but it does require some soul searching to really utilize her advice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting LearnR tutorials to run on mybinder.org</title>
      <link>/2020/09/15/getting-learnr-tutorials-to-run-on-mybinder-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/15/getting-learnr-tutorials-to-run-on-mybinder-org/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; package is a wonderful way to package your tutorials. Anyone can download a &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; package of tutorials, and use &lt;code&gt;learnr::run_tutorial()&lt;/code&gt; to run them on their own personal system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; is based on &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt;, these tutorials can also be published to a &lt;code&gt;Shiny&lt;/code&gt; server such as &lt;code&gt;shinyapps.io&lt;/code&gt;. However, one drawback to this is that the more popular the tutorial, the more access time you may be on the hook for, which can rapidly become expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter mybinder.org, which is a way of running reproducible analyses and tutorials. In short, you give a mybinder.org server some information about the software environment needed to run your code, and you can run code based on your repo. Mybinder.org servers are a little limited, (1 Gb RAM), but this is more than capable of running most &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, they added Shiny as a deployable format, which means you can run shiny apps, including &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorial packages off their servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting a &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorial package called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderas/tidyowl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tidyowl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I decided to share what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-the-problem&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the problem?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are some differences between the file structure of a &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; package and the expected file structure of a shiny-ready mybinder.org repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we get both setups to work at the same time? Yes, we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-would-we-want-to-run-learnr-tutorials-off-mybinder-org&#34;&gt;Why would we want to run learnr tutorials off mybinder.org?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer is making your material accessible to as many people as possible. &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorials can be run from a phone or tablet, and running your tutorial for a lot of people doesn&amp;rsquo;t cost you any bandwidth or usage costs, as you&amp;rsquo;re using the same infrastructure that mybinder.org provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;quick-review-of-learnr-package-structure&#34;&gt;Quick Review of &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; package structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a package, &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorials are stored in the following folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;inst/tutorials/TUTORIAL_NAME&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you had a tutorial named &lt;code&gt;learning_shiny&lt;/code&gt; it would live in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;inst/tutorials/learning_shiny/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; file containing the tutorial should be named &lt;code&gt;learning_shiny.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem I encountered is that mybinder.org expects your tutorial to exist as a folder in the root of the repo. In other words, it needs to see&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;learning_shiny/&lt;/code&gt; in the root of the repository to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can fix this by adding a file called &lt;code&gt;postBuild&lt;/code&gt; that gives instructions to run after the software environment is built. We&amp;rsquo;ll use it to copy the tutorials into the root folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-your-tutorial-mybinder-org-ready&#34;&gt;Making your tutorial mybinder.org ready&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, you&amp;rsquo;ll need 3 files to make your &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorial mybinder.org ready: a &lt;code&gt;runtime.txt&lt;/code&gt;, a &lt;code&gt;install.R&lt;/code&gt;, and a &lt;code&gt;postBuild&lt;/code&gt; file in order to make your &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; package compatible with mybinder.org. Let&amp;rsquo;s go through the steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step 1. Specify a &lt;code&gt;runtime.txt&lt;/code&gt; file in your root folder. You&amp;rsquo;ll need a file called &lt;code&gt;runtime.txt&lt;/code&gt; that contains a single line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;r-3.6-2020-08-01
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives mybinder.org the signal that the Docker image needs to have R installed. You can see that I specified a version (3.6) and a snapshot date (2020-08-01). These should be a valid version and date for the snapshot - check the MRAN pages for more info: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mran.microsoft.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://mran.microsoft.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: When R 4.0 and greater is available in MRAN, you should move to it. It includes RStudio Package Manager, which installs the binary images rather than installing from source code which speeds up building the Docker images by quite a bit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another Note: I tried to get this to work with a &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt; using the &lt;code&gt;rocker/binder&lt;/code&gt; images, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get this image to work. If anyone has gotten this working, I&amp;rsquo;d appreciate you sharing how you did it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step 2. Specify package dependencies using &lt;code&gt;install.R&lt;/code&gt; in your root folder - in this file, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to specify all the packages your tutorial is dependent on using &lt;code&gt;install.packages()&lt;/code&gt; commands. Here&amp;rsquo;s the contents of my &lt;code&gt;install.R&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;learnr&amp;quot;)
install.packages(&amp;quot;here&amp;quot;)
install.packages(&amp;quot;tidyverse&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: getting the dependencies right in package building can be major headaches to getting your binder container to work. You may have to specify some &lt;a href=&#34;https://mybinder.readthedocs.io/en/latest/config_files.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;system dependencies&lt;/a&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;apt.txt&lt;/code&gt; file for certain packages. This information is available here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/r-system-requirements&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/r-system-requirements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step 3. Specify moving the tutorials in &lt;code&gt;inst/tutorials/&lt;/code&gt; to the repository root folder using the &lt;code&gt;postBuild&lt;/code&gt; folder. These commands are run after the container is built and will make the tutorials accessible via Binder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, for the &lt;code&gt;tidyowl&lt;/code&gt; package, I have these &lt;code&gt;mv&lt;/code&gt; commands in my &lt;code&gt;postBuild&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mv inst/tutorials/learning_tidyselect/ .
mv inst/tutorials/learning_rowwise/ .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll need a &lt;code&gt;mv&lt;/code&gt; line for each tutorial that your package contains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;note-using-holepunch&#34;&gt;Note: Using &lt;code&gt;holepunch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe you can also use &lt;code&gt;holepunch&lt;/code&gt; to make setup a little easier. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/karthik/holepunch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/karthik/holepunch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it yet, but will update this when I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-the-docker-image-for-your-tutorial&#34;&gt;Build the Docker Image for your tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, almost there! Now we&amp;rsquo;re going to go to &lt;code&gt;mybinder.org&lt;/code&gt; to build your Docker image. This is the software environment that your tutorial will run off of. This image will have shiny-server and RStudio installed on it automatically, which makes debugging your package easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re ready, go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://mybinder.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://mybinder.org&lt;/a&gt; and put in the public location of your repository. Then click the &amp;ldquo;Launch&amp;rdquo; button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now your container will build. Note that this will take a little while (10+ minutes), especially if you need to install something like &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;. Note that this can be one of the hardest steps to get going, especially if you need packages such as &lt;code&gt;sf&lt;/code&gt; (see above for a link to system dependencies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020-learnr/binder_repo.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it&amp;rsquo;s done building, you&amp;rsquo;ll be at a Jupyter page. Click &amp;ldquo;New &amp;gt;&amp;gt; RStudio&amp;rdquo; to open up your image with RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020-learnr/binder_open_rstudio.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see that your tutorial folders have been moved to the root folders. This is good confirmation that the &lt;code&gt;mv&lt;/code&gt; statements of &lt;code&gt;postBuild&lt;/code&gt; work. I personally like to have individual &lt;code&gt;data/&lt;/code&gt; folders in each tutorial, as it makes making them a little easier to deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test out running the tutorial by going to the .Rmd file and running it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020-learnr/binder_rstudio.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve setup everything right, you should see your &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorial popup. I will say that this is usually the fine tuning step that takes the longest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: there is a GitHub action (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jupyterhub/repo2docker-action&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jupyterhub/repo2docker-action&lt;/a&gt;) to rebuild your Docker image on new commits. I&amp;rsquo;ll be looking into this in the future.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;specify-the-url-for-running-your-tutorial&#34;&gt;Specify the URL for running your tutorial.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tutorial in your package will need its own URL to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll add the following to your mybinder.org link:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;?urlpath=shiny/learning_tidyselect/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;urlpath&lt;/code&gt; is a signal to mybinder that it will need to run shiny, and you&amp;rsquo;ll put the name of your tutorial folder instead of &lt;code&gt;learning_tidyselect&lt;/code&gt;. Note the trailing slash after &lt;code&gt;learning_tidyselect&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my final URL for the &lt;code&gt;learning_tidyselect&lt;/code&gt; tutorial is this (click it and try it out):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/laderast/tidyowl/master?urlpath=shiny/learning_tidyselect/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/laderast/tidyowl/master?urlpath=shiny/learning_tidyselect/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now send this link out and nearly anyone in the world can run your &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorial without installing R and not using up precious Shinyapps.io CPU time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;caveats&#34;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shiny apps may suddenly disconnect - have students reload the page if that happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images get deleted off the mybinder.org servers within a week, so it is worth automating your container build to do so every week so that your students don&amp;rsquo;t have to wait for your container image to rebuild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, progress is not saved, because the final url is different each time you run it off mybinder.org servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks so much to the &lt;code&gt;mybinder.org&lt;/code&gt; team, what they do is beyond awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Sang Yun Oh, whose repository helped me figure more of these details out. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/syoh/learnr-tutorial&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/syoh/learnr-tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on the RStudio Instructor Training Experience</title>
      <link>/2019/11/15/my-experience-with-rstudio-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/15/my-experience-with-rstudio-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full Disclosure: my department paid for the training and two of the certification exams. I did the Shiny exam for free with the stipulation that I would provide feedback on the exam itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently became a &lt;a href=&#34;https://education.rstudio.com/trainers/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;certified RStudio Instructor in both Shiny and the Tidyverse&lt;/a&gt;. I thought I would write a little about the experience. I haven’t really had any formal pedagogical training, and having some of the state of the art and evidence-based practices were really helpful in extending my approaches to teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instructor-training&#34;&gt;Instructor Training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The instructor training is online, but delivered via Zoom. The session themselves are 4 hours apiece and at set times, with a small cohort overall (I think mine was about 14). Greg Wilson delivered a short set of slides for each activity, and depending on the activity, we were sent out into smaller groups to discuss the topic. I liked how the course was paced - I felt like having activities almost every half hour definitely kept me awake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training for me (I am on PST) was from 8 AM to 12 PM two days in a row, and my cohort was from all over the US/Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the parts of the instructor training that I found especially useful. Note that since Greg also helped develop the Carpentries instructor training, there is some overlap between the two training programs (in fact, if you’ve taught a Carpentries course and done the Carpentries training, you can waive the instructor training altogether).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building concept maps&lt;/strong&gt;. If you can, you should map out the concepts you want to teach, along with how these concepts are related. This concept map is important in helping your students build the mental models that will guide them towards mastery.  I did a concept map of Tidy data for my example. Concept maps themselves are a bit tricky to build, but I think they help clarify your understanding of what you are teaching, and thus your lessons will be more understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thinking about cognitive overload.&lt;/strong&gt; This was a call to think about limiting the number of concepts and connections covered per unit. Humans have a short term memory of about 5 +/- 2 things at a time. This is an extremely helpful guideline to consider when developing training units, as your course objectives and training should keep these in mind. Also, there are different kinds of cognitive overload, and some of them (like extraneous details), you can remove to help with the other kinds. There are lots of ways to teach coding, such as Parsons Problems (where students have to put lines of code in order), or faded examples (fill in the blank style coding assignments), that can focus on particular aspects of coding. (As an unrelated topic, I have been thinking about reading code as being an essential skill and I try to teach students to learn how to read code.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching needs to be dynamic.&lt;/strong&gt; As instructors, part of our value lies in tailoring our training for our students and their previous knowledge. Unlike YouTube videos, we can assess what our students already know, and focus on the concepts that they don’t. In order to do this, though, we need to have ways of assessing what our students know. Formative assessments (assessments during a lesson) are essential in figuring out whether you can proceed, or whether you need to spend more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Providing feedback.&lt;/strong&gt; We were to teach each other a short lesson of our choosing, which was pretty fun. After a test run with a larger group, my partner and I got to teach each other - she taught me about making jam (and the food safety issues) and I taught her about making cornbread. (It was close to lunchtime when we did this, I think we were both hungry.) The exercise was super useful in helping us to not be afraid of giving feedback and to be aware of what kinds of feedback to give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What demotivates students.&lt;/strong&gt; This was an important section, and a bit emotionally difficult. I have been guilty of some of the teaching behavior that demotivates students, such as taking over their keyboard, instead of letting them fix it. If we are to be inclusive and welcoming to everyone, we need to be aware of these (sometimes subtle) behaviors that can discourage and demotivate all of our students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other tips from other instructors&lt;/strong&gt;. I really enjoyed hearing other instructor’s experiences and I had a lot of respect for my cohort. There were lots of little tips we shared with each other that were super helpful, such as the types of mics to use. I also thought that it was helpful when we shared our struggles with each other. It made me feel much more as part of a group of instructors, which was very helpful for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instructor-certification-exam&#34;&gt;Instructor Certification Exam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The instructor certification covered the pedagogical techniques we discussed in the instructor training. This exam, like the others, was open book, open note, open internet, but not open person (no lifeline, no talking with others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the exam, we were required to develop and deliver a lesson. I ended up reworking one of my SQL lessons in my Analytics course. I found it a really useful exercise in rethinking my examples discussing left and inner joins, especially in my table examples. You can see my lesson here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.cloud/project/413048&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SQL Joins in R&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part of the exam is only about 10 minutes long, but you should be prepared, especially in figuring out how you will assess the learning of the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tidyverse-certification-exam&#34;&gt;Tidyverse Certification Exam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I had done my instructor certification, I had to do the technical qualifications. This was also done online, with Greg delivering the exam over Zoom. Most of the exam had to be done via RStudio on my computer.  This exam, like the others, was open book, open note, open internet, but not open person (no lifeline, no talking with others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did the exam cover? Roughly, it covered almost all of &lt;a href=&#34;https://r4ds.had.co.nz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R for Data Science&lt;/a&gt; and was very task-focused. There was a focus on debugging, data transformation, markdown and visualization. The tasks were mostly problem driven, on the order of recreating a figure, or parametrizing a workflow. It was emphasized that we should solve the problems the way we  usually work and talk out our problems aloud. For one of the problems, I actually had to search and teach myself on the fly. This was actually a good way to confirm that my conceptual models of the tidyverse were helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One tip: 90 minutes is a long amount of time for an exam, especially where you are actively thinking and talking out loud. You should have something to eat by your side so you can replenish your blood glucose. It is also slightly unnerving to have someone watch you actively solve problems and program. If you get flustered, take a breath. There’s not usually a single way to solve the problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;shiny-certification-exam&#34;&gt;Shiny Certification Exam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later, I took the Shiny certification. In terms of coverage, there is not currently a good text to study for the Shiny Certification exam (&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastering-shiny.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mastering Shiny&lt;/a&gt; is probably going to be the reference to study when it is finished).  In order to prepare, I went over the &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RStudio articles about Shiny&lt;/a&gt;, and looked over the &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com/gallery/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RStudio Shiny Gallery&lt;/a&gt; to bone up on the different programming techniques used in Shiny, such as UI elements, reactives, the observe/update pattern, and modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the exam covered debugging, including fixing applications, understanding control logic between ui and server, and building an app from scratch. I would say much of the exam covers how well established your own mental model of Shiny progamming is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember: as the technology and code changes,  the certification exams will change and you may have to get re-certified. So my experience of these exams may be different than your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would I recommend the training? I thought it was extremely useful, especially in terms of learning more about evidence based methods in effective education. As someone who is thinking about starting a consulting group focusing on training, having the certifications are extremely valuable to me and my future career. I look forward to teaching and training more people in R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-more-info&#34;&gt;For More Info&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please consult the &lt;a href=&#34;https://education.rstudio.com/trainers/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RStudio Trainer Website&lt;/a&gt; for info on how to register for the instructor training.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kindness at the Cost of Yourself</title>
      <link>/2019/09/23/kindness-at-the-cost-of-yourself/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/23/kindness-at-the-cost-of-yourself/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In healthy cultures, people rise by elevating others and fall by undermining others. In toxic cultures, people are forced to choose between helping others and achieving success. Choose the workplace where success comes from making others successful. - Adam Grant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read Adam Grant’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.adamgrant.net/give-and-take&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Give and Take&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it was like a light went off. In this book, Grant gives profiles of highly successful people who are givers - people who have changed their field by making things better for others. I immediately connected to this idea of giving. Here was a way to network with people that really worked for me. Giving and connecting people are what I do best. I like to help people achieve their goals if I know someone else who can help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And no doubt, embracing my identity as a giver has helped change my career trajectory - in the last few years, I co-founded &lt;a href=&#34;http://cascadiarconf.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cascadia R&lt;/a&gt;, produced the &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-bootcamp.netlify.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R-Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; with Jessica Minnier, and have met so many people in the field of education and open science that I want to work with and who have inspired me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as I’ve noted before, I tend to be giving to the point of being self sacrificing, which is not good. I’m reminded of the end of Kafka’s &lt;em&gt;Metamorphosis&lt;/em&gt; when (spoilers) as Gregor Samsa dies in his bug form. As he dies, he worries about the agency of his family. Will they be able to support themselves? In the end, the family that he was worried about finds jobs, support themselves and thrive in the end. Without him. One interpretation of this story: &lt;em&gt;no one is so irreplaceable in this world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Spring, I probably gave a little too much to my Health Analytics class, to the point of being self-sacrificing. This shouldn’t be a reflection of the class - they were great and really whip smart - I just tend to give a little too much. As a result, I was pretty drained by the time I got to Summer quarter. I’d definitely overdrawn on giving - I was pretty wiped out through the summer. Being overdrawn actually meant I didn’t have enough energy to teach as well as I would have liked - and I felt worse for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson I&amp;rsquo;ve learned this summer: If you find yourself giving to the point of self-sacrifice, you need to ask yourself why you are sacrificing so much of yourself. Excessive self-sacrifice seems to occur when your &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spsp.org/news-center/press-releases/relationship-sacrifice&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;self-esteem is tied to the perception of yourself by other people&lt;/a&gt;. Meaning, you should question &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you are self-sacrificing. Is it because you feel like you need the approval of others? No one&amp;rsquo;s approval is worth overworking yourself over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, self-sacrifice is ultimately bullshit. Ironically, being self-sacrificing can lead to &lt;a href=&#34;https://greatergood.berkeley.edu/article/item/when_are_you_sacrificing_too_much_in_your_relationship&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;feelings of helplessness and resentment&lt;/a&gt; from the people you are sacrificing yourself for.  Additionally, being &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2019/08/when-to-take-initiative-at-work-and-when-not-to?&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;highly proactive and championing change can actually have negative effects&lt;/a&gt; if your actions are perceived as a threat to your organizational culture. There’s a reason why change management is important. No one person can be a revolution - it takes others to do so. It shouldn’t fall to just being on you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to take care of yourself and protect yourself from the takers. As Faith Harper writes in &lt;a href=&#34;https://microcosmpublishing.com/catalog/books/6860&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Unf#ck Your Adulting&lt;/a&gt;, “taking care of yourself does the world a favor”. Taking care of yourself means that you can do good in the world sustainably, and continue to do it, rather than burning out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understand that the notion of true giving is not rooted in self-sacrifice. &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@janfortune/how-to-be-a-giver-not-a-sacrificer-a55bf354fcf7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Giving is in the spirit of generosity&lt;/a&gt;; in contrast, self-sacrifice is more akin depleting one’s own resources. As a giver, your generosity should be recognized and not exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to be aware of as a giver is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kqed.org/arts/13857471/artist-passion-exploitation-duke-study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;passion exploitation&lt;/a&gt;, where people and organizations will take advantage of you because of your passion for a subject as an opportunity to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fuqua.duke.edu/duke-fuqua-insights/kay-passion-exploitation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pay you much less than you’re worth&lt;/a&gt;.  Such an attitude is prevalent in creative industries, where one is encouraged to work for free or “exposure” (I don’t really do soundtrack work any more because of this). As if being a poor artist or creative was a privilege. Such situations will drain your passion and your energy and burn you out with nothing to show for it. Again, you have to keep something for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to continue to do good in the world, you must take care of yourself. This is especially the case in a toxic work culture. You have to build reserves - never give more of yourself than you can. Especially do not do this in a work setting. It is amazing how self-sacrifice can become the status-quo and what is expected of workers. No one is well off because of that. Toxic work cultures encourage this: &lt;a href=&#34;https://kotaku.com/crunch-time-why-game-developers-work-such-insane-hours-1704744577&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;crunch time as the norm at game studios&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/3b5e7k/the-japanese-are-dying-for-work&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;overwork at Japanese Black Companies&lt;/a&gt;, even in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bloomerang.co/blog/7-ways-to-prevent-passion-exploitation-at-your-nonprofit/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;non-profit sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I believe in kindness and giving. But the kindness and giving must be sustainable. You must defend yourself from those who would take more than they give, and avoid being exploited by those who see your passion as something exploitable. Identifying these people and organizations and saying no is key to taking care of yourself while making things better for others. Don’t feel guilty about this. Don’t make self-sacrifice part of your identity or job description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.adamgrant.net/give-and-take&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Give and Take&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - this is the book that opened my eyes to the power of being a social giver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://microcosmpublishing.com/catalog/books/6860&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unfuck Your Adulting&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - this book by Faith Harper is full of good advice about navigating situations, emotions, and taking responsibility for what you can take responsibility for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@janfortune/how-to-be-a-giver-not-a-sacrificer-a55bf354fcf7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to be a giver, not a self-sacrificer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - talks about giving in the spirit of generosity, and not self-sacrifice. Again, keep something for yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2019/08/when-to-take-initiative-at-work-and-when-not-to?&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;When to take initiative at work, and when not to&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wonderscounseling.com/burnout/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avoiding Burnout: Tips for self-care&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  - again, very good tips on taking care of yourself, because no one else will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Burning Out and Recovering (slowly)</title>
      <link>/2019/07/03/burning-out-and-recovering-slowly/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/03/burning-out-and-recovering-slowly/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last year about this time, &lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/2018/06/05/self-care-and-self-compassion-in-academia/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;I had a meltdown&lt;/a&gt;, which is a symptom of burnout. I&amp;rsquo;d like to explain a little bit about my burnout in the hopes that other people can avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to help people, and I’m a people pleaser. I’m a giver, and sometimes I give too much, to the point I have nothing left. I have to be aware when people exploit this. One collaboration, unfortunately took advantage of my giving nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was on a contracted project where I used some of the time to build an open source project to enable our research. With our collaborators, I showed them my work and they seemed excited. Unfortunately, this “excitement” turned into unreasonable demands. I was literally trying to do a full time development position while balancing the demands of other projects, including teaching. I started feeling like a machine, where each of my collaborators just wanted me to output figures and analyses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst I’ve ever felt is when I have been busting my ass for things I don’t believe in, or have been stretched across too many projects. Unlike a lot of faculty at OHSU, I don’t have my own R01. I am a collaborator, and I work hard at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wake-up call for me was persistent thoughts of suicide. I realized that I didn&amp;rsquo;t care that much about anything and I knew that things had to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;regaining-balance&#34;&gt;Regaining Balance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year has been about finding my way back. I’ve been trying to do the following to regain my balance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Working 4 days/week instead of the usual 5&lt;/em&gt;. On my “day off”, I try my best to contribute to open source projects, work on music, and do other things that recharge me. This has enabled me to say no more often.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Understanding my values and restructuring my work to fit it&lt;/em&gt;. I’m much more focused on education, outreach, and mentoring these days. If a project comes up, I have to ask myself whether it is in line with my values. I&amp;rsquo;d like my research to include educational and data exploration components, such as Shiny.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not putting all my eggs in the work basket&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m an artist in addition to being a data scientist. I play the cello, compose, and do photography. I make more time for these.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Realizing that excellence does not require self sacrifice&lt;/em&gt;. I try to stop working on things obsessively, and only within the time I&amp;rsquo;m paid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mindfulness work&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve been using the Calm app to help me reorient me and not immediately react to adversities I encounter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Giving up on perfection&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m learning to slowly abandon perfection on projects I don&amp;rsquo;t care that much about (more on this later), and instead turn my alerts off, or only respond to them within sane business hours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;am-i-recovered&#34;&gt;Am I Recovered?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to say I’m fully recovered, but I’m not. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I&amp;rsquo;ll ever be 100% recovered, if recovered means the insane productivity levels I was showing before. I have been slowly asking myself whether projects expect insane levels of work for the amount of time I can dedicate to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, I have had really great support from my department and from the university overall throughout. I have had support from the communities I help manage (BioData Club and Portland R User Group), and all the great people involved in open science that I have met (rOpenSci, Mozilla, The Carpentries).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that this support has been wonderful, and I feel like the journey back from research burnout has been ongoing. I wish there was a magic bullet for burnout, but working one&amp;rsquo;s way out of mental and emotional exhaustion ultimately takes a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are burned out, please seek &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nami.org/Find-Support/NAMI-HelpLine&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mental health assistance&lt;/a&gt; if you need help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/high-octane-women/201311/the-tell-tale-signs-burnout-do-you-have-them&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Telltale Signs of Burnout&lt;/a&gt; - How to recognize when you&amp;rsquo;re burned out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/burnout/art-20046642&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mayo Clinic on Burnout&lt;/a&gt; - More information on Burnout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.workplacestrategiesformentalhealth.com/managing-workplace-issues/burnout-response&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Responding to Burnout&lt;/a&gt;. How can we recognize burnout in others?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/podcasts/worklife&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;WorkLife Podcast&lt;/a&gt; - This podcast by Adam Grant (organizational psychologist) has been full of ideas on how to make what I work on more meaningful. Highly recommended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Bootcamp</title>
      <link>/teaching/r-bootcamp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/r-bootcamp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Package Building: How `DESCRIPTION`, `NAMESPACE`, `roxygen`, and `devtools::document` work together</title>
      <link>/2019/02/12/package-building-description-namespace/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/12/package-building-description-namespace/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;As part of my new year&amp;rsquo;s resolution to learn new things about R, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to plug some holes in my R knowledge by writing more vignettes to explain them to myself this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I finally think I understand more about namespaces in R and why you should use them in your R package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;namespaces-why-bother&#34;&gt;Namespaces: Why Bother?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, we need namespaces because of the &lt;em&gt;ambiguity&lt;/em&gt; of function names. Think of how many packages have a &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt; function! How does R know which function from which package you’re talking about? One nightmare case is the Bioconductor &lt;code&gt;exprs()&lt;/code&gt; method and the &lt;code&gt;rlang&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;exprs()&lt;/code&gt; function. These functions do very, very different things (one of them extracts an expression matrix from a Bioconductor &lt;code&gt;ExpressionSet&lt;/code&gt;, and the other one is used for quoting multiple expressions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when you call &lt;code&gt;library&lt;/code&gt; on both of these packages? The worst case scenario is that you mean to call one package function and R executes the other one. This is called a namespace collision, and unfortunately it can break your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the namespace, which allows us to be package and function specific. If I want to use the function &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;, I write it as &lt;code&gt;dplyr::filter&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;dplyr::&lt;/code&gt; part is the namespace of the &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description-the-gatekeeper-for-calling-packages&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt;: The gatekeeper for calling packages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file is one of the gatekeepers in your package. Ever wonder how &lt;code&gt;install.packages&lt;/code&gt; knows how to install the packages your package depends on? It’s actually because of a field in the &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file. Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file for my &lt;code&gt;burro&lt;/code&gt; package:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Package: burro
Type: Package
Title: Shiny App Package for setting up a data exploration session (&amp;quot;burro&amp;quot;w into the data)
Version: 0.1.0
Authors@R: as.person(c(
    &amp;quot;Ted Laderas &amp;lt;tedladeras@gmail.com&amp;gt; [aut, cre]&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;Jessica Minnier &amp;lt;minnier@ohsu.edu&amp;gt; [ctb]&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;Gabrielle Choonoo &amp;lt;choonoo@ohsu.edu&amp;gt; [ctb]&amp;quot;
  ))
Maintainer: Ted Laderas &amp;lt;ted.laderas@gmail.com&amp;gt;
Description: Allows the teacher to deploy a simple data exploration app for exploring a dataset (mostly for teaching purposes).
License: MIT LICENSE
Encoding: UTF-8
LazyData: true
Imports:
    dplyr,
    shinydashboard,
    ggplot2,
    visdat,
    skimr,
    naniar,
    data.table,
    magrittr,
    glue,
    usethis,
    here,
    viridis,
    DT
Depends:
    shiny
Roxygen: list(markdown = TRUE)
RoxygenNote: 6.1.0
Suggests:
    testthat
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the &lt;code&gt;Imports:&lt;/code&gt; field. You can see a list of all of the packages that &lt;code&gt;burro&lt;/code&gt; utilizes. In ye olde days of R, we used the &lt;code&gt;Depends:&lt;/code&gt; field. Nowadays we use the &lt;code&gt;Imports:&lt;/code&gt; fields. &lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/8637993/better-explanation-of-when-to-use-imports-depends&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a Stack Overflow post explaining why&lt;/a&gt;. The main reason is that &lt;code&gt;Imports:&lt;/code&gt; requires the package to have a namespace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modifying the &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file by hand is possible, but I don’t recommend it. Instead, you can use the &lt;code&gt;usethis&lt;/code&gt; package to modify it. For example, if I want to use &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; in my package I can do this in the console, while I am building it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_package(&amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will add &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;Imports:&lt;/code&gt; field of your &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Addition (Thanks Hao Ye, for the suggestion)&lt;/strong&gt;: If the function is in a development version (i.e., hosted on GitHub), you can use &lt;code&gt;usethis::use_dev_package()&lt;/code&gt; to add it to your &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file. It will add an additional field called &lt;code&gt;Remotes:&lt;/code&gt; to your package:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;usethis::use_dev_package(&amp;quot;tidyverse/dplyr&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more info about using remotes, check out the vignette: &lt;a href=&#34;https://remotes.r-lib.org/articles/dependencies.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://remotes.r-lib.org/articles/dependencies.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-namespaces-to-call-functions-from-other-packages&#34;&gt;Using namespaces to call functions from other packages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have specified the package in our DESCRIPTION file, we can now call any function in &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; by adding a &lt;code&gt;dplyr::&lt;/code&gt; before the function. So if we wanted to call &lt;code&gt;mutate()&lt;/code&gt; in our package function we can do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mutate_iris &amp;lt;- function(iris){
    dplyr::mutate(iris, sepal_sum = Sepal.Length + Sepal.Width)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases, calling a function by specifying its namespace is good practice. For one, there are many functions called &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt;: I can think of at least the ones that are in &lt;code&gt;base&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;. Using the namespace makes it &lt;em&gt;unambiguous&lt;/em&gt; to both R and other developers which &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt; function you&amp;rsquo;re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-i-call-functions-from-other-packages-using-roxygen-docstrings&#34;&gt;How do I call functions from other packages? Using &lt;code&gt;roxygen&lt;/code&gt; docstrings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugh, I&amp;rsquo;ve already written a bunch of code and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to add the namespaces before all of the functions from other packages! How can I avoid this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;code&gt;roxygen&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt; come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;roxygen&lt;/code&gt; docstrings are responsible for at least three things in your package: 1) producing the documentation (&lt;code&gt;.Rd&lt;/code&gt;) files, but also: 2) specifying what package namespaces you want to utilize, or import in your function, and 3) whether you want to export that function (i.e., make it accessible publicly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do they accomplish 2)? When you call &lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt; to build the documentation, they scan for multiple fields, such as &lt;code&gt;@import&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;@importFrom&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;roxygen&lt;/code&gt; doc strings. Then &lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt; actually modifies the &lt;code&gt;NAMESPACE&lt;/code&gt; file in your package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-importfrom-when-you-only-need-one-function&#34;&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;@importFrom&lt;/code&gt;: When you only need one function&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you just wanted to use &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;, but didn&amp;rsquo;t want to write &lt;code&gt;dplyr::filter&lt;/code&gt; before all of your functions. You can just import the &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt; function by including the following docstring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#&#39; @importFrom dplyr filter
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you can just use &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt; like normal in your code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#&#39; @importFrom dplyr filter               #This is where you add the @importFrom
use_filter &amp;lt;- function(df, cutoff=0.5) {

  filter(df, value &amp;lt; cutoff)

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-import-when-you-need-a-lot-of-functions-from-a-package&#34;&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;@import&lt;/code&gt;: When you need a lot of functions from a package&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you had a lot of functions from one package, such as &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt;, that you want to use? Do you need to add an &lt;code&gt;@importFrom&lt;/code&gt; for each of these functions? Nope. You can just use one &lt;code&gt;@import&lt;/code&gt; field for the whole package:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#` @import shiny
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then code like usual:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#` @import shiny            # This is where you add the @import
shinyUI &amp;lt;- function() {
    selectInput(&amp;quot;&amp;quot;)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;importing-multiple-packages-just-don-t-do-it-updated&#34;&gt;Importing multiple packages: just don&amp;rsquo;t do it (UPDATED).&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a note to not import multiple packages using &lt;code&gt;@import&lt;/code&gt;. As Hadley Wickham has noted, you have no control over the development of the packages you import. Just because there are no function collisions right now between the packages doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that one of the developers may add a function down the line that might collide. So, if you need to use multiple packages, &lt;code&gt;@import&lt;/code&gt; one package and use &lt;code&gt;@importsFrom&lt;/code&gt; or namespaces to refer to functions in the other packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exported-versus-internal-functions&#34;&gt;Exported versus Internal functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember I mentioned ‘@export’ above? Specifying in a docstring for your function &lt;em&gt;exports&lt;/em&gt; it. Specifying it means that ‘devtools::document()’ will add an &lt;code&gt;Export&lt;/code&gt; directive for the function in the NAMESPACE file. That means you can access it using ‘::’. Going back to our &lt;code&gt;use_filter&lt;/code&gt; example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#&#39; @export                              #This is where you add the @export
#&#39; @importFrom dplyr filter
use_filter &amp;lt;- function(df, cutoff=0.5) {

  filter(df, value &amp;lt; cutoff)

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our package name is &lt;code&gt;mypackage&lt;/code&gt;, then this function will be accessible if we use &lt;code&gt;library(mypackage)&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;mypackage::use_filter()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this important? You may write some &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; functions that are useful in your package, but they aren’t necessarily ones you want your users to use in their daily use. &lt;code&gt;@export&lt;/code&gt; allows you to control which functions you make publicly accessible in your package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, try typing &lt;code&gt;dplyr::&lt;/code&gt; in RStudio and hit the tab key. You’ll see the usual &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; verbs pop up. But these are only the exported functions. Now try &lt;code&gt;dplyr:::&lt;/code&gt; and hit the tab key. You’ll see a list of functions that pop up that’s much longer - these are all the functions, including the internal functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if there’s a cool bit of internal code you want to use in a package, you can use ‘:::’ to specify it. Just be aware that oftentimes, internal functions may change a lot as code gets refactored, so code that utilizes them may be refactored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remember-to-run-devtools-document&#34;&gt;Remember to run &lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve written code and want to test it in your package, remember to run &lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt; before you reinstall your package for testing. Otherwise, the &lt;code&gt;NAMESPACE&lt;/code&gt; file won&amp;rsquo;t be modified, and your code won&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also modify your Project Options for your package and check the &lt;strong&gt;Tools &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Project Options &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Build Tools &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Generate Documentation with Roxygen&lt;/strong&gt; box. Next to it, there is also a &lt;code&gt;Configure&lt;/code&gt; button that lets you select the option to run &lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt; whenever you build a package for testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;go-forth-and-package&#34;&gt;Go forth and Package!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/imports-workflow.png&#34; alt=&#34;Using a function from another package&#34; width = 500&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;usethis::use_package()&lt;/code&gt; to add packages to your &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file (while in the console) after you&amp;rsquo;ve created your package skeleton using &lt;code&gt;use_package()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use namespaces (such as &lt;code&gt;mypackage::usefilter()&lt;/code&gt;) to refer to external functions where possible to avoid collisions in function names when you are writing code.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;@imports&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;@importsFrom&lt;/code&gt; judiciously in your &lt;code&gt;roxygen&lt;/code&gt; documentation for a function if you need to use many extenral package functions within a function.  Use only 1 &lt;code&gt;@import&lt;/code&gt; statement in a function, use namespaces/&lt;code&gt;@importsFrom&lt;/code&gt; for the other packages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expose functions you want to be made public using &lt;code&gt;@export&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;roxygen&lt;/code&gt; documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember to run &lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt; in the console after you modify/add these fields to the roxygen documentation when you build for testing, or set it up in &lt;strong&gt;Tools &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Project Options&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this helps you to understand exactly the relationships between all of the components that are responsible for accessing namespaces in your package. I was confused about this for years, so writing this has helped me understand these relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading&#34;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to know how R searches for a function across its environments and why namespaces are a good thing, this is an excellent writeup: &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.obeautifulcode.com/R/How-R-Searches-And-Finds-Stuff/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://blog.obeautifulcode.com/R/How-R-Searches-And-Finds-Stuff/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More about the &lt;code&gt;usethis&lt;/code&gt; workflow: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hvitfeldt.me/blog/usethis-workflow-for-package-development/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.hvitfeldt.me/blog/usethis-workflow-for-package-development/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More about the &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file: &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/description.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/description.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More about namespaces: &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/namespace.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/namespace.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More about roxygen: &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/man.html#roxygen-comments&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/man.html#roxygen-comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An alternative workflow to modify the &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; file: You can use &lt;code&gt;attachment::att_to_description()&lt;/code&gt; to scan code and add packages to the file after coding (thanks,  Sébastien!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Hao Ye, Sébastien Rochette, Michael Chirico, Tim Hesterberg, and Hadley Wickham for their comments and questions. I&amp;rsquo;ve incorporated your suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;note&#34;&gt;Note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want this to be clear and correct. Please &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:laderast@ohsu.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; if there are any mistakes I&amp;rsquo;ve made.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Scavenger Hunt: NHANES</title>
      <link>/teaching/data_nhanes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/data_nhanes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rstudio Conf 2019: Education and Organizations</title>
      <link>/2019/01/24/rstudio-conf-2019-education-and-organizations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/24/rstudio-conf-2019-education-and-organizations/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Well, RStudio Conf 2019 has come and gone. I attended the main conference, starting with the poster session on wednesday and stayed through the tidyverse developer day on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say that the conference was inspiring was an understatement. So many talented people working on such interesting and inspiring packages! It made me excited again about doing data science and teaching data science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is going to highlight the interesting talks about education and organizational management at the conference. There were lots of thought provoking talks and great resources about education. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/RStudioConf2019Slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a link to the other resources, posters, and talks&lt;/a&gt; (thanks, Karl Broman!). There are a lot of new neat whiz bang features in RStudio, which I won&amp;rsquo;t cover, but are covered very well by others at Karl&amp;rsquo;s link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: I&amp;rsquo;m adding links to the videos as subheadings that you can click on. I won&amp;rsquo;t embed these directly because there is often related material with the video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;available-teaching-resources&#34;&gt;Available Teaching Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was much sharing of educational resources. I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carl-howe-s-talk-the-next-million-r-users-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-the-next-million-r-users&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/the-next-million-r-users&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Carl Howe&amp;rsquo;s Talk: The Next Million R Users&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mel-gregory-rstudio-for-education-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-rstudio-cloud-for-education&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/rstudio-cloud-for-education&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mel Gregory: RStudio for Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Howe (Director of Education for RStudio) presented a number of resources that RStudio is providing for educational purposes. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/learning-r-survey/blob/master/slides/Next-Million-R-Users.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Their goal is to train the next million R users&lt;/a&gt;. Here are some of the RStudio based educational resources that might be useful for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RStudio Cloud is now available free for people who teach courses&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/pricing/academic-pricing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;who can send them a course syllabus to gain access&lt;/a&gt;. RStudio Cloud includes resources to make coursework publically or privately available, allows instructors to install default packages, and gives students an immediate way to start playing with R/RStudio. We are definitely going to use this in teaching our &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/AnalyticsCourse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BMI &lt;sup&gt;569&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;669&lt;/sub&gt; Data Analytics&lt;/a&gt; course. Mel Gregory&amp;rsquo;s talk was about the nuts and bolts of using RStudio Cloud in a classroom situation. Highly recommended to get familiar with the basics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel also has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://datasciencebox.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data Science In a Box&lt;/a&gt; course available that can be forked and used by anyone. There is a great discussion of how to use the course and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://datasciencebox.org/hello/tech-stack/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tech stack (RStudio Cloud, GitHub, and Slack)&lt;/a&gt; needed to make the course runnable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also a number of LearnR Tutorials built into RStudio Cloud called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio-education/primers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RStudio Primers&lt;/a&gt; that cover a lot of basic RStudio operations for the self-directed learners.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jessica Minnier and I &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/equal_viz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;presented at the poster session&lt;/a&gt; about our LearnR tutorials, &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/laderast/DSIExplore&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DSIExplore&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/laderast/dataLiteracyTutorial&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dataLiteracyTutorial&lt;/a&gt; and our &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/burro&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;burro&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package, which lets &lt;a href=&#34;http://tladeras.shinyapps.io/nhanes_explore&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;users explore a new dataset with a simplified Shiny App&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s even a function that lets you build a shiny app from a dataset that you can publish to a Shiny server such as &lt;code&gt;shinyapps.io&lt;/code&gt; or RStudio Connect for sharing and having a &lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/burro/articles/data_scavenger_hunt.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;data scavenger hunt&lt;/a&gt; together. Or as Angela Bassa calls it, an EDA Party. Whoo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;irene-stevens-talk-teaching-data-science-with-puzzles-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-teaching-data-science-with-puzzles&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/teaching-data-science-with-puzzles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Irene Stevens&amp;rsquo; Talk: Teaching Data Science With Puzzles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really loved Irene Stevens&amp;rsquo; talk about &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/isteves/teaching-data-science-with-puzzles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Teaching Data Science Using Puzzles&lt;/a&gt;. Irene and Jenny Bryan put together a simple project-based framework that lets students download simple data wrangling puzzles per week, lets them submit their answer to an answer server and get feedback, and when they solve it, it creates a minimal reproducible example (reprex) to share with their puzzle community. Very Slick!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kelly-bodwin-introductory-statistics-with-r-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-introductory-statistics-with-r-easing-the-transition-to-software-for-beginner-students&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/introductory-statistics-with-r-easing-the-transition-to-software-for-beginner-students&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kelly Bodwin: Introductory Statistics with R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelly Bodwin gave a presentation of how she used Shiny apps as an intermediate step as part of an approach to &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.calpoly.edu/~kbodwin/RStudio_2019.html#1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;teaching introductory statistics&lt;/a&gt;. Kelly is of the opinion that coding is good even for non majors, and her Shiny apps provide an intermediate step between a more click-based app and coding, asking the students to input their variables, their hypothesis, and highlights the output that results. I really liked this approach. I also really loved this slide:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019-rstudioconf/downloads_folder.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diversity-and-inclusiveness-make-for-better-data-science&#34;&gt;Diversity and Inclusiveness Make for Better Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;jesse-mostipak-r4ds-online-learning-community-improvements-to-self-taught-data-science-the-critical-need-for-diversity-equity-and-inclusion-in-data-science-education-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-r4ds-online-learning-community-improvements-to-self-taught-data-science-amp-the-critical-need-for-diversity-equity-and-inclusion-in-data-science-education&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/r4ds-online-learning-community-improvements-to-self-taught-data-science-amp-the-critical-need-for-diversity-equity-and-inclusion-in-data-science-education&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jesse Mostipak: R4DS online learning community: Improvements to self-taught data science &amp;amp; the critical need for diversity, equity, and inclusion in data science education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed Jesse Mostipak&amp;rsquo;s talk about her data science journey starting the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rfordatasci.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R For Data Science (R4DS)&lt;/a&gt; learning community. She especially emphasized that data science was her path out of lower incomes and that she thought it needs to be more accessible to all. She talked about the barriers to going from &amp;ldquo;Using your computer for Netflix&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Using your computer for data science&amp;rdquo; as real, and what she learned as a community manager for the R4DS learning community. Finally, she ended with a call for data scientists to share their mistakes, in order to model that making mistakes is ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;caitlin-hudon-learning-from-eight-years-of-data-science-mistakes-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-learning-from-eight-years-of-data-science-mistakes&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/learning-from-eight-years-of-data-science-mistakes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Caitlin Hudon: Learning from Eight Years of Data Science Mistakes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of mistakes, Caitlin Hudon gave a talk called &amp;ldquo;Learning from Eight Years of Data Science Mistakes&amp;rdquo;, which was really helpful. One of her messages was that &amp;ldquo;Mistakes count as experience&amp;rdquo;, and learning from past mistakes is extremely helpful for the whole team. However, it must be safe for team members to share their mistakes, and so creating the right culture of respect and teaching is important. This includes documentation, and including pseudocode next to the actual code to talk non-data scientists through is important. Likewise, making sure that you are solving the correct business problem requires communication. I really liked her discussion of the Rhetorical Triangle as a way to frame communications: Speaker, Audience, and Context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tracy-teal-teaching-r-using-inclusive-pedagogy-practices-and-lessons-learned-from-over-700-carpentries-workshops-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-teaching-r-using-inclusive-pedagogy-practices-and-lessons-learned-from-over-700-carpentries-workshops&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/teaching-r-using-inclusive-pedagogy-practices-and-lessons-learned-from-over-700-carpentries-workshops&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tracy Teal: Teaching R using inclusive pedagogy: Practices and lessons learned from over 700 Carpentries workshops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracy Teal from Data Carpentries also talked about their efforts to &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1yZTOcm0hO3sq8nz24luNoxL2Tk4IWfwoeYSXa09-zB8/edit#slide=id.g4d9835a148_0_218&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Teaching R using inclusive pedagogy&lt;/a&gt;, including fostering a growth mindset. &lt;a href=&#34;https://carpentries.github.io/instructor-training/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Their instructor training&lt;/a&gt; is a wonderful 2-day crash course in teaching, and I&amp;rsquo;m going to propose that it be offered to our graduate students to prep them for teaching. (Full disclosure: I&amp;rsquo;ve contributed to these course materials.) I also appreciated how candid she was about how much further they need to go to increase the diversity of participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diversity and Inclusiveness was also a theme of Angela Bassa&amp;rsquo;s talk about &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/angelabassa/rstudioconf-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Team Data Science&lt;/a&gt;. She pointed out that data science teams need to be diverse to serve audiences who are highly diverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-teaching-resources-for-community-college-instructors&#34;&gt;Making Teaching Resources for Community College Instructors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mary-rudis-catching-the-r-wave-how-r-and-rstudio-are-revolutionizing-statistics-education-in-community-colleges-and-beyond-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-catching-the-r-wave-how-r-and-rstudio-are-revolutionizing-statistics-education-in-community-colleges-and-beyond&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/catching-the-r-wave-how-r-and-rstudio-are-revolutionizing-statistics-education-in-community-colleges-and-beyond&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mary Rudis: Catching the R wave: How R and RStudio are revolutionizing statistics education in community colleges (and beyond)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A really interesting talk for me was Mary Rudis&amp;rsquo; talk about her work &lt;a href=&#34;https://mrshrbrmstr.github.io/RStudioConf2019/pres/Marys_slides-rev/assets/player/KeynoteDHTMLPlayer.html#0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;teaching data science at the community college level&lt;/a&gt;. As head of the math department at Penn State Harrisburg, Mary has done a lot of work developing the first data science certification at the community college level. There are a lot more people attending community college than 4 year colleges, and we need to make paths to data science accessible for these students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot more work needs to be done to make data science accessible at this level. Mary has pointed out a number of efforts that need help, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://statprep.org/the-statprep-team/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;StatPREP&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://amatyc.site-ym.com/page/AMATYCAffiliateOrg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;American Mathematical Association of Two Year Colleges&lt;/a&gt;. She also ended with a call for Shiny Developers to help Community College instructors develop tools they can use to teach data science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;organizational-considerations-in-data-science&#34;&gt;Organizational Considerations in Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joe-cheng-shiny-in-production-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-shiny-in-production-principles-practices-and-tools-joe-cheng&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/shiny-in-production-principles-practices-and-tools-joe-cheng&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Joe Cheng: Shiny in Production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tonya-filz-the-resilient-r-champion-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-the-resilient-r-champion&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/the-resilient-r-champion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tonya Filz: The Resilient R Champion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizational considerations were also a really interesting part of RStudio Conf for me. Joe Cheng&amp;rsquo;s keynote on &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/jcheng5/shiny-in-production&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shiny in Production&lt;/a&gt; spent some time talking about overcoming resistance to Shiny in your organization, including talking with Data Engineers and IT Security. His point was that oftentimes, resistance comes from the feelings of territorialism and how to overcome them. Tonya Filz also gave a talk about being a Resilient R Champion at your organization, stressing these issues and giving us case studies/examples to show leaders at your organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hilary-parker-cultivating-creativity-in-data-work-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-cultivating-creativity-in-data-work&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/cultivating-creativity-in-data-work&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hilary Parker: Cultivating creativity in Data work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hilary Parker&amp;rsquo;s talk about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/hilaryparker/rstudioconf2019l&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Creativity and Data Science in the Organization&lt;/a&gt;, about applying system design principles to data science. Rather than thinking of ourselves as having a traditional role at the end of the analysis, Hilary suggested that we partipate in all parts of the process, including data collection. Her group suggested a change in an app, which resulted in a brand new data stream for them to analyse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;angela-bassa-data-science-as-a-team-sport-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-data-science-as-a-team-sport&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/data-science-as-a-team-sport&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Angela Bassa: Data science as a team sport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angela Bassa&amp;rsquo;s Talk about &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/angelabassa/rstudioconf-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Team Data Science&lt;/a&gt; talked about the organizational aspects of making a data team, including specializing roles, making sure that knowledge and expertise was distributed, and managing burnout by making sure that no one team member is overloaded. She stressed resilience within a team by making sure that people are taking care of themselves, having redundancy in the team. Process is also important, by making sure data is well documented, by allotting time. She also stressed the importance of young and new data scientists to the team, because they aren&amp;rsquo;t biased with previous knowledge. I also thought she had excellent arguments about the cost of &lt;em&gt;not expanding&lt;/em&gt; your data team - potential users who would be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;encouraging-a-growth-mindset&#34;&gt;Encouraging a Growth Mindset&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;panel-growth-change-of-careers-organizations-and-responsibility-in-data-science-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-4pm-panel-day-2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/4pm-panel-day-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Panel: Growth &amp;amp; change of careers, organizations and responsibility in data science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the final panel discussion, which was about encouraging a Growth Mindset for Data Scientists in their careers. Karthik Ram, Tracy Teal, Angela Bassa, and Hilary Parker all fielded questions about growing as a data scientist. One of my favorite remarks was from Tracy Teal, who mused about the possibility of a Leadership Carpentry, teaching potential leaders essential skills such as mentoring, faciliation skills, and valuing team contributions. Angela Bassa also had a great quote that &amp;ldquo;leadership is programming people&amp;rdquo;. She also pointed out that the role of Data Scientists is to &amp;ldquo;Question Dogma&amp;rdquo; and pointed out the importance of saying &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;david-robinson-the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-public-work-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-public-work&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-public-work&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Robinson: The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Public Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019-rstudioconf/public_work.png&#34; alt=&#34;Making your work public&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth mindset was also a theme of Dave Robinson&amp;rsquo;s Keynote, which was about making your &lt;a href=&#34;https://bit.ly/drob-rstudio-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;data science work public at a number of levels&lt;/a&gt;. He outlined a number of different types of public contributions, such as short form (tweets, discussions about data), long form (blogs), code contributions, and even writing a book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;direct-explicit-instruction-in-education&#34;&gt;Direct Explicit Instruction in Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;felienne-hermans-explicit-direct-instruction-in-education-https-resources-rstudio-com-rstudio-conf-2019-opening-keynote-day2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2019/opening-keynote-day2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Felienne Hermans: Explicit Direct Instruction in Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Felienne Hermans gave a wonderful keynote about teaching computer programming. I won&amp;rsquo;t crib her story, because her telling it was a delightful journey and I encourage you to watch it for yourself at the link above. Part of her point was that programming pedagogy is dominated by the &amp;ldquo;tyranny of fun&amp;rdquo;, rather than focusing on teaching fundamentals. One of the problems with programming education is that we haven&amp;rsquo;t defined what these fundamentals are, compared to the pedagogy of reading, which talks about teaching with fundamentals such as phonics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expect students to explore things without teaching them enough, and that actually hurts their progress. Instead, we should also be teaching fundamentals, such as code reading out loud and rote memorization of programming patterns. By utilizing these fundamentals, she has found improved learning outcomes. As she says, motivation comes from seeing progress, not necessarily from exploration alone. Her results on using direct instruction have showed improved outcomes in terms of motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that this talk really opened my eyes to the blind spots we have in programming education. Looking forward to incorporating these ideas in my coursework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-many-people-to-teach-so-many-ways-to-teach&#34;&gt;So Many People to Teach, So Many Ways to Teach!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s my summary about the education and organizational talks/posters at RStudio Conf. Hopefully it gives you an idea of what resources, opportunities, and pedagogy is out there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow Dashboard Demo</title>
      <link>/project/sample_flow_dashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sample_flow_dashboard/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NHANES explorer</title>
      <link>/project/nhanes_explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/nhanes_explorer/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reframing Impostor Syndrome as the Road to Mastery</title>
      <link>/2018/12/13/reframing-impostor-syndrome-as-being-on-the-road-to-mastery/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/13/reframing-impostor-syndrome-as-being-on-the-road-to-mastery/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;At some point in your life in Data Science, you will probably struggle with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apa.org/gradpsych/2013/11/fraud.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt;. We all do - in fact, even though I have used R and have done bioinformatics and data science for more than 15 years, I still struggle with this feeling. As a beginner, the mountain you must climb to master skills in data science seems like a long and impossible one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caitlin Hudon, in her post about &lt;a href=&#34;https://caitlinhudon.com/2018/01/19/imposter-syndrome-in-data-science/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dealing with impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt; has this to say about countering impostor syndrome:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way that I’ve dealt with imposter syndrome is this: I’ve accepted that I will never be able to learn everything there is to know in data science — I will never know every algorithm, every technology, every cool package, or even every language — and that’s okay. The great thing about being in such a diverse field is that nobody will know all of these things (and that’s okay too!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to try and reframe the feelings of impostor syndrome into something more positive. I think having self-compassion about the difficulties of the learning process can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Leonard&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/81940.Mastery&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mastery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a short book that I think can help provide the antidote to these feelings of fraud and inadequacy. I feel that beginners and learners would feel much better if their instructors would own up to their own personal shortcomings as learners. That is, instead of trying to project the image of the all knowledgable guru, instructors should show themselves as humble, lifelong learners as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/81940.Mastery&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mastery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Leonard talks about our unrealistic expectations and how these expectations can get in the way of actually learning and mastering a craft. We are conditioned by ads, movies, and social media that mastering a craft is a never ending set of ever rising climaxes (cue the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SPFCHuEegsk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;training montage&lt;/a&gt;), that we can make continuous and steady progress by working hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastering a craft takes practice, and lots of it. We must learn to be contented to practice when we are on a plateau and are not making visible progress. As Leonard notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Path to Mastery is practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leonard outlines 5 principles that can sustain us in our road to mastery and away from impostor syndrome: &lt;strong&gt;Instruction&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Practice&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Surrender&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Intentionality&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;The Edge&lt;/strong&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to map common feelings of impostor syndrome and show how these principles can counteract these feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instruction&lt;/strong&gt;. Leonard emphasizes the importance in finding good instructors and good mentorship that will help us to grow. Finding good instructors can actually be difficult and finding someone who remembers what it was like to be learning something is important. Avoid those instructors who say things like &amp;ldquo;it should now be obvious&amp;rdquo; or are disparaging when you don&amp;rsquo;t understand something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He or she is not necessarily the one that gives the most polished lectures, but rather the &lt;em&gt;one who has discovered how to involve each student actively&lt;/em&gt; in the process of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you can do today&lt;/em&gt;: look at twitter and other forums for your community of learners and support those who give good instruction. Realize that not all teachers are good teachers; leave them and seek better ones if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practice&lt;/strong&gt;. Practice for practices&amp;rsquo; sake. Deliberate practice where you slowly build up your understanding and perceptions is important to your growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where in our upbringing, our schooling, our career are we taught to value, to enjoy, even to love the plateau, the long stretch of diligent effort with no seeming progress?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you can do today&lt;/em&gt;: Join communities of practice such as Tidy Tuesday and share your learning with others. Tidy Tuesday is extremely friendly and encouraging for beginners. Learn together and grow together. These are safe communities to share knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intentionality&lt;/strong&gt;. This goes hand in hand with practice. Deliberate practice requires visualizing your process and guiding yourself gently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intentionality fuels the master&amp;rsquo;s journey. Every master is a master of vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you can do today&lt;/em&gt;: find small exercises and projects that help you reinforce what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far. Find people&amp;rsquo;s code and vignettes and modify them until you understand what they&amp;rsquo;ve done and how they structured their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surrender&lt;/strong&gt;. At some point, you will have to give up your own social position as an expert to grow as a learner. When this happens, you must be willing to risk that standing to progress further. Leonard talks about a karate master learning aikido who was not willing to start from scratch, which impeded his learning. For many of us academics, being willing to abandon the comfort of what we have learned is especially difficult. We feel like we are risking our own social standing and reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the master, surrender means there are no experts. There are only Learners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you can do today&lt;/em&gt;: be humble when faced with new concepts (for many impostor syndrome sufferers this is not the hard part). Recognize when you need to grow and when you have to leave old concepts behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Edge&lt;/strong&gt;. This is where things are undefined and scary. Still, part of the journey to mastery is a willingness to push your thoughts to beyond the horizon of what you thought was possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trick here is not only to test the edges of the envelope, but also to walk the fine line between endless, goalless practice and those alluring roles that appear along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you can do today&lt;/em&gt;: Identify some goals that are just beyond your current skillset and be willing to push your learning to that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leonard maintains that true mastery is not due to innate talent. True mastery is due to tenacity and perserverance in the face of difficult learning. In fact, he suggests that learning things too easily means that you might lack perserverance when the going gets rough and your progress slows. He maintains that someone who perseveres will &amp;ldquo;have learned whatever [they] are practicing to the marrow of [their] bones.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;encouraging-mastery-as-a-community&#34;&gt;Encouraging Mastery as a Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Caitlin&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://caitlinhudon.com/2018/01/19/imposter-syndrome-in-data-science/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;prescriptions for community wide suggestions for reducing impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt; are wonderful. Especially the advice to &amp;ldquo;Get comfortable with I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;. Normalizing &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo; within a community is incredibly important to making a psychologically safe learning environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encourage learners, I think that creating a community of practice and helpfulness is vitally important to give new learners the support they need. When communities take responsibility for the learning of their members, something magic happens. Learning no longer feels lonely and there is no shame when you don&amp;rsquo;t immediately grasp a concept. Patience becomes the norm and people become more confident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, this is the true value of schools and universities. To get the most out of online learning, you need to participate within a community that encourages you to learn further. Be on the pathway to mastery by participate within learning communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading&#34;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastery: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/81940.Mastery&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/81940.Mastery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things we learned teaching clinical data wrangling</title>
      <link>/2018/10/15/clinical-data-wrangling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/15/clinical-data-wrangling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, we just finished our &lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/clinical_data_wrangling/&#34;&gt;clinical data wrangling workshop&lt;/a&gt;. This was a 12 hour workshop (spread over 4 days) where students got to work with a real research dataset (the &lt;a href=&#34;http://sleepdata.org&#34;&gt;Sleep Heart Health Study&lt;/a&gt; data). This is a workshop that we developed as part of an National Library of Medicine T15 training supplement in Data Science. The following is a short report describing the workshop and its outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;intended-audience&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intended Audience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We designed the workshop for our incoming informatics students (both clinical and biological majors) in order to introduce them to the difficulties of working with clinical data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;learning-objectives&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were our learning objectives for the workshop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the biology of sleep and sleep apnea and how the biology informs the covariates measured in the Sleep Heart Health Study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand why clinical data is useful and also why it’s difficult to work with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn Exploratory Data Analysis techniques and use them to inform model building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to assess logistic regression models using simple diagnostics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-dataset&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Dataset&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sleepdata.org/datasets/shhs&#34;&gt;Sleep Heart Health Study&lt;/a&gt; dataset from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sleepdata.org&#34;&gt;National Sleep Research Resource&lt;/a&gt;. This is a dataset of approximately 5800 patients that have over 3000 covariates. We limited our students to a smaller number of covariates (17), including our outcome of interest, cardiovascular disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;workshop-format&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop Format&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We designed the workshop to be a mix of didactic lectures and active learning exercises. Where possible, we had students work in groups to answer questions about the data. These activities included a data scavenger hunt using our EDA exploration app, and a logistic modeling exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;day-1-outline&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Day 1 Outline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction, logistics, and groups assigned (30 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biology of Sleep and Cardiovascular Disease (40 minutes, format: in-person lecture)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break Time (15 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Value of Clinical Data (15 minutes, in-person lecture)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clinical Data Quality (40 minutes, in-person lecture)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lunch (90 minutes, with optional R setup session)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploring the SHHS Dataset (60 minutes, format: Data Scavenger Hunt w/ Shiny App, each team gets a task and has to show the class how to find the information)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applying the Clinical Wrangling Process: Diabetes (45 minutes, format: in-person lecture)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistic Regression Model Basics (60 minutes, format: walkthrough of R Notebook)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;day-2&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Day 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question/Answer session about Logistic Regression and Modeling (50 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assignment about &lt;code&gt;race&lt;/code&gt; variable (assigned to groups, take-home assignment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;day-3&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Day 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discussion about &lt;code&gt;race&lt;/code&gt; as a covariate, sharing of findings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview of hypertension and how it relates to cardiovascular disease and sleep apnea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Template/R Notebook given for final presentation in groups (in-class lab time, template is structured as a series of decisions.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;day-4&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Day 4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group presentations about covariate decisions and resulting model (1 hour, present final version of R notebook). At each decision stage, teams must decide on whether or not to include covariates or not given what they have found from exploring the data and justify their decision using EDA visualizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, we believe the workshop went well, as it encouraged discussion about data and its appropriateness among the students. Students were engaged overall and asked lots of questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final reports for each group were generated from a R Notebook. All three groups showed a thoughtful narrative and justification for each of the covariates included in the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive visualization removes barriers to understanding issues in data&lt;/strong&gt;. Ted developed a Shiny App that allowed the students to visually browse and understand the data. Along with the EDA scavenger hunt (see below), this served as a good introduction for students to get their feet wet with the SHHS dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our diverse backgrounds helped make the workshop accessible.&lt;/strong&gt; Nicole Weiskopf has a background in data quality of clinical data, Eilis Boudreau does sleep study work, and I’m a bit of a mongrel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Securing the cooperation of the data holders made the workshop possible&lt;/strong&gt;. The dataset comes from the National Sleep Study Resource. Eilis knows Susan Redline, who heads that group and pitched the idea (over two sessions) to her group. Susan’s group was very enthusiastic and helpful, especially in helping the students get their data use agreements in so they could access the dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group work is learning work&lt;/strong&gt;. We assigned each student to a group, and gave each group questions to answer and teach the class about the dataset. By pointing them to specific aspects of the data, we opened the door to discussion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDA scavenger hunt&lt;/strong&gt;. We had the students learn data exploration by giving them a scavenger hunt to look at the relationship between variables. Each group was then required to talk about their findings and which visualization helped them discover that relationship. For example, there is a relationship between age and race in our dataset; the “Other” category of race has a lower median age than the other two categories, “White” and “Black”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Didactic Teaching is also important&lt;/strong&gt;. Nicole and Eilis covered both the biology of sleep apnea and the difficulty of understanding the implications of clinical data. Without this background, students would not be able to make informed decisions about their final model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guide the Students, but don’t force discussion&lt;/strong&gt;. This was important. We think the students need to connect the dots to really understand the issues. The final product (a logistic regression model predicting cardiovascular disease with an R Notebook) had steps and choices. But the choices for each group of students was different.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Code of conduct is necessary and important&lt;/strong&gt;. We are big believers in psychological safety. If people don’t feel safe in the classroom environment (and let’s face it, grad school classrooms rarely are), they will be less likely to learn and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data restrictions made deploying difficult&lt;/strong&gt;. The activity materials were deployed as an RStudio project. However, we couldn’t share the data within a GitHub repo. As OHSU’s approved vendor is Box, we setup a box folder containing the material to be shared with students.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were grateful for the incoming informatics students’ enthusiasm and patience as we got this workshop going. Also thanks to the NLM T15 Supplement in Data Science, without which we would not have gotten the opportunity to conceptualize, put together, and deliver this workshop. Thanks again to Susan Redline and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://sleepdata.org&#34;&gt;National Sleep Research Resource&lt;/a&gt; group, especially Dan Mobley who helped us with the last-minute data use agreements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to Workshop: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/clinical_data_wrangling&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/laderast/clinical_data_wrangling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Interactive Visualization</title>
      <link>/project/introduction_to_interactive_vis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/introduction_to_interactive_vis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shiny and Tidyeval Part 1</title>
      <link>/2018/08/07/shiny-and-tidyeval/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/08/07/shiny-and-tidyeval/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: sometimes I write these posts to teach myself a better way to do things in R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been avoiding &lt;code&gt;tidyeval&lt;/code&gt; somewhat, because I seem to have a bit of a learning block about it. I’m going to try to write some posts that help me understand what’s going on with Tidy Evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;using-sym-in-a-shiny-app&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;sym()&lt;/code&gt; in a Shiny App&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One fairly simple Shiny Application might be selecting a column of the dataset and then doing something with it, such as using it in a &lt;code&gt;select()&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt; statement. Say we had a simple app to produce histograms, and we wanted to change the column that is being displayed on the histogram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this app out by running the following command. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/laderast/a5205554324306e642b2df9f80ed6409&#34;&gt;code is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;runGist(&amp;quot;https://gist.github.com/laderast/a5205554324306e642b2df9f80ed6409&amp;quot;, display.mode=&amp;quot;showcase&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our input is a select input called &lt;code&gt;numeric_var&lt;/code&gt;, which returns a single column name as a &lt;code&gt;character&lt;/code&gt; In our server logic, we’ve built a reactive called &lt;code&gt;selected_data&lt;/code&gt;, which returns the selected column as a vector using &lt;code&gt;pull()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  selected_data &amp;lt;- reactive({
    ## input$numeric_var is a character, so we cast it to symbol
    var_name &amp;lt;- sym(input$numeric_var)

    ## Now we evaluate it with !!
    out_col &amp;lt;- iris %&amp;gt;% pull(!!var_name)
  })&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is: how do we pass the input value into &lt;code&gt;pull()&lt;/code&gt;? We first have to use &lt;code&gt;rlang::sym()&lt;/code&gt; to pass our character in as a &lt;code&gt;symbol&lt;/code&gt; that we’re calling &lt;code&gt;var_name&lt;/code&gt;. But the issue is that our reactive doesn’t know which environment to look in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want our reactive to look for the column name within the environment of the &lt;code&gt;iris&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;tibble&lt;/code&gt;. This is where the &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt; (bang-bang) comes in. It says, ‘look for the value’ within the &lt;code&gt;tibble&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;using-syms-in-a-shiny-app&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;syms()&lt;/code&gt; in a Shiny App&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if wanted to pass in &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; variables from a select box? We’ll need to wrap our input with &lt;code&gt;syms()&lt;/code&gt;, which takes a list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s do a slightly different version where we’re visualizing a box plot and we want to select multiple columns to display in our dataset from a &lt;code&gt;selectInput&lt;/code&gt; where we’ve specified the &lt;code&gt;multiple=TRUE&lt;/code&gt; argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our setup is similar, but different. Because we have multiple values, we have to use &lt;code&gt;syms()&lt;/code&gt; to wrap the input from &lt;code&gt;input$numeric_vars&lt;/code&gt;. Then we can evaluate it with &lt;code&gt;!!!&lt;/code&gt; (the triple bang).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  selected_data &amp;lt;- reactive({
    ## input$numeric_var is a character vector, so we cast it to symbol
    var_list &amp;lt;- syms(input$numeric_vars)

    ## Now we evaluate it with !!!
    out_col &amp;lt;- iris %&amp;gt;% select(!!!var_list)
  })&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this app out. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/laderast/952120ac46d1f27c2d2dba5bd1ab5d10&#34;&gt;Code is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;runGist(&amp;quot;https://gist.github.com/laderast/952120ac46d1f27c2d2dba5bd1ab5d10&amp;quot;, display.mode=&amp;quot;showcase&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
