<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ted Laderas, PhD on Ted Laderas, PhD</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ted Laderas, PhD on Ted Laderas, PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachings</title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improvisation and Collaboration</title>
      <link>/improvisation-and-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/improvisation-and-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Way back in high school and college, I used to be a fairly avid jazz musician. I always loved the group aspect of Jazz - in a good group, there is this sense of support for each other&amp;rsquo;s creativity where everyone is backing each other up and giving each other musical space to express themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My background in improvisation has served me well, in that it has enabled a lot of my musical collaborations. My music is different in that I play improvisational cello, though on a very slow scale. But you can drop me into a lot of situations and I can come up with something that will work with someone else&amp;rsquo;s musical style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now realize that I use a lot of the rules of improvisation when I collaborate with others in Open Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being respectful and listening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes, and&amp;rdquo;. This is an old comedy improv rule. It means that you don&amp;rsquo;t shut other people&amp;rsquo;s performances down. You try to build on theirs and enhance it. I like to build on people&amp;rsquo;s ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being flexible. See previous two rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t hog the spotlight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most things are a process and rely on previous experience. No one became an expert improviser overnight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust the process when you can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python_resources</title>
      <link>/python_resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 13:55:55 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/python_resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A list of python resources at OHSU and beyond for the neuroscience students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-neuroscience&#34;&gt;In Neuroscience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;python-bootcamp-for-neuroscientists-neus640&#34;&gt;Python Bootcamp for Neuroscientists (NEUS640)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dasaderi/python_neurobootcamp&#34;&gt;Course Material&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is a gentle introduction to the Python
programming language using data types familiar to Neuroscience students, including behavioral, electrophysiology, and imaging data. Emphasis will be put on introducing students to concepts of visualization, data manipulation, and analysis using available Python packages (NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-medical-informatics-and-clinical-epidemiology-dmice&#34;&gt;In Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology (DMICE)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-to-programming-no-course-number&#34;&gt;Introduction to Programming (no course number)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructor: Lisa Karstens, Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 credits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohsu.edu/xd/education/schools/school-of-medicine/departments/clinical-departments/dmice/current-students/student-resources/upload/IntroductionToProgramming-Syllabus-WI18.pdf&#34;&gt;Course Syllabus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offered: Winter and Summer Quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This non-credit, online course will introduce the beginning programmer to programming structure and design, creating a solid foundation for all types of programming. The emphasis will be on procedural programming and control structures, although exercises will be in Python. The course fulfills the prerequisite for BMI 540 and BMI 565. Tuition fee is $500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students may register during the regular winter and summer term registration periods. Contact Diane Doctor for details at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:doctord@ohsu.edu&#34;&gt;doctord@ohsu.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bioinformatics-programming-and-scripting---bmi-565--656&#34;&gt;Bioinformatics Programming and Scripting - BMI 565 / 656&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructor: Michael Mooney, Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credits: 3.0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohsu.edu/xd/education/schools/school-of-medicine/departments/clinical-departments/dmice/current-students/student-resources/upload/BMI-565-Syllabus-FA17.pdf&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offered: Fall Quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this course is to equip research scientists with computational skills necessary to create and automate tools to analyze biological data.  The course is divided into four sub-topics: python programming, scripting in unix, biopython library, bioinformatics workflows.  Python will be used used to solve simple to sophisticated programming problems and to review general computational language paradigms such as problem abstraction, data types, file I/O, iteration, functions, and objects.  There will also be an emphasis on writing unix operating system shell scripts to automate repetitive tasks and connect disparate bioinformatics tools using files and pipes.  In addition, students will learn to access public repositories to perform basic bioinformatics tasks such as annotating gene products, sequence searching, and functional queries. This course is designed to be a first year requirement for students in the Bioinformatics and Computational Biology graduate program in Biomedical Informatics. Open to other students with consent of instructor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/strong&gt;: Background must include an introductory programming class including concepts such as variables, loops, I/O, methods, and algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;computer-science-and-electrical-engineering-csee-python-courses&#34;&gt;Computer Science and Electrical Engineering (CS/EE) Python Courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-science-programming---cs-527--627&#34;&gt;Data Science Programming - CS 527 / 627&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cslu.ohsu.edu/~kain/CS627/&#34;&gt;Course Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is designed to give you awareness and initial working knowledge of some of the most fundamental computational tools for performing a wide variety of academic research. As such, it will focus on providing breadth instead of depth, which means that for each concept we will talk about motivation, key concepts, and concrete usage scenarios, but without mathematical background or proofs, which can be acquired in more specialized classes. In this class we will: become familiar with the UNIX/LINUX environment, learn how to version control files with git, write programs inpython, perform numeric tasks using numpy and scipy, analyze data using pandas, apply machine learning algorithms using scikit-learn, visualize data using matplotlib and pyqtgraph, use QT/pyside to build graphical user interfaces, and finally we will address performance issues via compilation/profiling/parallelization tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-to-image-processing-ee-584--684&#34;&gt;Introduction to Image Processing EE 584 / 684&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course covers basic image processing principles and techniques with a brief introduction to machine vision. Specific topics include image transform methods, image filtering, image enhancement, image restoration, segmentation, image representation and feature extraction, image recognition and classification, and image compression. Application of these techniques is illustrated in numerous examples. Pre-requisite: probability and statistics or equivalent, calculus, linear algebra and proficiency in at least one high-level programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-visualization-cs-631&#34;&gt;Data Visualization CS 631&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course will give students a foundation in the principles of data visualization, particularly as applied to scientific and technical data, as well as provide students with hands-on experience using modern software tools for developing visualizations. Lecture topics will include an overview of visual perception, color theory and practice, different types of graphs and their purposes, visualizations for specialized forms of data including time-series and geospatial data sets, strategies for working with multidimensional data, etc. There will also be lecture content on ethical issues surrounding data visualization. Weekly lab sessions will introduce students to popular data visualization tools such as R&amp;rsquo;s ggplot and Shiny, Tableau, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;datacamp&#34;&gt;DataCamp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NEUS640 Students will have access to DataCamp for the next 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Objects: What are they for?</title>
      <link>/2017/05/29/objects-what-are-they-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/29/objects-what-are-they-for/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One area of programming that we do a really bad job teaching is Object-Oriented Programming (OOP). I was talking with one of my colleagues and he admitted that we don&amp;rsquo;t have enough time in our programming course (which is not CS) to show students what OOP is, much less what it&amp;rsquo;s for!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually find the examples that we teach in OOP to be rather useless to actually understanding what they&amp;rsquo;re for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about one reason to use Object Oriented Programming: to ensure data integrity in a Shiny App. Hopefully once you understand how I&amp;rsquo;ve applied the concepts here, you will start to think of other ways to apply them in your programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As most of you know, a Shiny App consists of two pieces: a User Interface piece, and a Server-side piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally understood why we encapsulate data in objects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>/talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cascadia-R Videos</title>
      <link>/cascadia-r-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/cascadia-r-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Keynote: Vinay Prasad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;125-140&#34;&gt;1:25-1:40&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meike Niederhausen  - Visualizing wearable activity tracker data and cardiometabolic risk factors with ggplot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mikhail Popov - Open knowledge in R with Wikimedia APIs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;140-155&#34;&gt;1:40-1:55&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Callahan - Best Practices for Error Handling and Logging&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myfanwy Hopkins - Building ensemble machine learning algorithms in R&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;155-210&#34;&gt;1:55-2:10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adler Nolis - Using R in consulting: how to get results while the clock is ticking&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oliver Keyes  - Playing with a Full Deque&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;210-225&#34;&gt;2:10-2:25&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hana Ševčíková - World Population Projections in R&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;225-240&#34;&gt;2:25-2:40&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Dane - Datasets that elucidate the role of the microenvironment in modulating cellular phenotypes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;240-255&#34;&gt;2:40-2:55&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dror Berel - Prototype meta-analysis demonstration for ImmuneSpaceR, using designated S4 objects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;255-310&#34;&gt;2:55-3:10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amelia Abreu - Improving the Developer Experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;310-325&#34;&gt;3:10-3:25&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn O&amp;rsquo;Neil - Teaching and Using R - A CS Perspective
Unavailable
John Smith - Uncovering the data science landscape in Portland&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;keynote-gabriela-de-quieroz&#34;&gt;Keynote: Gabriela de Quieroz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ted Laderas, PhD</title>
      <link>/cvitae/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/cvitae/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assistant Professor&lt;/em&gt;, 
Division of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology, 
Department of Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researcher&lt;/em&gt;, OHSU Knight Cancer Institute&lt;br&gt;
Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University&lt;br&gt;
3181 SW Sam Jackson Park Road CR145&lt;br&gt;
Portland, OR 97239&lt;br&gt;
(503) 481-8470&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:laderast@ohsu.edu&#34;&gt;laderast@ohsu.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B.A., Chemistry, Reed College, Portland, OR 1998.&lt;br&gt;
M.S. Biomedical Informatics, Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University, 2004.&lt;br&gt;
PhD, Biomedical Informatics, Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;teaching-statement&#34;&gt;Teaching Statement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective communication, hands-on learning, and mentoring are core to my
teaching philosophy. I am a strong believer in enabling students in
self-directed learning through hands-on workshops including both
practical skills in bioinformatics (software development, design, and
data analysis and visualization) and social skills essential to
collaboration (interpretation and communication). In terms of practical
skills, I have developed and contributed to a number of courses
(Analytics, RBootcamp, Network Analysis, and BD2K skills courses) and
workshops in a large variety of software development and communication
topics. These topics include software design, interactive visualization,
exploratory data analysis, and presentation of results. In terms of
fostering social and collaborative skills in students, I am a founder
and co-leader of &lt;a href=&#34;https://biodata-club.github.io&#34;&gt;BioData-Club&lt;/a&gt;, a collaborative
forum for students and postdocs to share and
teach each other practical skills for success in a research environment.
Through BioDSP, I have informally mentored a number of students through
feedback and collaboration on workshops and presentations. I believe
that by &amp;ldquo;training the trainers&amp;rdquo;, we can more effectively educate
students in these skills in Data Science and Analytics. In order to
accomplish this training of trainers, my course materials are openly
available for use and modification by other teachers. Because of my
dedication to teaching and incorporation of student feedback, I have
consistently high ratings from students in terms of teaching both
long-form courses and short-term workshops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;teaching-academic-courses&#34;&gt;Teaching: Academic Courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;BMI569/669 Data Analytics&lt;/em&gt;, co-taught with Kaiser Permanente (Brian Sikora and Delilah Moore). Summer Quarter, 2015-Present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;NEU640: Python Bootcamp for Neuroscientists.&lt;/em&gt; Taught with Stephen David and Brad Buran. Winter Quarter, 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;BMI551/561: BCBII Statistical Methods in Computational Biology&lt;/em&gt;. Co-instructor. Winter Quarter, 2014-Present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;HSMP410/PHE427: Introduction to Health Informatics.&lt;/em&gt; Course Co-Director. Spring Quarter, 2018-2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;BMI535/635 Management and Processing of Large Scale Data.&lt;/em&gt; Course co-instructor. Winter Quarter, 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;NEUS543 Stats for Neuroscientists&lt;/em&gt;. Course director. Spring Quarter 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;teaching-short-workshopslectures&#34;&gt;Teaching: Short Workshops/Lectures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lectures and Interactive Workshops are linked where possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/BMI535slides&#34;&gt;*Introduction to Relational Databases&lt;/a&gt;. Juypter notebooks introducing relational database concepts (SQL, design, and normalization).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/igraphTutorial&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;iGraph Tutorial in R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Interactive binder notebook introducing students to network analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://biodata-club.github.io/talks/repro_paper.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Practical Guide to Reproducible Papers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. BioData Club Workshop given with Aurora Blucher focusing on making research reproducible. January 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/data_storytelling_bdc&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Storytelling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. BioData Club workshop focusing on making effective visualizations. November 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/gradual_shiny&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Gradual Introduction to Shiny&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Workshop on interactive visualization. Given for PDX R User Group (2018), WNAR 2019, and used at both Reed College and Smith College (2018-2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/laderast/oop_talk&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Objected Oriented Programming in R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Scott Chamberlain and Ted Laderas. Talk/Workshop for PDX R User group, April 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/nhanes_explore&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Scavenger Hunt: NHANES&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Workshop on Exploratory Data Analysis given for BioData Club. January 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dasaderi/python_neurobootcamp&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Python Bootcamp For Neuroscientists&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Ted Laderas, Brad Buran, Daniela Sadieri, Charles Heller, Michael Mooney, Lisa Karstens, and Stephen David. 5 day in-person workshop for introductory Python using Neuroscience data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/BMI523slides/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Actionable Gene Variants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Guest Lecture for BMI 523 Clinical Research Informatics. November 2017 and 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/DSIExplore&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exploratory Data Analysis and Statistics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Workshop with Jessica Minnier for OHSU Data Science Institute 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datacamp.com/courses/rbootcamp&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;R-Bootcamp (tidyverse version on DataCamp)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Active exercises for learning introductory R using the tidyverse. Written with Jessica Minnier and Chester Ismay. 2017. Code and teaching material available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/RBootcamp&#34;&gt;https://github.com/laderast/RBootcamp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Cascadia-R/gRadual-intRoduction-tidyverse&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A gRadual intRoduction to the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Workshop given with Chester Ismay for &lt;a href=&#34;https://cascadiarconf.com&#34;&gt;Cascadia-R 2017&lt;/a&gt; introducing visualization and data cleaning using the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/cvdNight1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Cardiovascular Risk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. 2 night Workshop for Portland State University Students teaching &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/cvdNight1&#34;&gt;Exploratory Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/cvdNight2&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; on a synthetic patient cohort. With David Dorr. May 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/biodata-club/githubPagesTutorial&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Intro to GitHub Pages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Workshop given with Robin Champieux and Eric Leung on setting up a personal
GitHub webpage. April 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/erictleung/tutorial-tidyverse&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Intro To Data Carpentry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Lecture given with Eric Leung about the tidyverse suite of packages for data
wrangling and visualization. March 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/magic-of-markdown&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Magic of Markdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Updated for 2017, including examples of using Zotero as citation manager. March 2017. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495614&#34;&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.495614&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/CSE631Shiny&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shiny Tutorial for CSE631&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Workshop on
developing interactive visualizations using Shiny for CSE631 Data
Visualization course. November 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495621&#34;&gt;DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.495621&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/DreamEDAShiny&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exploring the DREAM Viral Respiratory Dataset using
Shiny&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Tutorial in
Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA) using &lt;em&gt;data.table&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Shiny&lt;/em&gt;.
July 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/shinyEDA&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Exploratory Data Analysis using
Shiny&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Interactive workshop
in using a Shiny Dashboard to conduct EDA on a dataset for BD2K
Advanced Skills Course. May 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495618&#34;&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.495618&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/MLtutorial&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Machine Learning using
Markdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Interactive
workshop using Markdown to explore machine learning algorithms for
BD2K Advanced Skills Course. May 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clustering Algorithms&lt;/em&gt;. Lecture given for Statistical
Methods class. February 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/igraphTutorial&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;iGraph Tutorial&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Introductory lecture for the igraph package in R for
network analysis. November 2015. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495616&#34;&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.495616&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/magic-of-markdown&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Magic of
Markdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Introduction to Markdown in both R, GitHub pages, and Pandoc. BioDSP
October 2015. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495614&#34;&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.495614&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pharmacogenomics&lt;/em&gt; Lecture for Analytics Course, August 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://church.ohsu.edu:3838/laderast/clusteringLecture/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to
Clustering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
Interactive slides for understanding clustering. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495624&#34;&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.495624&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/n0unpdkd5r2tdu7/ggvis-Tutorial.html?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to
ggvis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Lecture/Workshop given for OHSU Bioinformatics Discussion for
Students and Postdocs, April 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/efbwx3jjx89folh/ggplot2Intro.html?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to
ggplot2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
Lecture/Workshop given for OHSU Bioinformatics Discussion for
Students and Postdocs, March 2015. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495622&#34;&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.495622&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/chg6ciknxonp5el/exacloud-tutorial.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exacloud
Tutorial&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; -
A DIY tutorial to running jobs on Exacloud, OHSU&amp;rsquo;s cluster
computing environment. November 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/5ceg6wdrustjoae/tutorialApp.zip&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shiny
Tutorial&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; -
A do it yourself tutorial to try out Shiny, ggplot2, and dplyr for
interactive graphics. September 2015.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.495620&#34;&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.495620&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;R-Bootcamp&lt;/em&gt;. Massively Open Online Course available at:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13756&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13756&lt;/a&gt;. With contributions from
Eric Leung, Dian Chase, Tracy Edinger, Clint Olson, and
Gabrielle Chonoo. 2014-Present&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ddyq88gqh8priv8/insilicotalk-2015.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your In-silico Lab Notebook: Best Practices
2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
Lecture/Workshop given for OHSU BioDSP group, January 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/a4qgwap4jehzs8x/everything-you-wanted-to-know.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everything you wanted to know about bioinformatics but were afraid
to
ask&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
Lecture/Workshop given for OHSU PhD/Postdoc Fellows meeting,
October 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/1my6l8diprnzg4n/lecture_slides_day7_2012-laderas.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;List Comprehensions in
Python&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Lecture given for Bioinformatics Programming and Scripting Course,
Fall 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/jdgbb07xydmxah5/lecture_slides_day10_1027-laderas.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Unit
Testing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Lecture given for Bioinformatics Programming and Scripting Course,
Fall 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Numerical Python (NumPy).&lt;/em&gt; Lecture given for
Bioinformatics Programming and Scripting Course, Fall 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to SciPy.&lt;/em&gt; Lectures given for Bioinformatics
Programming and Scripting Course, Fall 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Introduction to ODE Models.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture given for Systems Biology
Class, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ksnogpxoh22eit8/IntegratingDataforSystemsBiology.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrating Data for Systems
Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Lecture given for Systems Biology Class, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work Smarter, Not Harder: Productivity Tools and You.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture
given for PhD/Postdoctoral meeting, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/xab61u1jo9y9io9/bayesnets-new-laderas.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bayesian
Networks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Lecture given for Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics Class, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/r2j0oi1madn0t1s/GibbsSampler-laderas.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gibbs
Samplers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Lecture given for Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics Class, 2011.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4829530&#34;&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.4829530&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Workshop on Strings and Matrices in R&lt;/em&gt;. Workshop given for
Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics class. 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to R Workshop.&lt;/em&gt; Workshop given for Statistical Methods
in Bioinformatics class. 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/yt8dybaap4sn8hy/03-eda-extended-dependency-analysis.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extended Dependency
Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Presentation given for Information Theory Independent Study 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/kkv4yv2vmwwdqfa/02-conant-laws-of-information.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conant&amp;rsquo;s Laws of Information that Govern
Systems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Presentation given for Information Theory Independent Study, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/jz0gthjbd9cqbrt/01-ashby-conant-variety.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ashby&amp;rsquo;s Law of Requisite Variety and Conant&amp;rsquo;s Information Transfer
in
Regulation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Presentation given for Information Theory Independent Study, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lab: Using Consense-Cluster to explore the Bittner dataset.&lt;/em&gt;
Laboratory given as part of Microarray Analysis Course, OHSU, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;research-statement&#34;&gt;Research Statement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research interests are complex diseases, precision medicine,
applications of systems science (including network analysis and
modeling), and applying data integration to difficult and high-impact
translational research questions. These questions include immune system
profiling in both infectious disease (tuberculosis) and Acute Myeloid Leukemia, understanding drug sensitivity in the context of multiple cancer types (AML, Colorectal, Breast and Head and Neck Cancer), and quantifying expression differences in alcoholic preference. I have worked with a large number of datatypes (high-throughput immunophenotyping,
proteomics, expression, genomic, and functional drug screen data) and
have focused on methods and frameworks integrating these datatypes
within the biological and clinical context of these translational
research questions. My training in biomedical informatics as a master’s
student in Biomedical Informatics, as an NLM Predoctoral Fellow, and as
a NLM Postdoctoral fellow has enabled me to communicate with a wide
variety of collaborators by giving me a strong background in Cancer
Biology, Software Development, and Clinical Systems. Additionally, I am
a strong advocate for Open Science initiatives, most notably the effort
for reproducibility in scientific analysis. To this end, I have
developed multiple novel software pipelines that transparently process
data from raw data to through the final stages of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-publications&#34;&gt;Research: Publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Gwendolyn Swarbrick, David Lewinsohn, Deborah Lewinsohn, Evan Lind and Shannon McWeeney. flowDashboard. status: awaiting submission to Bioinformatics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabrielle Choonoo, Aurora S. Blucher, Samuel Higgins, Mitzi Boardman, Sophia Jeng, Christina Zheng, James Jacobs, Ashley Anderson, Steven Chamberlin,Nathaniel Evans, Myles Vigoda,Benjamin Cordier, Jeffrey W. Tyner, Molly Kulesz-Martin, Shannon K. McWeeney, and &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;. Illuminating Biological Pathways for Drug Targeting in Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma. Submitted to PLOS One. 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David K Edwards, Kevin Watanabe-Smith, Angela Rofelty, Alisa Damnernsawad, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Adam Lamble, Evan F Lind, Andy Kaempf, Motomi Mori, Mara Rosenberg, Amanda d”Almeida, Nicola Long, Anupriya Agarwal, David Tyler Sweeney, Marc Loriaux, Shannon K McWeeney, Jeffrey W Tyner. CSF1R inhibitors exhibit anti-tumor activity in acute myeloid leukemia by blocking paracrine signals from support cells. Blood, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lauren K Brady, David Soong, Evan F Lind, Yoko Kosaka, Adam J Lamble, Michael Schaffer, Brendan P Hodkinson, Clare Lefave, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon K McWeeney, Homer Adams, Yann Abraham, Pegah Safabakhsh, Jeffrey W Tyner, Brian J Druker, Fei Huang. Immunogenomic Exploration of the Acute Myeloid Leukemia Microenvironment Identifies Determinants of T-Cell Fitness. Blood, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicole Vasilevsky, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Jackie Wirz, Bjorn Pederson, David A Dorr, William Hersh, Shannon McWeeney, Melissa Haendel. Training future biocurators through data science trainings and open educational resources.  F1000Research, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Lamble, Yoko Kosaka, Fei Huang, Kate Sasser, Cristina Tognon, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon McWeeney, Marc Loriaux, Brian J Druker, Jeffrey Tyner, Evan Lind. Comprehensive characterization of VISTA expression in patients with acute myeloid leukemia.. Journal of Clinical Oncology, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Lamble, Yoko Kosaka, Fei Huang, A Kate Sasser, Homer Adams, Cristina E Tognon, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon K McWeeney, Marc M Loriaux, Jeffrey W Tyner, Brian J Druker, Evan F Lind. Enhanced VISTA expression in a subset of patients with acute myeloid leukemia. Blood, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching data science fundamentals through realistic synthetic clinical cardiovascular data.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Nicole Vasilevsky, Bjorn Pederson, Shannon McWeeney, Melissa Haendel, and David Dorr. Submitted to JAMIA. BioRxiv Link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/12/12/232611&#34;&gt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/12/12/232611&lt;/a&gt;. 2017. Contribution: First author: helped conceive study, designed bayesian network, developed course material based on dataset. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrated functional and mass spectrometry-based flow cytometric phenotyping to describe the immune microenvironment in acute myeloid leukemia&lt;/em&gt;. Adam J Lamble, Matt Dietz, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon McWeeney, Evan F Lind. Journal of Immunological Methods. 2017. Contribution: developed informatics and visualization methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fgene.2015.00341/abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Network-Based Model of Oncogenic Collaboration to Predict Drug
Sensitivity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Laura Heiser and Kemal Sonmez. Featured article in
Frontiers in Genetics. 2015. Contribution: First author, developer
of methodology and visualization framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bloodjournal.org/content/128/22/2829?sso-checked=true&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mass Cytometry As a Modality to Identify Candidates for Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Therapy within Acute Myeloid Leukemia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Adam Lamble, Yoko Kosaka, Fei Huang, A Kate Sasser, Homer Adams III, Cristina E. Tognon, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon K. McWeeney, Marc M. Loriaux, Jeffrey W. Tyner, Brian J. Druker and Evan F. Lind. Blood, 2016. Contribution: contributed to panel development of CyTOF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/p92dn5buctlyqpc/nm.3967.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Consensus Molecular Subtypes of Colorectal
Cancer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;
123 citations, Impact Factor 30.36. Justin Guinney, Rodrigo
Dienstmann, Xin Wang, Aurélien de Reyniès, Andreas Schlicker,
Charlotte Soneson, Laetitia Marisa, Paul Roepman, Gift Nyamundanda,
Paolo Angelino, Brian M. Bot, Jeffrey S. Morris, Iris Simon, Sarah
Gerster, Evelyn Fessler, Felipe de Sousa e Melo, Edoardo Missiaglia,
Hena Ramay, David Barras, Krisztian Homicsko, Dipen Maru,
Ganiraju C. Manyam, Bradley Broom, Valerie Boige, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;,
Ramon Salazar, Joe W. Gray, Douglas Hanahan, Josep Tabernero, Rene
Bernards, Stephen H. Friend, Pierre Laurent-Puig, Jan P. Medema,
Anguraj Sadanandam, Lodewyk Wessels, Mauro Delorenzi, Scott Kopetz,
Louis Vermeulen, and Sabine Tejpar. Nature Medicine. 2015.
Contribution: mapped and analyzed OMICs data to consensus cancer subtypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/70z4yp3k36y9bmu/laderast_between_pathways.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Between Pathways and Networks lies
Context&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Impact Factor: 1.76. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Guanming Wu, and
Shannon McWeeney. Science Progress. 2015. Contribution: first
author, conceptualized and wrote manuscript.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.3184/003685015X14368898634462&#34;&gt;doi:10.3184/003685015X14368898634462&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/t9ic1rpirja4xqv/computational-exon-laderas.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computational detection of alternative exon
usage&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;
8 citations, Impact Factor: 3.398. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Nicole A Walter,
Michael Mooney, Kristina Vartanian, Priscila Darakjian, Kari Buck,
Chris Harrington, John Belknap, Robert Hitzemann, and
Shannon McWeeney. Frontiers in Neurogenomics. 2011. Article 69.
PMID 21625610. Contribution: First author, developer of methodology.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fnins.2011.00069&#34;&gt;doi:10.3389/fnins.2011.00069&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/2v0h7ufxu1664yt/preponderance-SNPs-walter-laderas.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;High throughput sequencing in mice: a platform comparison
identifies a preponderance of cryptic
SNPs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;
19 Citations, Impact Factor 3.87. Nicole A Walter, Daniel Bottomly,
&lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Michael Mooney, Priscila Darakjian, Robert P
Searles, Christina Harrington, Shannon K McWeeney, Robert Hitzemann,
Kari J Buck. BMC Genomics. 2009 Aug 17;10:379. Contribution: helped
develop methodology of manuscript, conceptualization.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-10-379&#34;&gt;doi:10.1186/1471-2164-10-379&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TandTRAQ: An open-source tool for integrated protein identification
and quantitation&lt;/em&gt;. 14 citations, Impact Factor 5.766. &lt;strong&gt;Ted
Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Cory Bystrom, Debra McMillen, Guang Fan and
Shannon McWeeney. Bioinformatics. 2007. Contribution: first author,
designed software framework.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btm467&#34;&gt;doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btm467&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/v56bomf1ijhmds3/Laderas_McWeeney07.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A consensus framework for exploring microarray data using multiple
clustering
methods&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;
16 citations. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt; and Shannon McWeeney. OMICS: A Journal
of Integrative Biology. OMICS: A Journal of Integrative Biology. 2007. 116-128. Contribution: first author, developed methodology for comparison analysis.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/omi.2006.0008&#34;&gt;doi:10.1089/omi.2006.0008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-software-sole-developer-unless-specified&#34;&gt;Research: Software (Sole Developer unless specified)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RBootcamp (free online version)&lt;/em&gt;. Available for free at &lt;a href=&#34;https://r-bootcamp.netlify.com&#34;&gt;https://r-bootcamp.netlify.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;burro&lt;/em&gt;. R/Shiny package for teaching exploratory data analysis. &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/burro&#34;&gt;http://laderast.github.io/burro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;decampr&lt;/em&gt;. R package for converting from DataCamp course format to Binder/Gatsby based framework. &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/laderast/decampr&#34;&gt;http://github.com/laderast/decampr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;cvdRiskData&lt;/em&gt;. Synthetic dataset for teach fundamentals in data science. Available as an R package at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/cvdRiskData&#34;&gt;https://github.com/laderast/cvdRiskData&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RBootcamp (tidyverse version)&lt;/em&gt;. DataCamp active exercises for learning introductory R using the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;. With Jessica Minnier and Chester Ismay. Available for free at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datacamp.com/courses/rbootcamp&#34;&gt;https://www.datacamp.com/courses/rbootcamp&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https:://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.854727&#34;&gt;https:://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.854727&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;flowDashboard&lt;/em&gt;. Visualization framework in R/Shiny and processing
pipeline for CyTOF and flow cytometry data. Currently under embargo,
waiting publication and submission. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.260421&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.260421&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Surrogate Network Explorer for Head and Neck Cancer&lt;/em&gt;. Interactive
visualization framework for understanding network effects in Head
and Neck cancer. Awaiting validation, publication, and submission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;R-Bootcamp: Introduction to R&lt;/em&gt;. Script-based introductory MOOC
to R. With contributions from Eric Leung, Dian Chase, Tracy Edinger,
Clint Olson, and Gabrielle Chonoo.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13756&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13756&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Surrogate Mutation Explorer&lt;/em&gt;. R/Shiny Interactive Application for
exploring surrogate mutations.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13757&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13757&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SurrogateMutation&lt;/em&gt;. R Package for mapping mutations and copy number
alterations to networks and associated statistics.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17303&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17303&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consense-Cluster&lt;/em&gt;. R Package for comparing clustering output
across algorithms. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17304&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17304&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ExonModelStrain&lt;/em&gt;. RPackage for detecting alternative exon usage
between two strains of mice.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17305&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17305&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TandTRAQ&lt;/em&gt;. Perl Script for mapping iTRAQ protein quantitation to
X!Tandem peptides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-lectures-invited-lectures-are-indicated&#34;&gt;Research: Lectures (Invited Lectures are Indicated)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/ief_talk_2019/&#34;&gt;Conversations about Sleep: Clinical Data Wrangling&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Nicole Weiskopf, and Eilis Boudreau. Talk given for American Medical Informatics Association&amp;rsquo;s Informatics Educator&amp;rsquo;s Conference, June 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clincal Data Wrangling: Active/Didactic Learning. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Nicole Weiskopf, and Eilis Boudreau. Talk given for Symposium on Data Science and Statistics. June 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/csv_talk/#1&#34;&gt;Data Scavenger Hunts: Learning about datasets together&lt;/a&gt;. Talk given for CSV Conference 2019, May 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/osu_talk/#1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching Bioinformatics Students about Clinical Data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Invited talk for OSU Center for Genome Research and Computing Spring Conference, April 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/oop_talk&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Object Oriented Systems in R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Ted Laderas and Scott Chamberlain. Talk given for Portland R User Group. April 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/DS4BS/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Science for Basic Scientists&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Invited talk for OHSU Symposium on Educational Excellence. April 2017. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4876811.v3&#34;&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.4876811.v3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ls6agg9uy2b6wp4/big-data-talk_laderas.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moving From Big Data to Knowledge: Implications for the Health
Care and Biomedical
Sciences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
Invited Lecture given for BioCatalyst Advanced Training workshop at
Oregon Bioscience Association. June 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Surrogate Mutations and Drug Sensitivity in Breast Cancer
Cell Lines.&lt;/em&gt; Plenary talk at NLM Training Conference, Pittburgh, PA,
June 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Connecting Genotypes to Drug Sensitivities in HER2 Positive Cancer
Cell Lines.&lt;/em&gt; Doctoral Defense, OHSU, March 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Understanding Expression Differences in RPPA Data: Implications for
ODE Models.&lt;/em&gt; Presentation at Integrative Cancer Biology Program
retreat 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Connecting Genotypes to Drug Sensitivity in HER2+ Breast Cancer
Cell Lines.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture/Dissertation proposal given for PhD/Postdoc
Meeting January 2012 and March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Connecting Genotypes to Drug Sensitivity in Breast Cancer
Cell Lines.&lt;/em&gt; Invited presentation at Integrative Cancer Biology
Program retreat, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/bi14mo1ahr4yod8/symposium-laderas.pptx?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are Models For? Making Sense of Systems
Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Predoctoral Symposium. 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two kinds of Robustness.&lt;/em&gt; Presentation given to Bioinformatics
Development Group, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portland Alcohol Research Center Scientific Advisory Board Review:
Bioinformatics &amp;amp; Statistics.&lt;/em&gt; Presentation given to PARC SAB,
OHSU, 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An introduction to trend analysis and consensus modules for
systems biology.&lt;/em&gt; Presentation given with Sophia Jeng to
Mathematical Modeling Core for Systems Virology, OHSU 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An introduction to Consensus Modules for Systems Biology.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture
given with Sophia Jeng to Bioinformatics Development Group,
OHSU, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Introduction to Sloppy Systems Biology.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture given to
Bioinformatics Development Group, OHSU, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Simulated and Synthetic Data for Benchmarking Algorithms.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture
given as part of Bioinformatics Methods class, OHSU, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to QPACA Pathway Analysis Software and BioPAX.&lt;/em&gt; Talk
given at 2006 caBIG Annual Meeting, Washington DC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consense: A software package for utilizing multiple clustering
methods on Microarray Data.&lt;/em&gt; Talk given at OHSU Student Research
Forum, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-posters-and-abstracts&#34;&gt;Research: Posters and Abstracts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/equal_vis&#34;&gt;Democratizing Data Science using LearnR and Shiny&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt; and Jessica Minnier. RStudio Conference, January 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/posters/7-1045&#34;&gt;flowDashboard: An interactive dashboard for comparative flow analysis&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Gwendolyn Swarbrick, Deborah Lewinsohn, David Lewinsohn, Evan Lind, BOSC (Bioinformatics Open Source Conference), July 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.causeweb.org/cause/ecots/ecots18/posters/3-03&#34;&gt;Mixing Active Learning and Lecturing: Using Interactive Visualization as a Teaching Tool&lt;/a&gt;. ECOTS (Electronic Conference on Teaching Statistics) e-poster session, June 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting your hands dirty with data&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Melissa
Haendel, Bjorn Pederson, Jackie Wirz, William Hersh, David A. Dorr,
Shannon McWeeney. Big Data to Knowledge (BD2K) All Hands meeting,
November 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4235594.v1&#34;&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.4235594.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Get Real: A synthetic dataset illustrating clinical and
genetic covariates.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Nicole Vasilevsky, Melissa
Haendel, Shannon McWeeney and David A. Dorr. BD2K All Hands meeting,
November 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4239959.v1&#34;&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.4239959.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mass Cytometry as a Modality to Identify Candidates for Immune
Checkpoint Inhibitor Therapy within Acute Myeloid Leukemia.&lt;/em&gt; Adam
Lamble, Fei Huang, Kate Sasser, Homer Adams III, Cristina E. Tognon,
&lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon McWeeney, Marc Loriaux, Jeffery W. Tyner,
Brian J. Druker, and Evan F. Lind. American Society for Hematology,
December 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enhanced VISTA Expression in a Subset of Patients with Acute
Myeloid Leukemia&lt;/em&gt;. Adam Lamble, Yoko Kosaka, Fei Huang, Kate Sasser,
Homer Adams III, Cristina E. Tognon, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon
McWeeney, Marc Loriaux, Jeffery W. Tyner, Brian J. Druker, and
Evan F. Lind. American Society for Hematology, December 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Improving Knowledge Discovery Through Development of Big Data to
Knowledge Skills Courses and Open Educational Resources&lt;/em&gt;. Nicole
Vasilevsky, Shannon McWeeney, William Hersh, David A. Dorr, &lt;strong&gt;Ted
Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Jackie Wirz, Bjorn Pederson and Melissa Haendel. Poster for
BICC Building 25th Anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consensus molecular subtyping through a community of experts
advances unsupervised gene expression-based disease classification
and facilitates clinical translation.&lt;/em&gt; Justin Guinney, Rodrigo
Dienstmann, Xin Wang, Aurelien de Reynies, Andreas Schlicker,
Charlotte Soneson, Laetitia Marisa, Paul Roepman, Gift Nyamundanda,
Paolo Angelino, Brian Bot, Jeffrey S. Morris, Iris Simon, Sarah
Gerster, Evelyn Fessler, Felipe de Sousa e Melo, Edoardo Missiaglia,
Hena Ramay, David Barras, Krisztian Homicsko, Dipen Maru, Ganiraju
Manyam, Bradley Broom, Valerie Boige, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Ramon
Salazar, Joe W. Gray, Josep Tabernero, Rene Bernards, Stephen
Friend, Pierre Laurent-Puig, Jan P. Medema, Anguraj Sadanandam,
Lodewyk Wessels, Mauro Delorenzi, Scott Kopetz, Louis Vermeulen and
Sabine Tejpar. American Association for Cancer Research Conference,
August 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Network-Based Model of Oncogenic Collaboration for Prediction of
Drug Sensitivity.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;. RECOMB/ISCB Conference on
Regulatory and Systems Genomics, November 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/y3rbkygjn41qsd6/poster-laderas-nlm-2013.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrating proteomics and genomic data to illuminate the effects
of Lapatinib in HER2+
Cells&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt; and Kemal Sonmez. National Library of Medicine
Training Conference, Utah, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4829749.v1&#34;&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.4829749.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/nhixsztlg1oo4z6/poster-laderas-ismb-2012.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrating to Interact: Using Reconstructability Analysis to
Integrate Genomic and Proteomic Data to Predict Drug
Sensitivity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt; and Kemal Sonmez. Intelligent Systems in Molecular
Biology conference, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4830007.v1&#34;&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.4830007.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tales from the Cryptic Snp: High Throughput Sequencing of DBA/2J
and C57BL/6J mouse chromosome 1 reveals an abundance
of polymorphisms.&lt;/em&gt; Kari J. Buck, Nicole A.R. Walter, Daniel
Bottomly, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Michael Mooney, Priscila Darakjian,
Shannon McWeeney, Robert Hitzemann. Research Society on Alcoholism
Annual Meeting. 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A computational framework for the detection of alternative exon
usage using Affymetrix Exon arrays.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Michael
Mooney, Nikki Walter, Kristina Vartanian, Christina Harrington,
Priscila Darakijan, John Belknap, Robert Hitzemann, and
Shannon McWeeney. Intelligent Systems in Molecular Biology
conference, Toronto, July 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) proteomics in children with acute
lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL).&lt;/em&gt; Robert C Trueworthy, Linda C Stork,
Yanping Zhong, Sharon Pine, Yousif Matloub, &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Shannon
McWeeney, and Guang Fan. Poster 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A metrics-based low-level preprocessing framework for
proteomics data.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Solange Mongoue-Tchokote, Veena
Rajaraman, Kimberly Sellers, Cory Bystrom and Shannon McWeeney.
Bioconductor Developer&amp;rsquo;s Meeting, Seattle, Washington, August 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A diagnostic test suite for the RProteomics statistical routines.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt;, Solange Mongoue-Tchokote, Veena Rajaraman, Kimberly
Sellers and Shannon McWeeney. caBIG annual meeting, Washington DC,
April 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consense-Cluster: a framework for comparing and benchmarking
clustering algorithms.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ted Laderas&lt;/strong&gt; and Shannon McWeeney.
Bioconductor Developer&amp;rsquo;s Meeting, Seattle, Washington, August 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;service-statement&#34;&gt;Service Statement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a strong supporter of service at OHSU and beyond. I currently
participate in the DMICE BCB (Bioinformatics and Computational Biology)
Faculty Division meeting, the DMICE Mentoring committee, and have
participated in the BCB Curriculum Retreat in order to plan upcoming
coursework at DMICE. As a Pacific Islander, I have a unique viewpoint
about diversity and I hope to enhance equal opportunity by participating
in OHSU’s Diversity Advisory Council (DAC). Beyond OHSU, I believe that
we need to increase public engagement of science and increase outreach
and mentoring of next-generation science students, especially from
disadvantaged populations will enable these students to succeed in
STEM-based careers. As a former student of Saturday Academy&amp;rsquo;s scientific
mentoring program, I want to contribute back to this community and
engage potential STEM students through student outreach and mentoring. I
am also involved in outreach through the development of course material
for the Biocatalyst training program through Oregon Bioscience
Association, which provides bioscience training for unemployed or
under-employed professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service: Accomplishments/Appointments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-organizer (2019-) of the Portland R User Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently serving on DMICE Assessment Planning committee, DMICE BCB Division committee DMICE BMI Curriculum Committee, OHSU Computational Forum planning committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-Founder of &lt;a href=&#34;https://biodata-club.github.io&#34;&gt;BioData Club&lt;/a&gt; group for students, postdocs, and staff at OHSU. Managed speakers, developed free workshops for students, and provided feedback for student presentations. BioData Club is currently at 109 members ranging from OHSU and PSU staff, faculty, students and postdocs, providing a unique opportunity to share information and provide peer mentoring to students across the organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-organizer for &lt;a href=&#34;https://cascadiarconf.com&#34;&gt;Cascadia R Conference&lt;/a&gt; 2017 and 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributor to instructor lesson materials to &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org&#34;&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editor at Large for &lt;a href=&#34;http://radiandata.org/&#34;&gt;Radian Data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participant/Instructor for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/daniellecrobinson/Data-Rescue-PDX&#34;&gt;PDX Data Rescue/Open Data Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation support for &lt;a href=&#34;http://portland.sciencehackday.org&#34;&gt;Science Hack Day PDX 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developed coursework for unemployed or underemployed IT workers in both biosciences and healthcare for Oregon Bioscience Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewer for JAMIA, BMC Bioinformatics, and Neurocomputing, and AMIA Symposium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mentees include Jason Li (summer mentor), Eisa Mahyari (ongoing mentor), Lawrence Hsu (co-advisor), Connor Smith (co-advisor), Gabrielle Choonoo (thesis committee), and Sean Babcock (thesis committee).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;employment-experience&#34;&gt;Employment Experience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assistant Professor&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiolgy, OHSU, 2017-present.
&lt;em&gt;Postdoctoral Researcher&lt;/em&gt;, OHSU Knight Cancer Institute, 2014-2017.
&lt;em&gt;Instructor&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology. 2015-Present.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;NLM Postdoctoral Fellow&lt;/em&gt;, Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University. 2014-2015.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Visiting Scientist&lt;/em&gt;, Sage Bionetworks, Seattle Washington. 2014-2015.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;NLM Predoctoral Fellow&lt;/em&gt;, Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology, Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University. 2009–2014.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics Developer/Project Manager&lt;/em&gt;, OHSU Knight Cancer Institute, Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University. 2003-2009.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Teaching Assistant/Computer Programmer/Server Admin&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Medical Informatics &amp;amp; Clinical Epidemiology, Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University. 2001-2002.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Research Assistant/Computer Programmer&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Molecular Medicine, Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University. 1999-2001.
&lt;em&gt;Research Assistant/Teaching Assistant&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Chemistry, Reed College. 1998&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;ongoing-research-support&#34;&gt;Ongoing Research Support**&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T15LM009461 (supplement)	
Hersh (PI)	
7/01/1992-6/01/2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biomedical Informatics Research Training at Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University.&lt;/em&gt; Supplement to develop Data Science Materials for T15 training grant. Role: educational developer and instructor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1U24TR002306-01	
Haendel (PI)	
9/01/2017-9/01/2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A National Center for Digital Health Informatics Innovation&lt;/em&gt;. We propose to create a national network for enabling digital health research, innovation, and continuous improvement. The goal is to use information science to impact the way that health care functions and the lives of those it serves. Role: education, software development, and data management advocate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1U54CA224019-01	
Tyner (PI)	
10/01/2017-10/01/2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tumor intrinsic and microenvironmental mechanisms driving drug combination efficacy and resistance in AML&lt;/em&gt;. Most patients with acute myeloid leukemia (AML) eventually die when their disease becomes resistant to conventional or even newer treatments. Our proposed studies will shed light on the mechanisms of drug resistance, both within the tumor and in the surrounding environment. This knowledge will help identify more effective therapies — involving combinations of two drugs — that will avoid drug resistance and provide better outcomes for patients with AML. Role: Computational Biologist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Completed Research Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No # assigned	
Druker (PI)	
5/1/2013-5/31/2018
The Leukemia &amp;amp; Lymphoma Society
&lt;em&gt;Beat AML: Precision Medicine for AML Based on Functional Genomics&lt;/em&gt;. The major goals of this project is to transform our approach to AML treatment through a deeper understanding of the diversity of the underlying molecular causes of disease and to bring targeted therapies to AML patients through 1) understanding the spectrum of genetic lesions and molecular drivers, 2) functionally annotating drug sensitivity, and 3) Initiating clinical trials with combinations of drugs in refractory patients. Role: Computational Biologist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T15LM009461 	
Hersh (PI)	
7/01/1992-6/30/2017
&lt;em&gt;Biomedical Informatics Research Training at Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University&lt;/em&gt;.
Predoctoral and postdoctoral training grant in biomedical informatics.
Role: Predoctoral Fellow (2009-14); Postdoctoral Fellow (2014-2015)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OPP1131709 	
Lewinsohn (PI)	
10/26/2015-10/31/2017
Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundation					
&lt;em&gt;Targeting MAIT cells for TB vaccines&lt;/em&gt;. This proposal is designed to establish whether or not a vaccine targeting Mucosal Associated Invariant (MAIT) can be used to prevent tuberculosis (TB). Role: Computational Biologist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BD2K Training Grant 
Dorr, D (Co-PI), Haendel, M (Co-PI), McWeeney, S (Co-PI) 
2015-2017 
&lt;em&gt;Big Data to Knowledge&lt;/em&gt;. The goal of this project is to develop training materials in data science. Role: educational developer and instructor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;awards&#34;&gt;Awards&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NLM Predoctoral Fellowship. 2009-2013.&lt;br&gt;
NLM Postdoctoral Fellowship. 2014-2015.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
