<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ted Laderas, PhD on Ted Laderas, PhD</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ted Laderas, PhD on Ted Laderas, PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Cascadia-R 2018: How we planned it and the reasons why</title>
      <link>/2018/06/09/cascadia-r-2018-how-we-planned-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/09/cascadia-r-2018-how-we-planned-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cascadiarconf.com&#34;&gt;Cascadia-R 2018&lt;/a&gt; has come and gone. This year we tried our best to make it as inclusive, welcoming, and friendly as we could. Considering we had 224 participants this time around, I’d say it was a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just thought I would do a little write up of some of the things we did and why we did them in our conference. I’m hoping it will be useful for other conference planners to create a welcoming environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We created a pull plan based on what we learned last year.&lt;/strong&gt; Because last year was pretty chaotic in terms of planning, we decided to try to make a pull plan this year. &lt;a href=&#34;https://esub.com/pull-planning-how-lean-construction-practices-can-improve-project-efficiency/&#34;&gt;Pull planning is a project management technique&lt;/a&gt; in which you work backwards from absolute deadlines (from the day of the conference). Doing so spaces out a lot of the work and makes things potentially more dividable across a group. I’ve made our &lt;a href=&#34;https://trello.com/b/lphkRbnU/cascadia-r-pull-plan&#34;&gt;pull plan public&lt;/a&gt; so other conference planners can see what we did and the timing it took to organize the conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find sponsorship money.&lt;/strong&gt; We ran last year on a shoestring, using only about $3500. We realized that to make the conference more inclusive this year, we had to get sponsorship money. Childcare and diversity scholarships cost money. We wanted sponsors who had values that aligned with our inclusion goals. Lilly Winfree was especially great at finding sponsors who were in tune with what we wanted to accomplish with our conference. Sponsorship also allowed us to pay for lunch for everyone, which we couldn’t last year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide childcare.&lt;/strong&gt; We wanted parents to be able to attend, so we got &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.divcarepdx.com&#34;&gt;DivCare&lt;/a&gt; to provide childcare for them in our building. DivCare provided childcare for 8 children, and we had some grateful parents who were happy they could attend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diversity Committee&lt;/strong&gt;. We did this last year, but we had more money this year for diversity scholarships for those who might not be able to attend. I think next year we might think about reaching out to more STEM groups, but I think the real challenge is finding how to get those diverse students who might not even know about data science in and how to properly host and support them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get rid of longer form talks. Keynotes and Lightning talks only.&lt;/strong&gt; This is probably the most controversial choice that we made. However, we realized that the 10-15 minute talks we had in 2017 were mostly academic ones. Honestly, there are already too many academic conferences out there. We wanted a format that was more accessible and encouraged discussion afterwards, so we stayed with the lightning talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have keynote speakers show newcomers how to join the R Community.&lt;/strong&gt; We chose Kara Woo and Alison Hill as our keynote speakers for a very specific reason: we wanted to encourage people new to R that they could learn things. Alison gave a &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/apreshill/big-magic-with-r-creative-learning-beyond-fear&#34;&gt;wonderful talk about ways to approach learning R&lt;/a&gt;; Kara gave a great talk talking about &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/karawoo/2018-06-02-cascadiarconf&#34;&gt;how to contribute to various R-projects on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, especially the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; suite of packages. What I really liked about both their talks was that they emphasized learning by doing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moar workshops.&lt;/strong&gt; We wanted beginners and intermediate people feel like they were learning something, and in a safe learning environment. One piece of feedback from last year was that people wanted more workshops. We created a beginner track and an intermediate track for workshops. I would just like to say that none of the workshop people got paid for their work, and I do wish that some of the attendees realized that before they provided feedback such as “BORING” (seriously? please realize that there are people who develop these, and constructive feedback is always better). All of these workshops were done for free as labors of love, unlike conferences like ODSC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organize Volunteers&lt;/strong&gt;. We had lots of volunteers this year and we finally were able to figure out roles for everyone to do (registration, nametags, TAs, etc).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do a visualization fest that wasn’t competitive&lt;/strong&gt;. I know that everyone loves bake-offs like the &lt;em&gt;DREAM Challenges&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Kaggle&lt;/em&gt;, but we felt that having a competition was in conflict with the community building we wanted to do with the conference.That, and Tidy Tuesday, were the inspirations for the &lt;em&gt;cRaggy&lt;/em&gt;. We wanted people to share ideas with each other and to be constructive with each other. We had &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lopierra/biketown&#34;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cwickham/cRaggyhttps://github.com/cwickham/cRaggy&#34;&gt;great&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WatanabeSmith/BIKETOWN_CascadiaR&#34;&gt;short&lt;/a&gt; talks talking about their approach to the visualization and we shared the data with Tidy Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk honestly about impostor syndrome&lt;/strong&gt;. We had a panel with three people (the wonderful Paige Bailey, Kevin Watanabe-Smith and Lilly Winfree) and they all talked about how they deal with impostor syndrome. Some of the lessons are: you feel like less of an impostor the more you do and the more you participate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have more downtime&lt;/strong&gt;. We had feedback last year that there wasn’t enough social time. We built more breaks into the schedule and had a third room (the hack room) dedicated to the “hallway track”: often the best times we’ve had conferences is when we play hooky from conference activities. Some people suggested this year that there maybe was too much downtime. I would say to that, there’s always more opportunity to meet people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s why Cascadia R was the way it was this year. In another blog post, I’ll talk more about the fun things that happened this year and our hopes for the next year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Time at the rOpenSci Unconf</title>
      <link>/my-time-at-the-ropensci-unconf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/my-time-at-the-ropensci-unconf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought I&amp;rsquo;d summarize my time at the rOpenSci unconf. Overall, I had a really great time and I commend the rOpenSci crew for putting together an event that was really welcoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I proposed building a Synthetic Data Generation framework, based on some previous work I&amp;rsquo;ve done with Bayesian Networks. In retrospect, I think I should have had a more clear plan for showing people how it worked - maybe we could have just installed the current package and had team members generate small datasets. I only had a vague idea of how to perhaps parametrize the network, which seemed to lose people even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I think I had a bit of a brain meltdown and I decided to bow out of this framework and help the flow cytometry crew (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/seaaan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sean Hughes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/juyeongkim&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ju Yeong Kim&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/malisas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Malisa Smith&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/angela-li&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Angela Li&lt;/a&gt;) with the &lt;code&gt;umapr&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I learn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You cannot meet everyone, no matter how hard you try.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s probably better to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Care and Self Compassion in Academia</title>
      <link>/2018/06/05/self-care-and-self-compassion-in-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/05/self-care-and-self-compassion-in-academia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I am not writing the following to complain, or excuse any past behavior. I am writing this just to be honest and transparent about my current struggles in academia. I hope it helps someone, or encourages other to seek help.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I haven&amp;rsquo;t really been feeling all that well the past few months. Right now I am plagued with feelings that I am doing my work as an Assistant Professor wrong. I struggle with this persistent voice in my head that even when I am working at full tilt and beyond, that it&amp;rsquo;s not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of my life, I have had chronic depression. I am a high functioning depressive; I have managed to get things done when I am depressed. However, this effort comes at the cost of self-care. I really think that some past posts have really come from a place of high stress and high anxiety. I apologize for &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/2018/01/15/if-you-want-to-talk-with-me-for-an-informational-interview/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the harsh tone of this post&lt;/a&gt;. I am also struggling with burnout at this point. I am beginning to feel like a lot of my efforts to encourage interdisciplinary collaborations are not feeling very productive. Part of this has to do with internal politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think my depression is an excuse for my past behavior. The lack of self-care, however, is a major cause. When I don&amp;rsquo;t take care of myself, I reach a place of high stress and high anxiety and I can&amp;rsquo;t think straight. If I have been hurtful or bullying to others in any way because of this, I apologize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still struggle with impostor syndrome. I do think that in many ways, this struggle has helped me become more compassionate as a teacher, remembering what concepts I struggled with. I have been trying my best to keep up with the added responsibilities of a faculty member: mentoring students, writing new course material, doing outreach, and also trying to keep the lights on by doing research (I won&amp;rsquo;t get into grant writing here; that&amp;rsquo;s another major depressive kettle of fish). I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve currently been a disappointment as a faculty member so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently in therapy, which has been very helpful in understanding what problems I can address and what problems that are currently endemic to the academic system. I don&amp;rsquo;t know of any other field where one can accomplish a lot yet still feel like a failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest thing for me is saying no, especially to students. But I realize that I can&amp;rsquo;t really be my best for students without taking care of myself. That balance between being considerate of others and also being considerate of my self is something that I am struggling with as a faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess my point being is that I need to reframe saying no as being protective of myself and my current students rather than registering the disappointment when I say no. I&amp;rsquo;d like to help people, but I can help people better when I&amp;rsquo;m feeling well and better. Part of this may be coming to grips that academia may not be my place in the world if it demands that I sacrifice my mental health just to stay where I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for the time being, I&amp;rsquo;d like to focus on getting better and feeling better. For your sake and mine. I will try to welcome newcomers to data science the best I can - just realize that what I may be able to do for you is a little limited right now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>group_by/summarize: Not just for numeric values!</title>
      <link>/2018/05/24/group-by-summarize-not-just-for-numeric-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/24/group-by-summarize-not-just-for-numeric-values/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even though I’ve been using the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; for a couple of years, there’s always a couple new applications of &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; verbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one, in retrospect, is pretty simple. I had a one to many table that I wanted to collapse, tidy-style. Let’s look at the &lt;code&gt;diamonds&lt;/code&gt; dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;diamonds %&amp;gt;% select(color, cut)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 53,940 x 2
##    color cut      
##    &amp;lt;ord&amp;gt; &amp;lt;ord&amp;gt;    
##  1 E     Ideal    
##  2 E     Premium  
##  3 E     Good     
##  4 I     Premium  
##  5 J     Good     
##  6 J     Very Good
##  7 I     Very Good
##  8 H     Very Good
##  9 E     Fair     
## 10 H     Very Good
## # ... with 53,930 more rows&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we wanted to collapse all the entries for each color into a single line? There’s 7 different colors, so we can use a combination of &lt;code&gt;group_by&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;color&lt;/code&gt; and use the &lt;code&gt;paste()&lt;/code&gt; function within &lt;code&gt;summarize()&lt;/code&gt; to get what we want, which I’ve called &lt;code&gt;all_colors&lt;/code&gt; here. By specifying the &lt;code&gt;collapse&lt;/code&gt; argument, we can specify the delimiter within that column:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;diamonds %&amp;gt;% select(color, cut) %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(color) %&amp;gt;% 
  summarize(all_colors=
              paste(cut, collapse=&amp;quot;;&amp;quot;))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 7 x 2
##   color all_colors                                                        
##   &amp;lt;ord&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;                                                             
## 1 D     Very Good;Very Good;Very Good;Good;Good;Premium;Premium;Ideal;Ide…
## 2 E     Ideal;Premium;Good;Fair;Premium;Premium;Very Good;Very Good;Very …
## 3 F     Premium;Very Good;Very Good;Very Good;Good;Premium;Very Good;Very…
## 4 G     Very Good;Ideal;Ideal;Very Good;Premium;Premium;Ideal;Very Good;I…
## 5 H     Very Good;Very Good;Very Good;Good;Good;Very Good;Good;Very Good;…
## 6 I     Premium;Very Good;Ideal;Good;Premium;Ideal;Ideal;Ideal;Ideal;Very…
## 7 J     Good;Very Good;Good;Ideal;Ideal;Good;Good;Very Good;Very Good;Ver…&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Ken Butler, who pointed out that the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; way (via &lt;code&gt;stringr&lt;/code&gt;) is to use &lt;code&gt;str_c&lt;/code&gt; instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;diamonds %&amp;gt;% select(color, cut) %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(color) %&amp;gt;% 
  summarize(all_colors=
              stringr::str_c(cut, collapse=&amp;quot;;&amp;quot;))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 7 x 2
##   color all_colors                                                        
##   &amp;lt;ord&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;                                                             
## 1 D     Very Good;Very Good;Very Good;Good;Good;Premium;Premium;Ideal;Ide…
## 2 E     Ideal;Premium;Good;Fair;Premium;Premium;Very Good;Very Good;Very …
## 3 F     Premium;Very Good;Very Good;Very Good;Good;Premium;Very Good;Very…
## 4 G     Very Good;Ideal;Ideal;Very Good;Premium;Premium;Ideal;Very Good;I…
## 5 H     Very Good;Very Good;Very Good;Good;Good;Very Good;Good;Very Good;…
## 6 I     Premium;Very Good;Ideal;Good;Premium;Ideal;Ideal;Ideal;Ideal;Very…
## 7 J     Good;Very Good;Good;Ideal;Ideal;Good;Good;Very Good;Very Good;Ver…&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if we wanted to just get the unique values of the cuts in a single line, we can use &lt;code&gt;unique&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;diamonds %&amp;gt;% select(color, cut) %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(color) %&amp;gt;% 
  summarize(all_colors=
              paste(unique(cut), collapse=&amp;quot;;&amp;quot;))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 7 x 2
##   color all_colors                       
##   &amp;lt;ord&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;                            
## 1 D     Very Good;Good;Premium;Ideal;Fair
## 2 E     Ideal;Premium;Good;Fair;Very Good
## 3 F     Premium;Very Good;Good;Fair;Ideal
## 4 G     Very Good;Ideal;Premium;Good;Fair
## 5 H     Very Good;Good;Premium;Fair;Ideal
## 6 I     Premium;Very Good;Ideal;Good;Fair
## 7 J     Good;Very Good;Ideal;Premium;Fair&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improvisation and Collaboration</title>
      <link>/improvisation-and-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/improvisation-and-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Way back in high school and college, I used to be a fairly avid jazz musician. I always loved the group aspect of Jazz - in a good group, there is this sense of support for each other&amp;rsquo;s creativity where everyone is backing each other up and giving each other musical space to express themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My background in improvisation has served me well, in that it has enabled a lot of my musical collaborations. My music is different in that I play improvisational cello, though on a very slow scale. But you can drop me into a lot of situations and I can come up with something that will work with someone else&amp;rsquo;s musical style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now realize that I use a lot of the rules of improvisation when I collaborate with others in Open Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Being respectful and listening.
1) Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes, and&amp;rdquo;. This is an old comedy improv rule. It means that you don&amp;rsquo;t shut other people&amp;rsquo;s performances down. You try to build on theirs and enhance it. I like to build on people&amp;rsquo;s ideas.
1) Being flexible. See previous two rules.
1) Don&amp;rsquo;t hog the spotlight.
1) Most things are a process and rely on previous experience. No one became an expert improviser overnight.
1) Trust the process when you can.
1) Help each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Introvert&#39;s Survival Guide to Conferences</title>
      <link>/2018/05/17/a-introvert-s-survival-guide-to-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/17/a-introvert-s-survival-guide-to-conferences/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In academia, it’s inevitable to have to travel and present at conferences and meetings. As an introvert, I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to compile a few tips that have helped me navigate large conferences so I don’t feel overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that though the academic community has many introverts, conference and meeting structure is heavily biased towards extroverts. (No offense to extroverts, but some of you can sometimes seem like blowhards to us introverts.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question for introverts is how to connect with people at meetings while being true to our nature. We value meaningful and deep connections rather than shallow ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set Yourself Up For Success. Be prepared.&lt;/strong&gt; If you can, try to connect with people or identify the people you want to meet before the conference even starts. Bring things that make you comfortable. A sweater, water, candy/energy bars. If there are sessions that look interesting, look at the author’s previous papers and think of questions beforehand. An introvert’s strength is that they are good at preparing for things. Use that preparation to your advantage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Curious, Not Scared.&lt;/strong&gt; You are a curious person. If you weren’t, you wouldn’t be in science. Use that curiosity to connect. Wonder about things. Think about where research could go.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be the Host, Not the Hosted&lt;/strong&gt;. According to Susan Cain, introverts do very well socially when they have a specific role. I like moderating sessions for this reason. I’m pretty good at being amiable and making other people comfortable in such situations. By being thoughtful and helping people with their problems, you can form connections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s Totally Ok to Take a Break&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s called self-care. Remember, introverts find social situations draining. Go outside for a few minutes, or find a corner that’s quiet and secluded, look at websites on your laptop. Just don’t withdraw. It’s a break, not a jailbreak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept That You’ll Miss Out. Emphasize quality over quantity.&lt;/strong&gt; As an introvert, I am constantly feeling guilty about not going to every session and meeting people. FOMO can drive me to the point of being overwhelmed. But the truth is, if I can meet two or three people that I can connect with and two or three talks I find inspiring, I consider that a good meeting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make Yourself Comfortable at Social Functions&lt;/strong&gt;.  Introverts can do very well socially when the situation is proscribed and the roles are clear, which is why I like poster sessions. There’s a limited set of questions you can ask and be asked. You can also do your homework by looking at the posters before you meet the person. Also: I hate asking public questions in meetings. (This again, is where extroverts can sometimes seem like blowhards to me. Bless their hearts.) I really prefer to go up to the speaker afterwards and try to have a meaningful conversation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember That Most People Are Equally Nervous. Be kind.&lt;/strong&gt; Be compassionate to yourself and to others. This will make you more relatable. When you focus on making others comfortable, you concentrate less on your own nervousness. Kindness goes a long way in these situations. Help someone out who’s struggling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask Questions and Listen&lt;/strong&gt;. Again, other people at conferences want to be heard and connect. You may run into raging egotists who don’t listen to you. It’s ok to politely disengage from the conversation. But there is something always interesting about everyone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gauge When You’re Exhausted&lt;/strong&gt;. As an introvert, being with people can be draining. At some point, enough is enough. Take the evening off, grab something to go, and watch tv or read a book in your hotel room alone. It’s ok, no one is keeping score of how many social events you are going to. Again, it’s ok to not go to the big reception (unless you’re giving a poster at that time, of course).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s OK, the Right People Will Like You&lt;/strong&gt;.  You will eventually find people you want to talk to. Nurture these relationships. If someone gives you their card, follow up on it. It’s a sign of wanting to make connections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t Expect The World of Each Social Interaction&lt;/strong&gt;. I think sometimes we idealize what our perfect interaction would be. We get disappointed when our interactions are less than that. Prepare to be pleasantly surprised, but don’t get bored and wander off. Respect goes a long way, and also serendipity is good. Try to learn more outside your field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s Totally Okay to be Awkward&lt;/strong&gt;. Just own it. Most scientists are awkward in some way.  (I know that I am, stop denying it people.) Being awkward is a way of being vulnerable - and being vulnerable is a way of connecting. I sometimes consider wearing an “I’m an introvert” button at conferences. At least it would be a good conversation starter. So go ahead, wear something quirky that you like. It can serve as a signal to find like minded people. Remember, own your awkwardness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breathe&lt;/strong&gt;.  Conferences can feel like scary and unsafe situations to introverts. If you feel agitated, don’t force it. Take a moment and breathe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of conferences doesn’t really value introverts, but it needs us (at least there are some people thinking about &lt;a href=&#34;https://scientistseessquirrel.wordpress.com/2018/03/15/making-a-conference-introvert-friendly/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;making conferences more introvert friendly&lt;/a&gt;). We’re thoughtful, slow to react, but we can synthesize and bring deeper understanding. Give us space to think and be ourselves, and we will contribute and add diversity to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-more-information&#34;&gt;For more information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of blogs written about this. Here are some of my favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theconfusedmillennial.com/conference-introvert/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How to Make the Most of a Conference as an Introvert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lifehack.org/articles/communication/how-to-survive-big-conferences-as-an-introvert.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How to Survive Big Conferences As an Introvert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2015/10/how-introverts-can-make-the-most-of-conferences&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How Introverts can Make the Most of Conferences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Informatics Course Materials</title>
      <link>/2018/04/25/health-informatics-course-materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/25/health-informatics-course-materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the lack of posts. I have been busy with co-teaching our Health Informatics course (HSMP410) for the OHSU/PSU School of Public Health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make most of my lectures activity-driven for my students, who are Community Health Education and Nursing majors. I believe that you can teach mathematical concepts visually, so I am experimenting with using &lt;code&gt;LearnR&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;Shiny&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://tladeras.shinyapps.io/dataLiteracy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;teach the basics of data literacy&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m also using &lt;code&gt;datacamp-light&lt;/code&gt; to show my students &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/HSMP410/week4.2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a simple intro to data science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/HSMP410/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HMSP410 Health Informatics&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/HSMP410/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HMSP410 repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Intro to Genome Wide Association</title>
      <link>/2018/04/04/a-simple-intro-to-genome-wide-association/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/04/a-simple-intro-to-genome-wide-association/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This term, I&amp;rsquo;m co-teaching an undergraduate course for the PSU/OHSU School of Public Health called &lt;a href=&#34;https://ohsu-psu-sph.org/highlighted-sph-courses/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Health Informatics&lt;/a&gt; with a number of my collegues in my department, including Bill Hersh, Eilis Boudreau, Karen Eden, and Virginia Lankes. We&amp;rsquo;re trying to give students a feel for what informatics is about in an accessible way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make the lectures as understandable as I can. This week we tackled Genome Wide Association Studies and discussed the strength of evidence behind SNP variants associated with phenotypes. We ended with an activity where they queried the GWAS catalog for information on particular SNP variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repo for my lectures is here and will be updated as the course goes along: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/HSMP410&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/laderast/HSMP410&lt;/a&gt; The lecture is here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/HSMP410/week1.2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Bioinformatics: Genome Wide Association&lt;/a&gt; and the activity is here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/hsmp410snp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SNP In class assignment&lt;/a&gt;. All my material is free to use and released under Apache 2.0, so if this is interesting to you, please feel free to fork it and remix it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Notes from the Evidence to Scholarship Conference</title>
      <link>/2018/03/19/some-notes-from-the-evidence-to-scholarship-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/19/some-notes-from-the-evidence-to-scholarship-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the good fortune to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reed.edu/e2s/conference/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;From Evidence to Scholarship Conference&lt;/a&gt; at my alma mater, Reed College. The focus of the conference was improving the research process for undergraduates using digital scholarship. I came away from it excited about the work other people are doing in this realm and thinking about ways we could adapt these approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicole Vasilevsky and I (both former Reedies) each gave talks, about our &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/data-sci-resources/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;experience developing materials for Data Science&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/NicoleVasilevsky/teaching-data-science-to-undergraduate-students&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;giving data science workshops to undergraduates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the conference to be very exciting and friendly overall. Laurie Allen kicked off the conference with a plenary session talking about the role digital scholarship librarians can have in the community surrounding them, talking about her work with &lt;a href=&#34;http://monumentlab.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Monument Lab&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datarefuge.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data Refuge&lt;/a&gt;. Key takeaway point: it&amp;rsquo;s ok to do something badly if it gets the conversation started with the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key takeaway points from the conference is the role that digital scholarship librarians have in revamping current curricula at the liberal arts colleges. They often do short-form training (in digital scholarship tools, such as webpage building and network analysis), which when integrated into a current course, can revitalize the course. &lt;a href=&#34;https://fromevidencetoscholarshipco2018.sched.com/event/DfDC/two-sessions-undergraduate-mvps-the-modernist-versions-project-digital-humanities-open-education-resources-connecting-text-and-data-a-collaborative-teaching-approach-to-a-literary-network-analysis-project-for-undergraduates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Laura O&amp;rsquo;Brien and Hélène Bilis&lt;/a&gt; talked about integrating digital scholarship tools into a french literature course, talking about modeling the social networks of characters and how they evolved over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An exciting talk was about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://iliads.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ILiADS&lt;/a&gt; program, which is a multi-disciplinary digital scholarship program. It&amp;rsquo;s run as a summer institute which starts as teams of students, faculty and staff. The projects are student driven and they try to incorporate both students with the technical skills and those who are non-technical. I really liked this idea of teaming up students from different fields and having faculty to advise them as needed. I&amp;rsquo;d like to try something similar at OHSU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaboration with allied departments led to enhanced interdisciplinary courses. Jon Caris&amp;rsquo; talk about his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.science.smith.edu/sal/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Spatial Analysis Lab&lt;/a&gt; at Smith College and the unexpected collaborations they had was a really great one, talking about using spatial analysis to analyze painting styles in the Painting III course, and using GIS to map out invasive species at a pond at Smith College for an intro Biology class. One of the best quotes from his talk was talking about emerging technology: &amp;ldquo;Emerging technology means that you&amp;rsquo;re in a perpetual state of incompetence. And that&amp;rsquo;s a fun place to be.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d be remiss if I didn&amp;rsquo;t mention Parveneh Abbaspour and Jeremy McWilliams&amp;rsquo; talk about &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcphysx.lclark.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LCPhysX&lt;/a&gt;, which is an online video archive showcasing student projects in the physics department. The videos are really great, especially the one about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcphysx.lclark.edu/project/golf-robot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Golf Robot&lt;/a&gt;. The engagement of the students actually seems to have had an effect on admissions; a few of the new physics students actually noted that the LCPhysX site made them decide to go to Lewis and Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I really enjoyed Andrew Bray&amp;rsquo;s talk about his collaborative course, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ds-elections&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Case Studies in Data Science: Elections&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, where he solicited political scientists about important problems in voting for the students to tackle. By giving them some basic analyses in R, the students managed to complete a number of projects, including a package for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ds-elections/rcv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;visualizing ranked choice voting&lt;/a&gt;, which is actually being utilized for visualizing these results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I emerged from this conference excited about the passion that undergraduates have and excited about how digital scholarship librarians can change curricula for the better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science and Systems Science</title>
      <link>/2018/02/28/data-science-and-systems-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/28/data-science-and-systems-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a talk for the Portland State University Systems Science seminar called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/sysc_data_sci/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How are Data Science and Systems Science Connected?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. In this talk, I was highlighting current blind spots in Data Science that I think Systems Science approaches can address, especially that of interactions between features. I talked a little about my dissertation research (surrogate oncogenes), and the problem of &lt;em&gt;black-box interpretability&lt;/em&gt; of predictive models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in listening to the recording, the playback is available here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://us.bbcollab.com/recording/059acf5cfed64f9abbf7cf432fdfb566&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://us.bbcollab.com/recording/059acf5cfed64f9abbf7cf432fdfb566&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A gRadual Introduction to Shiny</title>
      <link>/2018/01/24/gradual-introduction-to-shiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/24/gradual-introduction-to-shiny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just gave a workshop teaching the basics of &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shiny&lt;/a&gt; (the interactive web visualization framework) for a group of PDX R users. We had 10 people attend, and most of the attendees managed to get through the material and had lots of good questions. I really enjoyed talking with everyone and I hope everyone learned something. We&amp;rsquo;re planning to give the workshop again to the larger PDX R user community, and some of the attendees last night have volunteered to be TAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop materials consist of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/gradual_shiny&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/gradual_shiny/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Markdown document&lt;/a&gt; that can be done either in person or independently. The materials are freely available under an Apache 2.0 License.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the workshop, we build a flexible &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt; (comma separated value) explorer that can load in &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt; data files with adaptive controls and tooltips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of packages, the workshop uses the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; (mostly &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;), and &lt;code&gt;plotly&lt;/code&gt; to show some basic programming patterns in &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connecting controls to &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; aesthetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filtering data using &lt;code&gt;reactive&lt;/code&gt;s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;observe&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;update_&lt;/code&gt; pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tooltips (the hard way/the plotly way)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The final product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d love for more people to take a look at the workshop and would &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/gradual_shiny/issues/2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;love any suggestions&lt;/a&gt; for making it better!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What We learned teaching Python to Neuroscience Students</title>
      <link>/2018/01/17/what-we-learned-teaching-python-to-neuroscience-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/17/what-we-learned-teaching-python-to-neuroscience-students/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Well, the week of teaching our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dasaderi/python_neurobootcamp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Python Bootcamp for Neuroscientists&lt;/a&gt; is over. I had the pleasure of working with a great group of students, professors and instructors in developing the material, and had a great time teaching complete beginners to programming and Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had the overall goal of introducting 21 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohsu.edu/xd/education/schools/school-of-medicine/academic-programs/neuroscience-graduate-program/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Neuroscience Graduate Program&lt;/a&gt; students at OHSU to the basics of programming in Python using data that they were interested in: electrophysiology data, and confocal microscopy data. The course was designed to be a 1 credit course to encourage students to persist and finish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of the class was spread over 5 days (2.5 hours a day) and had the following schedule:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction to basic data types in Python&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction to for loops and Pandas DataFrames&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using Pandas to analyse electrophysiology data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using NumPy to analyse confocal microscopy data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evaluation of students; installing Python/Juypter; wrap-up with questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll just write up some random thoughts about our experiences about the course. We are definitely planning to give the course again next year, given the enthusiastic reception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;things-that-really-worked-well&#34;&gt;Things that really worked well&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid the first day blues of installing Python by using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jupyterhub/jupyterhub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JupyterHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I think one of the major pain points for beginners is installing software before they can even learn. Instead of making them install Python the first day, we had them sign into an AWS server that had JuypterHub deployed. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jupyterhub/jupyterhub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JupyterHub is a multi-user server for Juypter Notebooks&lt;/a&gt; which had the right version of Python and our need the dependencies installed. So our students just needed a laptop and a web browser to access our lessons. We could update the notebooks by pulling changes from our course repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen David, my fellow instructor, figured a lot of the difficult deployment details out. He has put together some &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dasaderi/python_neurobootcamp/blob/master/server_setup/hubInstall.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;handy instructions about deploying JuypterHub to AWS&lt;/a&gt; and keeping the accounts updated via a GitHub repo in case other people are interested in using our bootcamp materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the atmosphere welcoming to beginners&lt;/strong&gt;. In order to do so, we used many great tips from Software/Data Carpentry: modeling resilience by using live coding (and making mistakes along the way), using post-it notes for students to signal when they need help or are finished, and having plenty of TAs per student (at least 4 students/TA or instructor). We tried to emphasize that learning programming is an ongoing process, and that even we still have to Google errors on Stack Overflow. Showing that you can make mistakes and still recover is a big part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan some early wins and make the exercises as interactive as possible.&lt;/strong&gt; For the most part, we tried to avoid lecturing too long and break up the session with interactive exercises. I also really don&amp;rsquo;t like workshops where the trainer/teacher moves on no matter whether people understand the material or not. By using the post-its to signal when they were done, we were able to more appropriately pace the workshop. We also planned on stopping points if we couldn&amp;rsquo;t get through the day&amp;rsquo;s materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emphasize working together and building a community.&lt;/strong&gt; From the beginning, we emphasized that everyone needed to work together. I always emphasize the chain of help: 1) First your programming partner, 2) then the TA help. Discussing and working on issues together fosters a sense of community. I think there will be a group of students who will really want to learn more because of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting feedback along the way&lt;/strong&gt;. I still feel like being a teacher is about 75% preparation and 25% improvisation. You need to be flexible enough to come up with examples on the fly, and you need to evaluate whether students are getting the material along the way. The exercises we tried to sprinkle throughout the notebooks helped us understand where people were stumbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning follow-up sessions&lt;/strong&gt;. Through BioData Club, we&amp;rsquo;re planning some follow-up sessions. Through DataCamp in the Classroom, I also got our students premium access. We also pointed students out to &lt;a href=&#34;/python_resources/&#34;&gt;other Python-based courses at OHSU&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-things-we-could-improve-on&#34;&gt;Some things we could improve on&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that given our time frame, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t really have anticipated many of these issues. We did our best to deal with them in the moment, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Describing the difference between Jupyter Notebooks and Python&lt;/strong&gt;. At the beginning, we glossed over what a Jupyter Notebook was and really didn&amp;rsquo;t describe its relation to Python. I think next time we will open with describing the relationship between Jupyter and Python with a diagram, and revisit it on the last day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anticipate the JupyterHub server requirements better&lt;/strong&gt;. On Day 3, we had a large dataset that basically hosed the server because 21 students were trying to open it up at once. We managed to recover by getting another AWS server and dividing the students among the two, but we could have stress tested that day a little more. Lesson learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going slowly enough&lt;/strong&gt;. I am a very excitable teacher, to the point of which sometimes I go a little too fast. I have to confess that I may have sped through some of the material a little too fast. As a result, some of the students didn&amp;rsquo;t quite get what functions like &lt;code&gt;enumerate()&lt;/code&gt; were for and the concept of &lt;em&gt;unpacking&lt;/em&gt; a list. Luckily, Brad Buran covered these on Day 4 and the students felt comfortable enough to finish the programming test on the final day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting student expectations&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s vital to show the students that they can learn programming, but also what&amp;rsquo;s possible if they do. One of the days was a big leap from the previous day, but we did mention that it&amp;rsquo;s really to show them what&amp;rsquo;s possible if they continued to learn about programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;would-we-do-it-again&#34;&gt;Would we do it again?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would definitely say yes! We had to waitlist some students who really wanted to take it, and our overall feedback about the course was really positive. I hope that we can have more TAs, and have the future data workshops be more student driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowlegements&#34;&gt;Acknowlegements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a collaboration between the Neuroscience Graduate Program (NGP) and the Department of Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology (DMICE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NGP students involved in designing and testing the material were&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniela Saderi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lucille Moore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charles Heller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zack Schwartz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faculty/Instructors involved were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brad Buran  (Research Instructor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stephen David (NGP Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lisa Karstens (DMICE Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Mooney (DMICE Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ted Laderas (DMICE Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks very much to Gary Westbrook (Director of the NGP program), Shannon McWeeney (Head of the Division of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology within DMICE), and Bill Hersh (Head of DMICE).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you want to talk with me for an informational interview</title>
      <link>/2018/01/15/if-you-want-to-talk-with-me-for-an-informational-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/15/if-you-want-to-talk-with-me-for-an-informational-interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: I have come to believe that this post is way too harsh and unwelcoming to
people interested in data science. I will post an update to this, and a FAQ
for those who want informational interviews. But in the spirit of showing my
mistakes, I&amp;rsquo;ll leave this up here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had many people who have asked me for informational interviews. They tell me that they are interested in Data Science and want to hear about what I do on a day to day basis. To be honest, I&amp;rsquo;ve begun to dread these kinds of interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, I spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of energy explaining what I do to someone who rarely follows up. Consequently, I don&amp;rsquo;t find these interviews rewarding at all. So I&amp;rsquo;ve written this post so that I have a better time doing these kinds of interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reserve the right to refuse interviews from people who do not read this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) &lt;em&gt;Do your homework&lt;/em&gt;. Please don&amp;rsquo;t expect me to give the five minute spiel about my research, hoping to look for an &amp;ldquo;in&amp;rdquo;. Please do some research and try to ask &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; questions about my work. I&amp;rsquo;ve given you plenty of resources on this website to know more about me. Ask me about my software, ask me about teaching, ask me carefully thought questions about my research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t offer to buy me coffee&lt;/em&gt;. If I talk with you for 30 minutes, know that my time is worth far more than a cup of coffee. Instead, offer to pay it forwards. Volunteer with a group that does scientific communication or education; I don&amp;rsquo;t work with people who aren&amp;rsquo;t willing to teach others. I don&amp;rsquo;t work or talk with selfish people, having been burned many times by such people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) &lt;em&gt;Be specific in your ask&lt;/em&gt;. Asking about what next steps to take in learning data science and where to get a job is not specific enough. Again, do your research. What kinds of Data Science are you interested in? Are you interested in predictive analytics in healthcare? Or are you interested in systems modeling of disease? Be specific, and if you ask for something, make sure I can &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samuelthomasdavies.com/the-five-minute-favour/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;achieve it in five minutes or less&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t ask for a job, ask for connections&lt;/em&gt;. I know a decent number of people around Oregon and OHSU, so if you want me to introduce you to one of my connections, I&amp;rsquo;m happy to. If I know someone, I&amp;rsquo;m happy to do this, since it&amp;rsquo;s usually a five-minute ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) &lt;em&gt;Follow up, and be willing to return the favor&lt;/em&gt;. Even a nice thank-you email is good. I&amp;rsquo;m happy to make you a Linkedin connection, if it means I can help someone else further down the line. If I expend energy on you, I&amp;rsquo;d like to see my impact. If my efforts meant that you managed to find a job, please let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) &lt;em&gt;Read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adamgrant.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Give and Take&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. This book by Adam Grant really struck me as the way to actually network. In short, I learned that if I want a return on my energy expenditure, I have to spend my energy on Givers, or people who help others. I am a Giver, but I now tend only to give informational interviewers to other Givers. The rest are too draining for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have given so many of these interviews and have gotten nothing from them. Not even a follow-up, which really is bad practice. So, if I&amp;rsquo;m considered difficult to approach about these, know it is because your previous askers have really been an energy drain and have been inconsiderate Takers. Make it interesting for me and be considerate. I&amp;rsquo;m much more likely to help you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python_resources</title>
      <link>/python_resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 13:55:55 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/python_resources/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A list of python resources at OHSU and beyond for the neuroscience students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-neuroscience&#34;&gt;In Neuroscience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;python-bootcamp-for-neuroscientists-neus640&#34;&gt;Python Bootcamp for Neuroscientists (NEUS640)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dasaderi/python_neurobootcamp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Course Material&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is a gentle introduction to the Python
programming language using data types familiar to Neuroscience students, including behavioral, electrophysiology, and imaging data. Emphasis will be put on introducing students to concepts of visualization, data manipulation, and analysis using available Python packages (NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-medical-informatics-and-clinical-epidemiology-dmice&#34;&gt;In Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology (DMICE)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-to-programming-no-course-number&#34;&gt;Introduction to Programming (no course number)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructor: Lisa Karstens, Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 credits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohsu.edu/xd/education/schools/school-of-medicine/departments/clinical-departments/dmice/current-students/student-resources/upload/IntroductionToProgramming-Syllabus-WI18.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Course Syllabus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offered: Winter and Summer Quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This non-credit, online course will introduce the beginning programmer to programming structure and design, creating a solid foundation for all types of programming. The emphasis will be on procedural programming and control structures, although exercises will be in Python. The course fulfills the prerequisite for BMI 540 and BMI 565. Tuition fee is $500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students may register during the regular winter and summer term registration periods. Contact Diane Doctor for details at doctord@ohsu.edu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bioinformatics-programming-and-scripting-bmi-565-656&#34;&gt;Bioinformatics Programming and Scripting - BMI 565 / 656&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructor: Michael Mooney, Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credits: 3.0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohsu.edu/xd/education/schools/school-of-medicine/departments/clinical-departments/dmice/current-students/student-resources/upload/BMI-565-Syllabus-FA17.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offered: Fall Quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this course is to equip research scientists with computational skills necessary to create and automate tools to analyze biological data.  The course is divided into four sub-topics: python programming, scripting in unix, biopython library, bioinformatics workflows.  Python will be used used to solve simple to sophisticated programming problems and to review general computational language paradigms such as problem abstraction, data types, file I/O, iteration, functions, and objects.  There will also be an emphasis on writing unix operating system shell scripts to automate repetitive tasks and connect disparate bioinformatics tools using files and pipes.  In addition, students will learn to access public repositories to perform basic bioinformatics tasks such as annotating gene products, sequence searching, and functional queries. This course is designed to be a first year requirement for students in the Bioinformatics and Computational Biology graduate program in Biomedical Informatics. Open to other students with consent of instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/strong&gt;: Background must include an introductory programming class including concepts such as variables, loops, I/O, methods, and algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;computer-science-and-electrical-engineering-cs-ee-python-courses&#34;&gt;Computer Science and Electrical Engineering (CS/EE) Python Courses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-science-programming-cs-527-627&#34;&gt;Data Science Programming - CS 527 / 627&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cslu.ohsu.edu/~kain/CS627/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Course Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is designed to give you awareness and initial working knowledge of some of the most fundamental computational tools for performing a wide variety of academic research. As such, it will focus on providing breadth instead of depth, which means that for each concept we will talk about motivation, key concepts, and concrete usage scenarios, but without mathematical background or proofs, which can be acquired in more specialized classes. In this class we will: become familiar with the UNIX/LINUX environment, learn how to version control files with git, write programs inpython, perform numeric tasks using numpy and scipy, analyze data using pandas, apply machine learning algorithms using scikit-learn, visualize data using matplotlib and pyqtgraph, use QT/pyside to build graphical user interfaces, and finally we will address performance issues via compilation/profiling/parallelization tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-to-image-processing-ee-584-684&#34;&gt;Introduction to Image Processing EE 584 / 684&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course covers basic image processing principles and techniques with a brief introduction to machine vision. Specific topics include image transform methods, image filtering, image enhancement, image restoration, segmentation, image representation and feature extraction, image recognition and classification, and image compression. Application of these techniques is illustrated in numerous examples. Pre-requisite: probability and statistics or equivalent, calculus, linear algebra and proficiency in at least one high-level programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-visualization-cs-631&#34;&gt;Data Visualization CS 631&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course will give students a foundation in the principles of data visualization, particularly as applied to scientific and technical data, as well as provide students with hands-on experience using modern software tools for developing visualizations. Lecture topics will include an overview of visual perception, color theory and practice, different types of graphs and their purposes, visualizations for specialized forms of data including time-series and geospatial data sets, strategies for working with multidimensional data, etc. There will also be lecture content on ethical issues surrounding data visualization. Weekly lab sessions will introduce students to popular data visualization tools such as R&amp;rsquo;s ggplot and Shiny, Tableau, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;datacamp&#34;&gt;DataCamp&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NEUS640 Students will have access to DataCamp for the next 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So You&#39;ve Accidentally Checked in a Large File Into Git</title>
      <link>/2018/01/05/so-you-ve-accidentally-checked-in-a-large-file-into-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/05/so-you-ve-accidentally-checked-in-a-large-file-into-git/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: after posting this, I heard back from Roberto Tyley, the creator of the BFG. I&amp;rsquo;d like to note that the BFG actually does its job really well. I was mostly really frustrated about how Git/GitHub doesn&amp;rsquo;t prevent a user from doing something that&amp;rsquo;s hard to undo. So my frustration is really about that, not really about the BFG. This post has been edited to reflect that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greg Wilson first said it, but I&amp;rsquo;ve come to agree. Git is an aggressively antisocial piece of software. Git is a piece of software that can make developers with any amount of experience feel dumb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I accidentally checked a large file (greater than 100 Megs) into my local repo. When I tried to push to GitHub, of course, it refused it (I know about git large file storage, but I don&amp;rsquo;t have any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my local repo was screwed up. Of course, I did what seemed like the rational thing and deleted the file from my repo and recommitted. More than once. This is a mistake I&amp;rsquo;ve done more than once. So you need to scrub your git history with BFG so that GitHub will accept your lowly commits again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rtyley.github.io/bfg-repo-cleaner/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The BFG&lt;/a&gt; documentation specifies how to fix a &lt;em&gt;remote&lt;/em&gt; repo. I would say that this situation is much less common than the local situation. So I just decided to share how I got the BFG to work for the local repo situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually install the BFG through &lt;code&gt;homebrew&lt;/code&gt;, using &lt;code&gt;brew install bfg&lt;/code&gt;. When you install it this way, you can just run BFG with &lt;code&gt;bfg&lt;/code&gt;. You can download it from the website, but you&amp;rsquo;ll have to call &lt;code&gt;java -jar bfg[VERSION].jar&lt;/code&gt; to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you&amp;rsquo;ve accidently checked in a large file into your current repo. The first thing to do is to clone your local repo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone --mirror local_repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create another folder called &lt;code&gt;local_repo.git&lt;/code&gt; that you will do all the BFG magic on. This &lt;code&gt;local_rep.git&lt;/code&gt; is what is called a &lt;em&gt;bare&lt;/em&gt; repo. I want to remove any files larger than 100 Megs, so I do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bfg -b 100M local_repo.git
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this doesn&amp;rsquo;t return an error, you can move on. However, I got the dreaded error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Warning : no large blobs matching criteria found in packfiles - 
does the repo need to be packed?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Augh. Ok, some googling later I found that I needed to pack my orignal repo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd local_repo
git repack
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, we need to get rid of our cloned repo and redo the last few steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rm -rf local_repo.git
git clone --mirror local_repo
bfg -b 100M local_repo.git
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes some git commands that no one has bothered to explain to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git reflog expire --expire=now --all &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git gc --prune=now --aggressive
git push
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uh oh, I get a &lt;code&gt;remote: error: refusing to update checked out branch: refs/heads/master&lt;/code&gt; error! More ugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the trick. Since you cloned a &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; repo, you need to set the origin of your current repo (&lt;code&gt;local_repo.git&lt;/code&gt;) to the GitHub remote. First we remove the current &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt;, and then add back our remote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git remote rm origin
git remote add origin https://github.com/laderast/remote_repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after much gnashing of the teeth, we can&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git push
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to remove your now &lt;em&gt;dirty&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;local_repo&lt;/code&gt;, and the mirrored copy, and then pull a fresh copy down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##remove both original local repo and altered bare repo
rm -rf local_repo
rm -rf local_repo.git
##clone a fresh copy from GitHub
git clone https://github.com/laderast/remote_repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be obvious to the 10 people in the world who have read all of the git documentation, but I am not one of them. I&amp;rsquo;m stuck with git, unfortunately. I&amp;rsquo;m writing this post to remind me of what to do when I innocently do something like commit a large file to my repo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
