<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ted Laderas, PhD</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ted Laderas, PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Introvert&#39;s Survival Guide to Conferences</title>
      <link>/2018/05/17/a-introvert-s-survival-guide-to-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/17/a-introvert-s-survival-guide-to-conferences/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In academia, it’s inevitable to have to travel and present at conferences and meetings. As an introvert, I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to compile a few tips that have helped me navigate large conferences so I don’t feel overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that though the academic community has many introverts, conference and meeting structure is heavily biased towards extroverts. (No offense to extroverts, but some of you can sometimes seem like blowhards to us introverts.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question for introverts is how to connect with people at meetings while being true to our nature. We value meaningful and deep connections rather than shallow ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set Yourself Up For Success. Be prepared.&lt;/strong&gt; If you can, try to connect with people or identify the people you want to meet before the conference even starts. Bring things that make you comfortable. A sweater, water, candy/energy bars. If there are sessions that look interesting, look at the author’s previous papers and think of questions beforehand. An introvert’s strength is that they are good at preparing for things. Use that preparation to your advantage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Curious, Not Scared.&lt;/strong&gt; You are a curious person. If you weren’t, you wouldn’t be in science. Use that curiosity to connect. Wonder about things. Think about where research could go.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be the Host, Not the Hosted&lt;/strong&gt;. According to Susan Cain, introverts do very well socially when they have a specific role. I like moderating sessions for this reason. I’m pretty good at being amiable and making other people comfortable in such situations. By being thoughtful and helping people with their problems, you can form connections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s Totally Ok to Take a Break&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s called self-care. Remember, introverts find social situations draining. Go outside for a few minutes, or find a corner that’s quiet and secluded, look at websites on your laptop. Just don’t withdraw. It’s a break, not a jailbreak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept That You’ll Miss Out. Emphasize quality over quantity.&lt;/strong&gt; As an introvert, I am constantly feeling guilty about not going to every session and meeting people. FOMO can drive me to the point of being overwhelmed. But the truth is, if I can meet two or three people that I can connect with and two or three talks I find inspiring, I consider that a good meeting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make Yourself Comfortable at Social Functions&lt;/strong&gt;.  Introverts can do very well socially when the situation is proscribed and the roles are clear, which is why I like poster sessions. There’s a limited set of questions you can ask and be asked. You can also do your homework by looking at the posters before you meet the person. Also: I hate asking public questions in meetings. (This again, is where extroverts can sometimes seem like blowhards to me. Bless their hearts.) I really prefer to go up to the speaker afterwards and try to have a meaningful conversation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember That Most People Are Equally Nervous. Be kind.&lt;/strong&gt; Be compassionate of yourself and others. This will make you more relatable. When you focus on making others comfortable, you concentrate less on your own nervousness. Kindness goes a long way in these situations. Help someone out who’s struggling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask Questions and Listen&lt;/strong&gt;. Again, other people at conferences want to be heard and connect. You may run into raging egotists who don’t listen to you. It’s ok to politely disengage from the conversation. But there is something always interesting about everyone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gauge When You’re Exhausted&lt;/strong&gt;. As an introvert, being with people can be draining. At some point, enough is enough. Take the evening off, grab something to go, and watch tv or read a book in your hotel room alone. It’s ok, no one is keeping score of how many social events you are going to. Again, it’s ok to not go to the big reception (unless you’re giving a poster at that time, of course).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s OK, the Right People Will Like You&lt;/strong&gt;.  You will eventually find people you want to talk to. Nurture these relationships. If someone gives you their card, follow up on it. It’s a sign of wanting to make connections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t Expect The World of Each Social Interaction&lt;/strong&gt;. I think sometimes we idealize what our perfect interaction would be. We get disappointed when our interactions are less than that. Prepare to be pleasantly surprised, but don’t get bored and wander off. Respect goes a long way, and also serendipity is good. Try to learn more outside your field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s Totally Okay to be Awkward&lt;/strong&gt;. Just own it. Most scientists are awkward in some way.  (I know that I am, stop denying it people.) Being awkward is a way of being vulnerable - and being vulnerable is a way of connecting. I sometimes consider wearing an “I’m an introvert” button at conferences. At least it would be a good conversation starter. So go ahead, wear something quirky that you like. It can serve as a signal to find like minded people. Remember, own it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breathe&lt;/strong&gt;.  Conferences can feel like scary and unsafe situations to introverts. If you feel agitated, don’t force it. Take a moment and breathe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of conferences doesn’t really value introverts, but it needs us (at least there are some people thinking about &lt;a href=&#34;https://scientistseessquirrel.wordpress.com/2018/03/15/making-a-conference-introvert-friendly/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;making conferences more introvert friendly&lt;/a&gt;). We’re thoughtful, slow to react, but we can synthesize and bring deeper understanding. Give us space to think and be ourselves, and we will contribute and add diversity to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-more-information&#34;&gt;For more information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of blogs written about this. Here are some of my favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theconfusedmillennial.com/conference-introvert/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How to Make the Most of a Conference as an Introvert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lifehack.org/articles/communication/how-to-survive-big-conferences-as-an-introvert.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How to Survive Big Conferences As an Introvert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2015/10/how-introverts-can-make-the-most-of-conferences&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How Introverts can Make the Most of Conferences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Informatics Course Materials</title>
      <link>/2018/04/25/health-informatics-course-materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/25/health-informatics-course-materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the lack of posts. I have been busy with co-teaching our Health Informatics course (HSMP410) for the OHSU/PSU School of Public Health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make most of my lectures activity-driven for my students, who are Community Health Education and Nursing majors. I believe that you can teach mathematical concepts visually, so I am experimenting with using &lt;code&gt;LearnR&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;Shiny&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://tladeras.shinyapps.io/dataLiteracy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;teach the basics of data literacy&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m also using &lt;code&gt;datacamp-light&lt;/code&gt; to show my students &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/HSMP410/week4.2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a simple intro to data science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/HSMP410/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HMSP410 Health Informatics&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/HSMP410/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HMSP410 repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Intro to Genome Wide Association</title>
      <link>/2018/04/04/a-simple-intro-to-genome-wide-association/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/04/a-simple-intro-to-genome-wide-association/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This term, I&amp;rsquo;m co-teaching an undergraduate course for the PSU/OHSU School of Public Health called &lt;a href=&#34;https://ohsu-psu-sph.org/highlighted-sph-courses/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Health Informatics&lt;/a&gt; with a number of my collegues in my department, including Bill Hersh, Eilis Boudreau, Karen Eden, and Virginia Lankes. We&amp;rsquo;re trying to give students a feel for what informatics is about in an accessible way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make the lectures as understandable as I can. This week we tackled Genome Wide Association Studies and discussed the strength of evidence behind SNP variants associated with phenotypes. We ended with an activity where they queried the GWAS catalog for information on particular SNP variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repo for my lectures is here and will be updated as the course goes along: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/HSMP410&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/laderast/HSMP410&lt;/a&gt; The lecture is here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/HSMP410/week1.2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Bioinformatics: Genome Wide Association&lt;/a&gt; and the activity is here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/hsmp410snp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SNP In class assignment&lt;/a&gt;. All my material is free to use and released under Apache 2.0, so if this is interesting to you, please feel free to fork it and remix it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Notes from the Evidence to Scholarship Conference</title>
      <link>/2018/03/19/some-notes-from-the-evidence-to-scholarship-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/19/some-notes-from-the-evidence-to-scholarship-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the good fortune to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reed.edu/e2s/conference/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;From Evidence to Scholarship Conference&lt;/a&gt; at my alma mater, Reed College. The focus of the conference was improving the research process for undergraduates using digital scholarship. I came away from it excited about the work other people are doing in this realm and thinking about ways we could adapt these approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicole Vasilevsky and I (both former Reedies) each gave talks, about our &lt;a href=&#34;http://laderast.github.io/data-sci-resources/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;experience developing materials for Data Science&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/NicoleVasilevsky/teaching-data-science-to-undergraduate-students&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;giving data science workshops to undergraduates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the conference to be very exciting and friendly overall. Laurie Allen kicked off the conference with a plenary session talking about the role digital scholarship librarians can have in the community surrounding them, talking about her work with &lt;a href=&#34;http://monumentlab.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Monument Lab&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datarefuge.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data Refuge&lt;/a&gt;. Key takeaway point: it&amp;rsquo;s ok to do something badly if it gets the conversation started with the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key takeaway points from the conference is the role that digital scholarship librarians have in revamping current curricula at the liberal arts colleges. They often do short-form training (in digital scholarship tools, such as webpage building and network analysis), which when integrated into a current course, can revitalize the course. &lt;a href=&#34;https://fromevidencetoscholarshipco2018.sched.com/event/DfDC/two-sessions-undergraduate-mvps-the-modernist-versions-project-digital-humanities-open-education-resources-connecting-text-and-data-a-collaborative-teaching-approach-to-a-literary-network-analysis-project-for-undergraduates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Laura O&amp;rsquo;Brien and Hélène Bilis&lt;/a&gt; talked about integrating digital scholarship tools into a french literature course, talking about modeling the social networks of characters and how they evolved over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An exciting talk was about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://iliads.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ILiADS&lt;/a&gt; program, which is a multi-disciplinary digital scholarship program. It&amp;rsquo;s run as a summer institute which starts as teams of students, faculty and staff. The projects are student driven and they try to incorporate both students with the technical skills and those who are non-technical. I really liked this idea of teaming up students from different fields and having faculty to advise them as needed. I&amp;rsquo;d like to try something similar at OHSU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaboration with allied departments led to enhanced interdisciplinary courses. Jon Caris&amp;rsquo; talk about his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.science.smith.edu/sal/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Spatial Analysis Lab&lt;/a&gt; at Smith College and the unexpected collaborations they had was a really great one, talking about using spatial analysis to analyze painting styles in the Painting III course, and using GIS to map out invasive species at a pond at Smith College for an intro Biology class. One of the best quotes from his talk was talking about emerging technology: &amp;ldquo;Emerging technology means that you&amp;rsquo;re in a perpetual state of incompetence. And that&amp;rsquo;s a fun place to be.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d be remiss if I didn&amp;rsquo;t mention Parveneh Abbaspour and Jeremy McWilliams&amp;rsquo; talk about &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcphysx.lclark.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LCPhysX&lt;/a&gt;, which is an online video archive showcasing student projects in the physics department. The videos are really great, especially the one about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcphysx.lclark.edu/project/golf-robot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Golf Robot&lt;/a&gt;. The engagement of the students actually seems to have had an effect on admissions; a few of the new physics students actually noted that the LCPhysX site made them decide to go to Lewis and Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I really enjoyed Andrew Bray&amp;rsquo;s talk about his collaborative course, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ds-elections&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Case Studies in Data Science: Elections&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, where he solicited political scientists about important problems in voting for the students to tackle. By giving them some basic analyses in R, the students managed to complete a number of projects, including a package for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ds-elections/rcv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;visualizing ranked choice voting&lt;/a&gt;, which is actually being utilized for visualizing these results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I emerged from this conference excited about the passion that undergraduates have and excited about how digital scholarship librarians can change curricula for the better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science and Systems Science</title>
      <link>/2018/02/28/data-science-and-systems-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/28/data-science-and-systems-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a talk for the Portland State University Systems Science seminar called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/sysc_data_sci/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How are Data Science and Systems Science Connected?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. In this talk, I was highlighting current blind spots in Data Science that I think Systems Science approaches can address, especially that of interactions between features. I talked a little about my dissertation research (surrogate oncogenes), and the problem of &lt;em&gt;black-box interpretability&lt;/em&gt; of predictive models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in listening to the recording, the playback is available here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://us.bbcollab.com/recording/059acf5cfed64f9abbf7cf432fdfb566&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://us.bbcollab.com/recording/059acf5cfed64f9abbf7cf432fdfb566&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A gRadual Introduction to Shiny</title>
      <link>/2018/01/24/gradual-introduction-to-shiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/24/gradual-introduction-to-shiny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just gave a workshop teaching the basics of &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shiny&lt;/a&gt; (the interactive web visualization framework) for a group of PDX R users. We had 10 people attend, and most of the attendees managed to get through the material and had lots of good questions. I really enjoyed talking with everyone and I hope everyone learned something. We&amp;rsquo;re planning to give the workshop again to the larger PDX R user community, and some of the attendees last night have volunteered to be TAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop materials consist of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/gradual_shiny&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://laderast.github.io/gradual_shiny/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Markdown document&lt;/a&gt; that can be done either in person or independently. The materials are freely available under an Apache 2.0 License.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the workshop, we build a flexible &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt; (comma separated value) explorer that can load in &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt; data files with adaptive controls and tooltips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of packages, the workshop uses the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; (mostly &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;), and &lt;code&gt;plotly&lt;/code&gt; to show some basic programming patterns in &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connecting controls to &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; aesthetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filtering data using &lt;code&gt;reactive&lt;/code&gt;s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;observe&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;update_&lt;/code&gt; pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tooltips (the hard way/the plotly way)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The final product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d love for more people to take a look at the workshop and would &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/gradual_shiny/issues/2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;love any suggestions&lt;/a&gt; for making it better!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What We learned teaching Python to Neuroscience Students</title>
      <link>/2018/01/17/what-we-learned-teaching-python-to-neuroscience-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/17/what-we-learned-teaching-python-to-neuroscience-students/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Well, the week of teaching our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dasaderi/python_neurobootcamp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Python Bootcamp for Neuroscientists&lt;/a&gt; is over. I had the pleasure of working with a great group of students, professors and instructors in developing the material, and had a great time teaching complete beginners to programming and Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had the overall goal of introducting 21 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohsu.edu/xd/education/schools/school-of-medicine/academic-programs/neuroscience-graduate-program/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Neuroscience Graduate Program&lt;/a&gt; students at OHSU to the basics of programming in Python using data that they were interested in: electrophysiology data, and confocal microscopy data. The course was designed to be a 1 credit course to encourage students to persist and finish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of the class was spread over 5 days (2.5 hours a day) and had the following schedule:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction to basic data types in Python&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction to for loops and Pandas DataFrames&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using Pandas to analyse electrophysiology data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using NumPy to analyse confocal microscopy data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evaluation of students; installing Python/Juypter; wrap-up with questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll just write up some random thoughts about our experiences about the course. We are definitely planning to give the course again next year, given the enthusiastic reception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;things-that-really-worked-well&#34;&gt;Things that really worked well&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid the first day blues of installing Python by using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jupyterhub/jupyterhub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JupyterHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I think one of the major pain points for beginners is installing software before they can even learn. Instead of making them install Python the first day, we had them sign into an AWS server that had JuypterHub deployed. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jupyterhub/jupyterhub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JupyterHub is a multi-user server for Juypter Notebooks&lt;/a&gt; which had the right version of Python and our need the dependencies installed. So our students just needed a laptop and a web browser to access our lessons. We could update the notebooks by pulling changes from our course repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen David, my fellow instructor, figured a lot of the difficult deployment details out. He has put together some &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dasaderi/python_neurobootcamp/blob/master/server_setup/hubInstall.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;handy instructions about deploying JuypterHub to AWS&lt;/a&gt; and keeping the accounts updated via a GitHub repo in case other people are interested in using our bootcamp materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the atmosphere welcoming to beginners&lt;/strong&gt;. In order to do so, we used many great tips from Software/Data Carpentry: modeling resilience by using live coding (and making mistakes along the way), using post-it notes for students to signal when they need help or are finished, and having plenty of TAs per student (at least 4 students/TA or instructor). We tried to emphasize that learning programming is an ongoing process, and that even we still have to Google errors on Stack Overflow. Showing that you can make mistakes and still recover is a big part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan some early wins and make the exercises as interactive as possible.&lt;/strong&gt; For the most part, we tried to avoid lecturing too long and break up the session with interactive exercises. I also really don&amp;rsquo;t like workshops where the trainer/teacher moves on no matter whether people understand the material or not. By using the post-its to signal when they were done, we were able to more appropriately pace the workshop. We also planned on stopping points if we couldn&amp;rsquo;t get through the day&amp;rsquo;s materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emphasize working together and building a community.&lt;/strong&gt; From the beginning, we emphasized that everyone needed to work together. I always emphasize the chain of help: 1) First your programming partner, 2) then the TA help. Discussing and working on issues together fosters a sense of community. I think there will be a group of students who will really want to learn more because of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting feedback along the way&lt;/strong&gt;. I still feel like being a teacher is about 75% preparation and 25% improvisation. You need to be flexible enough to come up with examples on the fly, and you need to evaluate whether students are getting the material along the way. The exercises we tried to sprinkle throughout the notebooks helped us understand where people were stumbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning follow-up sessions&lt;/strong&gt;. Through BioData Club, we&amp;rsquo;re planning some follow-up sessions. Through DataCamp in the Classroom, I also got our students premium access. We also pointed students out to &lt;a href=&#34;/python_resources/&#34;&gt;other Python-based courses at OHSU&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-things-we-could-improve-on&#34;&gt;Some things we could improve on&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that given our time frame, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t really have anticipated many of these issues. We did our best to deal with them in the moment, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Describing the difference between Jupyter Notebooks and Python&lt;/strong&gt;. At the beginning, we glossed over what a Jupyter Notebook was and really didn&amp;rsquo;t describe its relation to Python. I think next time we will open with describing the relationship between Jupyter and Python with a diagram, and revisit it on the last day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anticipate the JupyterHub server requirements better&lt;/strong&gt;. On Day 3, we had a large dataset that basically hosed the server because 21 students were trying to open it up at once. We managed to recover by getting another AWS server and dividing the students among the two, but we could have stress tested that day a little more. Lesson learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going slowly enough&lt;/strong&gt;. I am a very excitable teacher, to the point of which sometimes I go a little too fast. I have to confess that I may have sped through some of the material a little too fast. As a result, some of the students didn&amp;rsquo;t quite get what functions like &lt;code&gt;enumerate()&lt;/code&gt; were for and the concept of &lt;em&gt;unpacking&lt;/em&gt; a list. Luckily, Brad Buran covered these on Day 4 and the students felt comfortable enough to finish the programming test on the final day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting student expectations&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s vital to show the students that they can learn programming, but also what&amp;rsquo;s possible if they do. One of the days was a big leap from the previous day, but we did mention that it&amp;rsquo;s really to show them what&amp;rsquo;s possible if they continued to learn about programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;would-we-do-it-again&#34;&gt;Would we do it again?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would definitely say yes! We had to waitlist some students who really wanted to take it, and our overall feedback about the course was really positive. I hope that we can have more TAs, and have the future data workshops be more student driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowlegements&#34;&gt;Acknowlegements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a collaboration between the Neuroscience Graduate Program (NGP) and the Department of Medical Informatics and Clinical Epidemiology (DMICE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NGP students involved in designing and testing the material were&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniela Saderi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lucille Moore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charles Heller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zack Schwartz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faculty/Instructors involved were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brad Buran  (Research Instructor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stephen David (NGP Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lisa Karstens (DMICE Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Mooney (DMICE Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ted Laderas (DMICE Assistant Professor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks very much to Gary Westbrook (Director of the NGP program), Shannon McWeeney (Head of the Division of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology within DMICE), and Bill Hersh (Head of DMICE).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you want to talk with me for an informational interview</title>
      <link>/2018/01/15/if-you-want-to-talk-with-me-for-an-informational-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/15/if-you-want-to-talk-with-me-for-an-informational-interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: I have come to believe that this post is way too harsh and unwelcoming to
people interested in data science. I will post an update to this, and a FAQ
for those who want informational interviews. But in the spirit of showing my
mistakes, I&amp;rsquo;ll leave this up here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had many people who have asked me for informational interviews. They tell me that they are interested in Data Science and want to hear about what I do on a day to day basis. To be honest, I&amp;rsquo;ve begun to dread these kinds of interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, I spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of energy explaining what I do to someone who rarely follows up. Consequently, I don&amp;rsquo;t find these interviews rewarding at all. So I&amp;rsquo;ve written this post so that I have a better time doing these kinds of interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reserve the right to refuse interviews from people who do not read this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) &lt;em&gt;Do your homework&lt;/em&gt;. Please don&amp;rsquo;t expect me to give the five minute spiel about my research, hoping to look for an &amp;ldquo;in&amp;rdquo;. Please do some research and try to ask &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; questions about my work. I&amp;rsquo;ve given you plenty of resources on this website to know more about me. Ask me about my software, ask me about teaching, ask me carefully thought questions about my research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t offer to buy me coffee&lt;/em&gt;. If I talk with you for 30 minutes, know that my time is worth far more than a cup of coffee. Instead, offer to pay it forwards. Volunteer with a group that does scientific communication or education; I don&amp;rsquo;t work with people who aren&amp;rsquo;t willing to teach others. I don&amp;rsquo;t work or talk with selfish people, having been burned many times by such people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) &lt;em&gt;Be specific in your ask&lt;/em&gt;. Asking about what next steps to take in learning data science and where to get a job is not specific enough. Again, do your research. What kinds of Data Science are you interested in? Are you interested in predictive analytics in healthcare? Or are you interested in systems modeling of disease? Be specific, and if you ask for something, make sure I can &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samuelthomasdavies.com/the-five-minute-favour/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;achieve it in five minutes or less&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t ask for a job, ask for connections&lt;/em&gt;. I know a decent number of people around Oregon and OHSU, so if you want me to introduce you to one of my connections, I&amp;rsquo;m happy to. If I know someone, I&amp;rsquo;m happy to do this, since it&amp;rsquo;s usually a five-minute ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) &lt;em&gt;Follow up, and be willing to return the favor&lt;/em&gt;. Even a nice thank-you email is good. I&amp;rsquo;m happy to make you a Linkedin connection, if it means I can help someone else further down the line. If I expend energy on you, I&amp;rsquo;d like to see my impact. If my efforts meant that you managed to find a job, please let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) &lt;em&gt;Read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adamgrant.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Give and Take&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. This book by Adam Grant really struck me as the way to actually network. In short, I learned that if I want a return on my energy expenditure, I have to spend my energy on Givers, or people who help others. I am a Giver, but I now tend only to give informational interviewers to other Givers. The rest are too draining for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have given so many of these interviews and have gotten nothing from them. Not even a follow-up, which really is bad practice. So, if I&amp;rsquo;m considered difficult to approach about these, know it is because your previous askers have really been an energy drain and have been inconsiderate Takers. Make it interesting for me and be considerate. I&amp;rsquo;m much more likely to help you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So You&#39;ve Accidentally Checked in a Large File Into Git</title>
      <link>/2018/01/05/so-you-ve-accidentally-checked-in-a-large-file-into-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/05/so-you-ve-accidentally-checked-in-a-large-file-into-git/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: after posting this, I heard back from Roberto Tyley, the creator of the BFG. I&amp;rsquo;d like to note that the BFG actually does its job really well. I was mostly really frustrated about how Git/GitHub doesn&amp;rsquo;t prevent a user from doing something that&amp;rsquo;s hard to undo. So my frustration is really about that, not really about the BFG. This post has been edited to reflect that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greg Wilson first said it, but I&amp;rsquo;ve come to agree. Git is an aggressively antisocial piece of software. Git is a piece of software that can make developers with any amount of experience feel dumb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I accidentally checked a large file (greater than 100 Megs) into my local repo. When I tried to push to GitHub, of course, it refused it (I know about git large file storage, but I don&amp;rsquo;t have any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my local repo was screwed up. Of course, I did what seemed like the rational thing and deleted the file from my repo and recommitted. More than once. This is a mistake I&amp;rsquo;ve done more than once. So you need to scrub your git history with BFG so that GitHub will accept your lowly commits again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rtyley.github.io/bfg-repo-cleaner/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The BFG&lt;/a&gt; documentation specifies how to fix a &lt;em&gt;remote&lt;/em&gt; repo. I would say that this situation is much less common than the local situation. So I just decided to share how I got the BFG to work for the local repo situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually install the BFG through &lt;code&gt;homebrew&lt;/code&gt;, using &lt;code&gt;brew install bfg&lt;/code&gt;. When you install it this way, you can just run BFG with &lt;code&gt;bfg&lt;/code&gt;. You can download it from the website, but you&amp;rsquo;ll have to call &lt;code&gt;java -jar bfg[VERSION].jar&lt;/code&gt; to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you&amp;rsquo;ve accidently checked in a large file into your current repo. The first thing to do is to clone your local repo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone --mirror local_repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create another folder called &lt;code&gt;local_repo.git&lt;/code&gt; that you will do all the BFG magic on. This &lt;code&gt;local_rep.git&lt;/code&gt; is what is called a &lt;em&gt;bare&lt;/em&gt; repo. I want to remove any files larger than 100 Megs, so I do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bfg -b 100M local_repo.git
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this doesn&amp;rsquo;t return an error, you can move on. However, I got the dreaded error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Warning : no large blobs matching criteria found in packfiles - 
does the repo need to be packed?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Augh. Ok, some googling later I found that I needed to pack my orignal repo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd local_repo
git repack
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, we need to get rid of our cloned repo and redo the last few steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rm -rf local_repo.git
git clone --mirror local_repo
bfg -b 100M local_repo.git
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes some git commands that no one has bothered to explain to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git reflog expire --expire=now --all &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git gc --prune=now --aggressive
git push
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uh oh, I get a &lt;code&gt;remote: error: refusing to update checked out branch: refs/heads/master&lt;/code&gt; error! More ugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the trick. Since you cloned a &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; repo, you need to set the origin of your current repo (&lt;code&gt;local_repo.git&lt;/code&gt;) to the GitHub remote. First we remove the current &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt;, and then add back our remote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git remote rm origin
git remote add origin https://github.com/laderast/remote_repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after much gnashing of the teeth, we can&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git push
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to remove your now &lt;em&gt;dirty&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;local_repo&lt;/code&gt;, and the mirrored copy, and then pull a fresh copy down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##remove both original local repo and altered bare repo
rm -rf local_repo
rm -rf local_repo.git
##clone a fresh copy from GitHub
git clone https://github.com/laderast/remote_repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be obvious to the 10 people in the world who have read all of the git documentation, but I am not one of them. I&amp;rsquo;m stuck with git, unfortunately. I&amp;rsquo;m writing this post to remind me of what to do when I innocently do something like commit a large file to my repo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Tidy Evaluation in R</title>
      <link>/2017/12/19/understanding-tidyeval/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/19/understanding-tidyeval/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had something that no matter how many times someone explained it, you really had no idea what it was for? For me, that was Non Standard Evaluation (NSE) in R, and its newer cousin Tidy Evaluation, or &lt;code&gt;tidyeval&lt;/code&gt;. I had a real learning block about it. I really wanted to understand it, but for some reason I just really wasn’t getting the general concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is evaluation, really? For the longest time, I was extremely confused about it. When you provide an expression to R such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(rlang)
this_variable &amp;lt;- 2
this_variable * 6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 12&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You notice that there is an output to &lt;code&gt;this_variable * 6&lt;/code&gt;, which is &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt;. Evaluation is really about looking up variable names in an environment and then acting on the results. What is going on here is that R looks for an object that is named &lt;code&gt;this_variable&lt;/code&gt; in our global environment, and then returns the value, &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;, which it then &lt;em&gt;substitutes&lt;/em&gt; in the expression. So our original expression:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;this_variable * 6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 12&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becomes this expression:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;2 * 6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 12&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which R knows how to calculate, the output of which is &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt;. But sometimes you want to pass an expression or a variable, as is, without evaluating it first. The best case for this is to passing a variable into a function. We can do this by wrapping them up in &lt;code&gt;quosures&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;enquosures&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;quosure&lt;/code&gt; and an &lt;code&gt;enquosure&lt;/code&gt; can be thought of as envelopes around an object. They obscure certain properties of the object until they can be delivered into a function. The envelopes basically are a way to sneak variables and expressions into a function’s environment. When the envelope is in the function, we can open it up and evaluate what’s in the envelope. The trick to NSE and tidyeval is that we can control when the function &lt;em&gt;evaluates&lt;/em&gt; the expression, by controlling when we open this envelope. We do this by using the &lt;code&gt;UQ()&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt; functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, &lt;code&gt;quosures&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;enquosures&lt;/code&gt; are ways to prevent R from looking up a variable’s value in our current environment (usually the global environment), and delay this lookup until we get them into the environment of interest. This might be one level down (in our function of interest), or several levels down (in a function called by our function).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is, R won’t open the envelope with our variable in it until we tell it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-should-i-care&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Should I Care????&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short answer: if you want to write functions that directly work with the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;, you need to understand &lt;code&gt;tidyeval&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to understand why you need to do this is to write a function that takes a &lt;code&gt;data.frame&lt;/code&gt; and a reference to a column within that &lt;code&gt;data.frame&lt;/code&gt;. You might notice that we can directly refer to a column in a &lt;code&gt;data.frame&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;select&lt;/code&gt;, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mtcars %&amp;gt;% select(cyl) %&amp;gt;% head(10)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##                   cyl
## Mazda RX4           6
## Mazda RX4 Wag       6
## Datsun 710          4
## Hornet 4 Drive      6
## Hornet Sportabout   8
## Valiant             6
## Duster 360          8
## Merc 240D           4
## Merc 230            4
## Merc 280            6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does that work? This is the power of NSE and tidy evaluation. Basically, by wrapping up &lt;code&gt;cyl&lt;/code&gt; in an envelope, we prevent R from &lt;em&gt;evaluating&lt;/em&gt; it right away. We can then pass the envelope into other functions, or environments, and then tell R to remove the envelope and then &lt;em&gt;evaluate&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s try and mimic this. We’ll write a function &lt;code&gt;grab_col(x, colname)&lt;/code&gt; which returns the values in the column whose name we ask for as an object. If we do this, without tidyeval, this will happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;grab_col &amp;lt;- function(x, colname){
  x %&amp;gt;%
    pull(colname)
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try running &lt;code&gt;grab_col(mtcars, colname=cyl)&lt;/code&gt;. You’ll get an error that &lt;code&gt;cyl&lt;/code&gt; does not exist as an object. Augh! This is harder than we thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can we fix this? We can wrap &lt;code&gt;colname&lt;/code&gt; up in an &lt;code&gt;enquosure&lt;/code&gt; using the &lt;code&gt;enquo()&lt;/code&gt; function. Once it’s into &lt;code&gt;pull()&lt;/code&gt;, we use &lt;code&gt;UQ()&lt;/code&gt; to open the envelope and R knows that it should look in the &lt;code&gt;data.frame&lt;/code&gt;’s environment for our &lt;code&gt;colname&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(rlang)

grab_col &amp;lt;- function(x, colname){
  ##wrap up colname in an enquosure
  cc &amp;lt;- rlang::enquo(colname)

  ##use UQ to evaluate it within the pull function
  x %&amp;gt;%
    pull(
      ## unquote and evaluate (open the envelope!)
      UQ(cc)
      )
}

grab_col(mtcars, colname=cyl)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  [1] 6 6 4 6 8 6 8 4 4 6 6 8 8 8 8 8 8 4 4 4 4 8 8 8 8 4 4 4 8 6 8 4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now try &lt;code&gt;grab_col(mtcars, colname=cyl)&lt;/code&gt;. Nifty, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;with-quosures-values-can-come-along-for-the-ride&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;With &lt;code&gt;quosure&lt;/code&gt;s, values can come along for the ride&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would we use &lt;code&gt;quosure&lt;/code&gt;s at all, instead of &lt;code&gt;enquosure&lt;/code&gt;s? Because with &lt;code&gt;quosure&lt;/code&gt;s we can actually bring some needed values along for the ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-about-lots-of-arguments&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What about lots of arguments?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what &lt;code&gt;quos()&lt;/code&gt; is for. Ever notice that you can specify a number of unnamed arguments by specifying a &lt;code&gt;...&lt;/code&gt; in your function definition? And did you ever notice that &lt;code&gt;select()&lt;/code&gt; can take lots of arguments such as &lt;code&gt;select(mpg, cyl, wt)&lt;/code&gt;? That is the power of &lt;code&gt;...&lt;/code&gt; combined with &lt;code&gt;quos()&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;quos&lt;/code&gt; takes a list and makes each element of the list a &lt;code&gt;quosure&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-about-expressions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What about expressions?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say we wanted to pass an expression such as &lt;code&gt;cyl &amp;gt; 2&lt;/code&gt; into our function. We’ll need to wrap it up in &lt;code&gt;enexpr()&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;enquo()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;filter_on_column &amp;lt;- function(x, col_expr){
  c_e &amp;lt;- rlang::enexpr(col_expr)

  x %&amp;gt;%
    ## The !! (called a bangbang) is just another way to use UQ()
    ## I don&amp;#39;t really like it, I&amp;#39;d rather use UQ()
    filter(!! c_e)
}

#pass in a simple expression
mtcars %&amp;gt;% filter_on_column(cyl &amp;gt; 2) %&amp;gt;% head(5)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##    mpg cyl disp  hp drat    wt  qsec vs am gear carb
## 1 21.0   6  160 110 3.90 2.620 16.46  0  1    4    4
## 2 21.0   6  160 110 3.90 2.875 17.02  0  1    4    4
## 3 22.8   4  108  93 3.85 2.320 18.61  1  1    4    1
## 4 21.4   6  258 110 3.08 3.215 19.44  1  0    3    1
## 5 18.7   8  360 175 3.15 3.440 17.02  0  0    3    2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#pass in a compound expression
mtcars %&amp;gt;% filter_on_column(cyl &amp;gt; 2 &amp;amp; qsec &amp;gt; 18) %&amp;gt;% head(5)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##    mpg cyl  disp  hp drat    wt  qsec vs am gear carb
## 1 22.8   4 108.0  93 3.85 2.320 18.61  1  1    4    1
## 2 21.4   6 258.0 110 3.08 3.215 19.44  1  0    3    1
## 3 18.1   6 225.0 105 2.76 3.460 20.22  1  0    3    1
## 4 24.4   4 146.7  62 3.69 3.190 20.00  1  0    4    2
## 5 22.8   4 140.8  95 3.92 3.150 22.90  1  0    4    2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;be-really-careful-with&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be really careful with &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above example, we used &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt;, called a bangbang, to unquote and evaluate our expression. Be really careful with what you put after the &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt;, since everything after it will be evaluated. If you have elements after the expression you don’t want to unquote, wrap the &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt; up in a set of parentheses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bang &amp;lt;- function(val2){
  x &amp;lt;- enquo(val2)
  return((!! x) + 10)
}

bang(5)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;other-applications&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the coolest applications of NSE is to write code that writes code. You have to be very careful with this, but it’s potentially really useful. On my list of things to do for my &lt;code&gt;flowDashboard&lt;/code&gt; package is to write code that generates a standalone app given the data objects you supply it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;appendix-what-is-a-quosure-really&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Appendix: What is a &lt;code&gt;quosure&lt;/code&gt;, really?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;for-more-information&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;For more information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this was helpful in understanding NSE and tidyeval. I find that sometimes I have to write things up so I more clearly understand it. So, if anything, writing this was useful for clarifying my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m indebted to Edwin Thoen’s code examples that helped me finally understand what’s going on with &lt;code&gt;tidyeval&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://edwinth.github.io/blog/dplyr-recipes/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://edwinth.github.io/blog/dplyr-recipes/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t really talk about Base-R’s NSE, but I would say that this should at least give you enough background to understand what’s going on there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Synthetic Data for Teaching Data Science</title>
      <link>/2017/12/14/using-synthetic-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/14/using-synthetic-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi Everyone, our paper called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/12/12/232611&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching data science fundamentals through realistic synthetic clinical cardiovascular data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is now available to read on Biorxiv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we talk about a dataset that we synthesized for teaching aspects of clinical data that may be tricky to understand in data science. This dataset is interesting because it&amp;rsquo;s derived from a multivariate distribution based on real patient data, modeled as a Bayesian Network. Even when we knew true marginals for the real data, there was a lot of fine tuning to the Bayesian Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve used this dataset for a couple of classes, and we&amp;rsquo;ve found that it helps highlight real issues in predictive modeling of clinical data. One of the largest is that most predictive models are based on a much older patient cohort (50+), which means that we don&amp;rsquo;t know much about how to predict cardiovascular risk in younger patients. Part of the teaching exercise is having the students choose a cohort of interest and then attempt to predict on that patient cohort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data is currently available as an R package here, including vignettes about how the data was generated: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/laderast/cvdRiskData&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/laderast/cvdRiskData&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Open Data Science Conference West 2017</title>
      <link>/2017/11/07/odsc-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/07/odsc-notes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I just came back from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://odscwest.pathable.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open Data Science Conference&lt;/a&gt; (ODSC) in San Francisco and I found it really stimulating and interesting. I learned a ton, met some great people working in very different fields, and overall found it quite worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the highlights from my notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;workshops&#34;&gt;Workshops&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/amueller/ml-training-intro&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;scikit-learn intro Workshop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/amueller/ml-training-advanced&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Advanced&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit that I am not really a Python person. But I am helping to develop some materials for an introductory workshop and I found this workshop and its materials to be a very beginner-friendly to &lt;code&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/code&gt; and machine learning concepts, much like &lt;code&gt;caret&lt;/code&gt; for R. All the slides and workshop materials are available at the above links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WinVector/ODSCWest2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SparklyR Workshop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked this workshop from John Mount of Win-Vector. It started out with a &lt;em&gt;dplyr&lt;/em&gt; intro, and introduced us to the basics of Apache Spark, which is a cluster-computing based machine learning framework, which is designed to do very large queries and machine learning. RStudio&amp;rsquo;s Edgar Ruiz managed to get us each an RStudio Pro Instance running on AWS with all the required packages installed so we could test out the SparklyR package, which uses dplyr&amp;rsquo;s commands to run Spark jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B3MFD2S4MhtGd1ltVHZkbFhHX0ZUbGlGZmtNRjllQ2NtQkJN/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;In-Memory Computing Essentials for Data Scientists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an introduction to Apache Ignite, which is a distributed, in-memory database that can be leveraged by different languages. The really interesting thing about Ignite is that it will colocate related data on the same cluster node, resulting in rapid queries within each node. I think this technology will become very important as we need more datasets to be openly accessible to compute on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;talks&#34;&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were the most interesting talks that I attended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mfviz.com/odsc-2017/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Visually Explaining Statistical and Machine Learning Concepts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a great talk by Mike Freedman about his process of how he put together D3.js based visualizations to explain some statistical concepts. I thought the explanation of his process (isolate specific ideas, identify data structures, leverage visualization algorithms). Check out the slides above. They&amp;rsquo;re very cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://odscwest.pathable.com/meetings/596522&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Wonder Twins: Data Science and Human Centered Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a really interesting talk about the interplay between data science and design in helping encourage a mobile money system in Tanzania. It was inspiring to see how they had both designers and data scientists embedded and looking at how the mobile payment system worked. One interesting example was doing network analysis of the Mobile Money Agents, who distribute cash. They targeted a highly influential group of these agents based on this analysis. Very cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://odscwest.pathable.com/meetings/601861&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The People&amp;rsquo;s Data&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://odscwest.pathable.com/meetings/604496&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Deontology of Data Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought these were really interesting sides about the human side of data science. DJ Patil, who was chief data scientist under the Obama administration, talked about citizen-driven data projects and how it enabled a number of advances. The most interesting case was basically a parent built an online community of people who had a very rare disease condition so he could help his son with the condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Igor Perisic (of LinkedIn) followed this with a talk about ethical issues in data science. In particular, he identified three different areas to concentrate on: 1) The Ethics of Data, 2) The Ethics of Algorithms, and 3) The Ethics of practice. He concentrated on the recent New York Times article about using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/01/us/politics/sent-to-prison-by-a-software-programs-secret-algorithms.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;machine learning to identify potential re-offenders in the prison system&lt;/a&gt;. The lack of transparency in how the algorithm identifies potential reoffenders is a huge ethical problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all, I had an interesting time and I met lots of people in industry, which was a nice contrast to the academic side of things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Separation of Code and State</title>
      <link>/2017/08/22/separation-of-code-and-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/22/separation-of-code-and-state/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the hardest concepts as an analyst that I have struggled with is separating my code from my data. A related issue is making your code reproducible across data instances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting useR 2017 Talks</title>
      <link>/2017/07/05/interesting-user2017talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/05/interesting-user2017talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I didn&amp;rsquo;t get to go to useR 2017 this year, I&amp;rsquo;m compiling the interesting talks. This is an ongoing list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqM/automatically-archiving-reproducible-studies-with-docker&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqM/automatically-archiving-reproducible-studies-with-docker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axq4/clouds-containers-and-r-towards-a-global-hub-for-reproducible-and-collaborative-data-science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axq4/clouds-containers-and-r-towards-a-global-hub-for-reproducible-and-collaborative-data-science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axq9/scraping-data-with-rvest-and-purrr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axq9/scraping-data-with-rvest-and-purrr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axq1/using-the-alphabetr-package-to-determine-paired-t-cell-receptor-sequences&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axq1/using-the-alphabetr-package-to-determine-paired-t-cell-receptor-sequences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqG/show-me-the-errors-you-didnt-look-for&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqG/show-me-the-errors-you-didnt-look-for&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqR/community-based-learning-and-knowledge-sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqR/community-based-learning-and-knowledge-sharing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqT/r-based-computing-with-big-data-on-disk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqT/r-based-computing-with-big-data-on-disk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqA/codebookr-codebooks-in-r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxqA/codebookr-codebooks-in-r&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axor/how-we-built-a-shiny-app-for-700-users&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/Axor/how-we-built-a-shiny-app-for-700-users&lt;/a&gt; Useful concepts: reactiveTrigger to force a rerender.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxsL/ensemble-packages-with-user-friendly-interface-an-added-value-for-the-r-community&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://user2017.sched.com/event/AxsL/ensemble-packages-with-user-friendly-interface-an-added-value-for-the-r-community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Not Be Afraid of Your Data</title>
      <link>/2017/06/28/howtonotbeafraid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/28/howtonotbeafraid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be giving a talk for the PDX RLang Meetup on July 11 called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.meetup.com/portland-r-user-group/events/240846589/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How to Not Be Afraid of Your Data: Teaching EDA using Shiny&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. Abstract below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many graduate students in the basic sciences are afraid of data exploration and cleaning, which can greatly impact their downstream analysis results. By using a synthetic dataset, some simple &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; commands, and a &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt; dashboard, we teach graduate students how to explore their data and how to handle issues that can arise (missing values, differences in units). For this talk, we&amp;rsquo;ll run through a simple EDA example (combining two weight loss datasets) with a general data explorer in &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt; that can be easily customized to teach specific EDA concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
